<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The glory of the B. Father S. Ignatius of Loyola, founder of the Society of Iesus.</title>
            <author>Łęczycki, Mikołaj, 1574-1652.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1633</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 207 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 181 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B00242</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 15188.7</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S120479</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99855675</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99855675</idno>
            <idno type="VID">174734</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B00242)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 174734)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 713:20, 2121:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The glory of the B. Father S. Ignatius of Loyola, founder of the Society of Iesus.</title>
                  <author>Łęczycki, Mikołaj, 1574-1652.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[10], 336 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>by John Cousturier,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At Rouen :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed MDC. XXXII. [1632 i.e. 1633]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>By Mikołaj Łęczycki.</note>
                  <note>Title and imprint from engraved title page. Actual publiction date from STC.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: The glory of S. Ignatius.</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 11921a on reel 713:20.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect; letterpress title page lacking.</note>
                  <note>Reproductions of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Ignatius, --  of Loyola, Saint, 1491-1556 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="engraved_title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:174734:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:174734:1"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <p>THE GLORY OF THE B. FATHER S. IGNATIVS OF LOYOLA, FOVNDER OF THE SOCIETY OF IESVS.</p>
                  <p>PRINTED MDC.XXXII.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>At Rou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>n by John <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>tu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>er. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>33.</hi>
                  </p>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="biography">
            <pb facs="tcp:174734:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:174734:2"/>
            <head>THE LIFE OF THE B. FATHER S. IGNATIVS OF LOYOLA <hi>FOVNDER OF</hi> THE SOCIETY OF IESVS.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>ND the glory he atchiued, through Gods aſſiſtance partly by his owne admirable
<pb facs="tcp:174734:3"/>ſanctity, confirmed by his miracles and Canoniza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; partly by the won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull holy life of <hi>S. Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis Xauerius,</hi> his aſsociate and ſpirituall child; partly by the many commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the <hi>Society</hi> he inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted, many wayes diuul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged by <hi>S. Tereſia;</hi> partly by <hi>S. Philip <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>erius</hi> his rare te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony of <hi>S. Ignatius:</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geather with the correſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pondency held betwixt him and the <hi>Society:</hi> &amp; par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tly by the knowne ſanctity of <hi>S. Charles Borromeus,</hi> mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raculouſly attained by the vſe of <hi>S. Ignatius</hi> his <hi>spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall Exerciſes,</hi> with his af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection
<pb facs="tcp:174734:3"/>and eſteeme of the <hi>Society.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The heads from whence ſuch things are deriued as this treatiſe maketh mention of, in the ſelfe-ſame words and phraſes of the Authours.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. The many proceſses for the Canonization of the <hi>SS. Ignatius</hi> and <hi>Xaue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius,</hi> contayning the graue teſtimonies of ſix hundred threeſcore &amp; fifteene wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſses, concerning the life and vertues of <hi>S. Ignatius</hi> alone.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The relations of the <hi>Auditours</hi> of the <hi>holy Rote,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:174734:4"/>deliuered in writing to the <hi>Pope,</hi> and gathered out of ſundry proceſſes made by autority of his <hi>Holines,</hi> for the Canonization of the <hi>Ss. Ignatius, Xauerius, Tereſia</hi> &amp; <hi>Phillip Nerius;</hi> receaued and approued by the Lords Cardinalls of the <hi>holy Rites</hi> (as they terme them)</p>
            <p n="3">3. The relations made in the name of the Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation of Cardinalls of the <hi>holy Rites</hi> (before our holy Father Pope <hi>Gregory</hi> the fifteenth, in a priuate <hi>Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory</hi>) by the right Honora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Lord Cardinall <hi>a Monte Franciſco Maria,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Portua,</hi> printed at <hi>Rome</hi> this
<pb facs="tcp:174734:4"/>preſent yeare, touching the life, ſanctity and mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles of the S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>Ignatius, Xa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerius, Tereſia</hi> and <hi>Phillip Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. The memorable things done by the SS. <hi>Igna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius, Xauerius, Tereſia, Phillip Nerius,</hi> &amp; <hi>Charles Borromaeus,</hi> publiſhed at <hi>Rome, Naples, Salamanca, Venice, Madrid, Antvverp, Collen, Ingolſtade, Dilinge, Ausbourg,</hi> &amp; other places, by permiſſion of ſuperiours.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Out of all vvhich heads this treatiſe vvas compiled at</hi> Cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couia, <hi>printed by</hi> Andrew Petriconius, <hi>vvith licence
<pb facs="tcp:174734:5"/>of Superiours, and intituled:</hi> The glory of the B. Father Saint Ignatius of Loyola, Founder of the Society of IESVS. <hi>Which copy</hi> wo <hi>follow.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div xml:lang="lat" type="approbation">
            <pb facs="tcp:174734:5"/>
            <head>APPROBATIO Cracouienſis.</head>
            <p>EGo Sebaſtianus Nucerinus San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctae Theologiae Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor, Eccleſiae Cathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dralis Cracouien: Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarius Conciona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, librorum in dioe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſi Craco. In lucem prodeu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tium Cenſor, fide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> preſentibus facio quia opuſculum hoc, <hi>de Gloria S. Ignatii Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yola,</hi> Fundatoris So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cietatis
<pb facs="tcp:174734:6"/>Ieſu, à Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus eiuſdem Societa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis prius relectum, vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di, ac deuoto ſtudio probaui: atque vt lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerna haec in cande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>labro, Eccleſiae typo poneretur poteſtate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> feci.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Crac. <date>6. Iulij, Anno 1622.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Sebaſtianus Nucerinus.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:174734:6"/>
            <head>THE GLORY OF St. IGNATIVS OF LOYOLA. Founder of the Society of IESVS.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>Of the Birth of <hi>S. Ignatius</hi> and of his Conuerſion to a good life.</head>
               <head type="sub">CHAPTER I.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>AINT <hi>Ignatius</hi> was borne in that part of Spaine (ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyning to the Pyrenan
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:174734:7"/>hills) which beareth the name of Biſcay, in the yeare 1461. His Father was <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trand Iannez</hi> Lord of <hi>Ognez</hi> and <hi>Loyola,</hi> of an ancient &amp; noble Family: His Mother, no way inferiour to her Huſband in worth and Nobility, was <hi>Mary Sa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>chez,</hi> deſcended of noble Pare<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, Lords of <hi>Balda.</hi> Both which families in Biſcay are of the number of them, to which the Spaniards giue the name and title of <hi>Great Ones.</hi> Theſe were the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents from whom <hi>S. Igna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius</hi> deſcended; who, being himſelf endowed with ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable parts of ſoule and
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:174734:7"/>body, &amp; hauing been bred a Page ſome tyme in the Court of King Ferdinand the Catholike, deſirous now to gaine himſelfe a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation by the warres, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tooke himſelf to Don An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonio Manriquez Duke of <hi>Naiara</hi> and Vice-Roy of <hi>Nauarre</hi> one who had been anciently allied with the family of <hi>Loyolaes;</hi> &amp; began to apply himſelfe wholy to the warres. But the Caſtle of <hi>P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>plona,</hi> the principall Citty of <hi>Nauarre</hi> (the defe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce of which was co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted to the charge of <hi>Ignatius</hi>) chancing to be beſieged by the French Army, a ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:174734:8"/>driuen out of the wall, by the force of the Artil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lery, wounded him in his left thigh, as he was ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing brauely at the head of his troupes, and ſo vtterly broke his right leg, that with the blow he fell halfe dead vpon the place, which hapned vpon whitſon: Munday, the 26. of May, in the yeare 1521. <hi>Ignatius</hi> being wounded, the Fort was taken by the French, by whom <hi>Ignatius</hi> was no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly treated, cured of his hurts, and ſent home. But whilſt yet he kept his bed, demaunding ſome propha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne Bookes to paſſe his ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:174734:8"/>two Bookes were brought vnto him; one, of the life of Chriſt, the other of his Saints; with the pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſall of which, he found himſelfe ſo touched, that to follow the ſtepps of Chriſt, he reſolued to leaue the world, and take a iour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney to <hi>Hieruſalem;</hi> there to confirme the Chriſtians in matters of ſpirit, and to conuert the Infidels to the Faith of Chriſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:174734:9"/>
               <head>The memorable things done by <hi>S. Ignatius,</hi> from the tyme of his conuerſion till his death.</head>
               <head type="sub">CHAPTER II.</head>
               <p>SAint <hi>Ignatius</hi> now cured of his hurts, bids adieu to his Pare<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, &amp; all world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſtractions, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the ſtrong oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of his Brother; and, being to ſerue from then<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce-forth vnder the colours of Chriſt, tooke his iour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney to the Monaſtery of the Benedictin Monks of <hi>Mont-ſerrata,</hi> where making
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:174734:9"/>a generall confeſſion of his ſinnes (a thing in thoſe dayes almoſt out of vſe) offering vp his ſword and dagger with which he ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued the world, in the Church of that Monaſtery he watched that whole night, being the Eue of the <hi>Saluation</hi> of our B. Lady, before the Altar of that ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Virgin, bare-headed, clad in a courſe long Caſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſacke, girt with a Cord, dedicating himſelfe there to the ſeruice of God, in the yeare 1522. from whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce he departed conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuing to yeild worthy fruits of pennance, in the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:174734:10"/>Hoſpital of <hi>Manreſa,</hi> and in a Caue neare the Riuer which waſheth the feilds therabouts, and arriued at laſt at <hi>Rome,</hi> in the yeare 1523. where, hauing had the bleſſing of Pope Adria<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the 4. he trauelled fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward towards <hi>Hieruſalem.</hi> But, not being able, for the imminent daunger and feare of the Turks, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayne there, and employ his endeauours in the gai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of ſoules, he returned into <hi>Spaine:</hi> where, that he might the better aſſiſt his neighbour in affayres of ſpirit, being now thirty yeares of age, he put him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:174734:10"/>to the Grammer-ſcho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le at <hi>Bercelona,</hi> ſpending afterwards, at <hi>Alcala</hi> a yea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re and a halfe in the ſtudies of Philoſophy and Diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity; and laſtly, in the ſpace of almoſt eight yeares, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de a repetition of theſe ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies at <hi>Paris,</hi> liuing vpon Almes, in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinuall works of Charity, Humility and Pennance; where by the example of his holy life, by his prayers &amp; ſpirituall diſcourſes, he gained to himſelfe Nine other Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panions, and amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ght them <hi>S. Francis Xauerius:</hi> Men fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous for their vertues, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion, and learning: And,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:174734:11"/>togeather with them made a vowe, that their courſe of ſtudies being ended, and all other reſpects ſet aſide, they would take their iourney to <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> and wholy apply themſelues there to the gaining of ſou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les: but if, within a yeares ſpace, they ſhould light v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon no commodity of ſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping, or ſhould not be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to remayne at <hi>Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem;</hi> that then, their vowe being diſpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſed with, they ſhould repaire to <hi>Rome</hi> offering their ſeruice to his Holines, for the ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall good of their neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours. But he himſelfe ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:174734:11"/>contracted a grieuous payne in his ſtomacke, by his continuall &amp; laborious watchings and ſtudies, and hauing (with the, reſt of his Companions, after a ſtrict examen, demaunded by themſelues, and graun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted them) been honoured with the degree of Doctor in that Vniuerſity; at laſt, by the counſell of his Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panions, and aduiſe of Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitians, he returned to his natiue Country: Where, after the working of many miracles, when he had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couered his health, he too<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke his iourney towards <hi>Venice,</hi> whether the reſt of
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:174734:12"/>his Companio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, by agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, were likewiſe to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paire, and in that Citty was preferred to the dignity of Preiſthood. But the yeare aboue mentioned being now expired, and their embarquing for <hi>Paleſtin</hi> cut off by reaſon of the warres broken fort betwixt the Turke and the Venetians, he, with his Companions came to <hi>Rome,</hi> in the yeare 1537. At <hi>Rome,</hi> he preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted his ſeruice to his Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, for the gaining of his neighbour. The Pope ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proued the pious reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of theſe Fathers, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claming many ſoules by
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:174734:12"/>the induſtry of S. <hi>Ignatius,</hi> and his ſpirituall exerciſes; and placed two of <hi>Ignatius,</hi> his Companions in the Roman Vniuerſity (com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly knowne by the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me of <hi>Sapientia</hi>) there to read the publike lectures of Scripture and ſchoole Diuinity. Meane while S. <hi>Ignatius</hi> inſtituted the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety of IESVS, for the defence and propagation of the Faith, and the gai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of ſoules; and procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to haue it ratified by the Sea Apoſtolike, in the yeare 1540. in which So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety, beſides the three vowes common to it with
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:174734:13"/>other Orders, he added a fourth vowe, by which, promiſe is made to obey his Holines, in vnderta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king iourneyes to the Turks and Infidels, for the gaining of ſoules, without demaunding any ſtipend or prouiſion for that iour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney. Which done, he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed the Conſtitutions of the Society, directed by ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable Diuine inſpiratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s (as ſhall hereafter be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared) And being himſelf, by the vniforme conſent of his Companions, choſen General of the Order, after he had gouerned it with an admirable reputation of
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:174734:13"/>wiſdome and ſanctity, for the ſpace of fifteene yeares, three monethes and nine dayes, and diſperſed wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neare a thouſand of his So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety, in almoſt a hundred ſeuerall Colledges, ouer the whole world; not only in <hi>Italy, Spaine, France,</hi> and <hi>Germany,</hi> but euen in the <hi>Eaſt</hi> and <hi>vveſt Indies, Iapo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia, Braſil, Ethiopia &amp; Perſia;</hi> infinite multitudes of peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple being conuerted by him, and his, to the true Faith, and good life; ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing inſtituted many <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>gs for the good of t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oly Church; brought to a c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome the often frequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:174734:14"/>of Sermons, Lectures, Maſſes, Confeſſion and Communion, in <hi>Rome</hi> firſt, and afterwards in other places of the world; ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, by theſe meanes, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couered the ſubtility of the Diuell, and ſet a new luſtre vpon the face of the Church: he ended his dayes of a gentle ague, full of merites, ſtrengthned with the Popes bleſſing, and the Sacraments, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the rites of the Church and gaue vp his Ghoſt moſt peaceably, into the hands of his Creatour, inuoking the name of IESVS, in the yeare 1556.
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:174734:14"/>the laſt day of Iuly, the 65. yeare of his age, famous for his holy life, and miracles, as wel in his life tyme, as after his deceaſe; and for other rare endowments (of which we now treate.)</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>The gift of Prophecy in <hi>S. Ignatius</hi> moſt perfect.</head>
               <head type="sub">CHAP. III.</head>
               <p>BEcauſe the gift of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecy, in compariſon of ſupernaturall vertues, is eſteemed one of the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary or meaneſt ornaments of Sanctity, and therfore to be attained without gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:174734:15"/>or Gods frie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dſhip, from thence I thought good to begin the prayſes of S. <hi>Ignatius.</hi> And for as much as by the Spirit of Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, many things not ſubiect to our ſenſes are diſcoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and things yet to come are infallibly foretould, the ſecrets of mens harts are layd open, and, which is more admirable &amp; rare, the very ſecrets of Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty God, ſurpaſſing human vnderſtanding, are perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctly vnderſtood; all theſe things were in S. <hi>Ignatius</hi> in as eminent degree. The very firſt yeare, immedia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tely after his conuerſion,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:174734:15"/>Almighty God began ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirably to enlighten his vnderſtanding: for going for deuotion ſake to viſit a Church of S. Paul the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle, without the Towne of <hi>Manreſa,</hi> &amp; reſting him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe in his iourney neare the Riuer <hi>Rubricate,</hi> which ru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes through that Towne vpon a ſuddaine, a certaine diuine light ſhined ſo clea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re vpon him, that by that, without the helpe of any Maſter, he perfectly vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood many things, not only of the myſteries of Chriſtian beliefe, but of the moſt ſubtile queſtions and opinions of Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phy,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:174734:16"/>as perfectly as if they had been preſented to his view in ſome curious loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king glaſſe; myſteryes, which other me, after long reading and paynes, hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly comprehend. In which celeſtiall viſion he remay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned a long ſpace, not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out infinite comfort and conſolation of mynd. Ar other tymes alſo, by cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne ſecret ſignes and my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall examples, the order, that great workeman ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued in the Frame of this world, was repreſented vnto him, which myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryes, as in themſelues they ſurpaſſe the forces of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:174734:16"/>vnderſtanding, ſo S. <hi>Ignatius</hi> afterwards affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, that it was a thing not poſſible to gheſſe at them, much leſſe to expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe and make them vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood to life. And of this kind, about the ſame tyme, he miraculouſly came to to the knowledge many other things. By which di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine fauours he was ſo far forth confirmed in Faith, that though no other mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numents had been extant of Chriſtian Religion, yet by theſe only myſteryes, miraculouſly reuealed to him, he would haue been moſt ready to giue his life
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:174734:17"/>for the Catholike truth. In which reſpect S. <hi>Ignatius</hi> may well apply to him ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fe thoſe words of S. Paul: <hi>For neither haue I receaued it from men, neither haue I lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned it, but by the reuelation of Chriſt Ieſus.</hi> Which extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary manner of faith in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed in S. <hi>Ignatius</hi> whilſt yet he was vnlearned, as well the Auditours of the holy Rote, as the Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalls of the holy Rites, par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly noted in their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations to his Holines. His courſe of ſtudies being en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, at <hi>Venice,</hi> in his retire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to <hi>Vicenza,</hi> and in his iourney to <hi>Rome,</hi> he often
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:174734:17"/>receaued ſo many diuine reuelations, and ſo abſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te and perfect content and conſolation, that he ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med not only to be reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red againe, but to be reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with aduantage to the ſtate, in which he had for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly found himſelfe at <hi>Manreſa</hi> (which place for the ſingular fauours ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him there by Almighty God, he was wont, in a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious merriment, to ſtile his primatiue Church) At ſuch tyme as he compoſed the Conſtitutions of the Society, amongſt other things, he principally re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaued reuelations of the
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:174734:18"/>myſtery of the B. Trinity, of the diuine Eſſence, of the diſtinction &amp; proprie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the perſons; and this in a way of vnderſtanding ſo plaine, ſo perfect, and ſo beyond the iudgement of the ſenſes, that as he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe confeſſeth, in a little treatiſe found after his death, of his owne hand writing, it had been im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible for him, in many yeares ſtudy to haue attai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the like knowledge. And, in an other booke he left writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that he though it impoſſible in this life, to arriue to a more perfect knowledge and vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:174734:18"/>of myſteries, then Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God, in a certaine viſion, had been pleaſed to reueale to him; Which of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten reuelations, intermin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gled with a kind of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakeable delectation, were wont to poſſeſſe his vnderſtanding, not for a ſhort ſpace, but often-ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes for many dayes togea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; ſo that, whether-ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer he went, whether he were in his chamber, in the Refectory, whether at home, or abroad, they euer accompanied, and as it we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, watched with him; with the vehemency of which he was often ſo tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſported,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:174734:19"/>and did ſo looſe himſelfe, that he ſeemed in ſpirit euer to be in Heauen, in body only vpon Earth. Moreover, the very firſt yeare after his conuerſion, whilſt he liued at <hi>Manreſa,</hi> the principall points of the Society he was to Inſtitute, and ſuch things eſpecially, by which the Society dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fereth from other Orders, were reuealed to him by Almighty God, as he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe acknowledged to Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Iames Laynez,</hi> one of the firſt of his Society, and other graue Fathers: who, when they demaunded of him, for what cauſe he or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:174734:19"/>ſome things in the Society, differing from the cuſtomes of other Orders; he yeelding them a parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular reaſon for each thing they demaunded; in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion was wont to place the force of all his reaſons, in thoſe admirable inſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, miraculouſly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed vpon him at <hi>Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſa,</hi> and the recollection he made there, in which Almighty God ſealed and imprinted in his mind moſt manifeſt and euident notions of all theſe things. At his departure out of <hi>Spaine,</hi> giuing ſome good precepts to one <hi>Iohn Paſcall</hi>
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:174734:20"/>at that tyme but a youth, for the reſt of his life to come; and being asked of the youth, what would be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come of him? take hart child, quoth he, when thou groweſt elder thou ſhalt marty, and haue thy ſhare of many troubles, which ſhall hinder thee from bei<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſported with pleaſures, or being ſlack in imploring the aſſiſtance of God: And ſo it fell out. It was mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culouſly reuealed to him, that one of his companio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, taken with a ſolitary life, caſting with himſelfe how to forſake the Society, was affrighted, by Gods per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:174734:20"/>with an ill Spirit. One <hi>Peter Ferrus,</hi> a Patauian borne, liyng ſick, paſt hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man hope of recouery, was certainely foretould by S. <hi>Ignatius</hi> that by the helpe of the Mother of God; he ſhould ſhortly recouer: the night following the ſick man; expecting with deuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, what would become of him, the Mother of God, accompained with a glorious traine of Virgins, preſented her ſelfe to him, and by giuing him her pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture, reſtored him his health: The day following, <hi>Ignatius</hi> returning, with a countenance more chere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:174734:21"/>the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ordinary, not being ignorant of what had paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, found Peter recouered and ſaid vnto him: Did not I tell thee that the Mother of God would recouer thee? The death of <hi>Agnes Paſchalis,</hi> who ended her dayes moſt holily at <hi>Berce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lona,</hi> was miraculouſly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uealed to him at <hi>Rome;</hi> ſo that the letters of <hi>Antony Araozius,</hi> one who was preſent at that widdowes death, brought him after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards no newes of it. At <hi>Antvverp,</hi> long before the founding of the Society of IESVS, he foretould one <hi>Peter Quadratus,</hi> a Spaniard,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:174734:21"/>that he ſhould one day be the founder of a Colledge of the Society: and ſo it fell out: for he afterwards, with <hi>Francis Manionia</hi> his wife, fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded the Colledge of <hi>Medina del Campo.</hi> He fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retould one <hi>Simon Rodriguez</hi> that infallibly he ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couer and eſcape that ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. It was miraculouſly diſcouered to S. <hi>Ignatius</hi> that a certaine perſon, not long before admitted into the Society, being ſo mole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted with an office impoſed vpon him, that he could not take his reſt, or ſleep in the night tyme, &amp; therfore began to thinke of retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:174734:22"/>back into the world the Saint commaunded the party to be called to him in the night tyme out of his bed, diſcouering to him, by little and little his moſt ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cealed thoughts, &amp; with an admirable dex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terity quieted his troubled mind. The like charitable offices, with the like in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſight, he performed to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny others, who not being able through their igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, to make knowne their diſeaſes, he diſcoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the nature &amp; cauſes of them preſcribing remedies for them. He foretould one <hi>Stephen Baroellus</hi> lying dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerouſly
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:174734:22"/>ſick, that he ſhould not dye of that diſeaſe, who preſently after recouered to the admiration of all me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. His Companions at <hi>Venice</hi> finding ſtrong oppoſition by many powerfull ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myes, and being halfe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolued to let their buſines dye, informed S. <hi>Ignatius</hi> of the danger they flood in; who returned anſwer, wis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hing them they should not forſake the cauſe of Chriſt, for by his aſſiſtance they should bring their buſines to their deſired iſſuë: which promiſe did not faile them; for within eight dayes af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, a ſentence was giuen to
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:174734:23"/>their aduantage, almoſt by the vniforme conſent of the Senate: a thing eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med no ſmall miracle by men of vnderſtanding, that two ſtrange and vnkown Fathers of the Society, and they of the Spaniſh nation, ſhould be able to conteſt with the fauour and riches of the moſt eminent Citti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens of that Citty. He fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tould <hi>Don Fraciſco de Borgia,</hi> whilſt he was yet Duke of <hi>Gandia,</hi> and <hi>F. Iames Laynez,</hi> that they ſhould one day be Generalls of the Society of <hi>Ieſus<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> He diſcouered to <hi>Michael Arrouira,</hi> whilſt he was yet a youth, the moſt
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:174734:23"/>inward ſecrets of his hart about a marriage he then intended, with many miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries that were to befall him. I omit other examples of his ſpirit of prophecy, too long to be mentioned in this ſhort abridgement.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>The manifold and often viſions of <hi>S. Ignatius.</hi>
               </head>
               <head type="sub">CHAP. IV.</head>
               <p>FOR as much as cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiall viſions haue a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendency of the Spirit of prophecy, this is a fit place to make mention of them: not that the Sanctity of
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:174734:24"/>Gods ſeruants is diriued from them, ſeeing it may be, &amp; is often tymes found without them, but becauſe they are alſo certaine orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Sanctity: &amp; ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſome rehearſall is to be made of them: for with theſe alſo, in as eminent a degree as may be attayned in this life, Bleſſed S. <hi>Igna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius</hi> was plentifully ſtored.</p>
               <p>The friſt viſion he had, was of S. <hi>Peter</hi> the Apoſtle, who reſtored him to health, when the Phiſicians had giuen him ouer: for, it pleaſed his Diuine Maieſty to haue him reſtored to health by the cheife Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtour
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:174734:24"/>(vnder Chriſt) and Prince of his Church, whom, in a manner pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portionable to his diuine prouidence, he had choſen for a ſpeciall Champion &amp; enlarger of the ſame. Lying awake one night, ſick in his Fathers houſe, the <hi>B. Virgin Mary,</hi> appeared to him, with her little Infant IESVS, in a bright and glorious ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ner: not ſhewi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g her ſelfe ſlightly, but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayning long in his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence: with which he was ſo taken, that immediately he conceaued a ſenſible hatred of all ſuch things, as blind mortall men
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:174734:25"/>hould moſt in eſteeme, and of thoſe things eſpecially, which carry with them any ſhew of vnlawfull delight: ſo that fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thence-forward, the remembrance of them, how deeply ſoeuer, by long vſe and cuſtome, rooted in his imagination, was vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly extinct in him, &amp; waſhed away.</p>
               <p>At other tymes, in like manner, the Mother of God often ſhewed her ſelfe to S. <hi>Ignatius,</hi> but principal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly whilſt he compoſed the Conſtitutions of the Socie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, either offering vp her prayers, and comforting him with her preſence, or
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:174734:25"/>confirming the Conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions he wrote of the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety. Beſides, Chriſt our Sauiour himſelfe vouchſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fed often to comfort him with his deſired preſence, at <hi>Manreſa,</hi> and other pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. In his iourney to <hi>Veni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce,</hi> being left behind by his fellow-trauellers, in certai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne meddowes neare the Riuer <hi>Po,</hi> not being able, through weakenes, to hould on his iourney with them; our Sauiour Chriſt (as he had often done) ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared vnto him the next night, and hauing excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly encouraged him, conducted him, the direct
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:174734:26"/>way, to the Towne of <hi>Padua</hi> firſt, and after wards to <hi>Venter.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In his ſea-voyage to <hi>Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem,</hi> our B. Sauiour of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten appeared to him, to his infinite incouragement, and conducted him at laſt to a ſafe Hauen in <hi>Paleſtine.</hi> At <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> being reuiled with opprobrious words, by a certayne Armenian, who laying violent hands vpon him, dragged him, in an iniurious manner to his Inne: in the midſt of theſe affronts, he behold our Sauiour preſent with him, accompanying him, in his iniuryes, to his great
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:174734:26"/>contentment.</p>
               <p>As he trauelled to <hi>Rome,</hi> with his two Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, to found the Socie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, he entred into a certai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne Church) of which the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re are many ſtanding v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the high way not far from the Citty) to perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me ſome deuotio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s; &amp; being (as he was accuſtomed rapt into an <hi>Extaſie.</hi> and tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſpor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in <hi>Contemplation, God the Father appeared to him in a glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious light, with his B. ſonne bearing his Croſſe, making shew of the bitter</hi> pangs and torments he endured who commending S. <hi>Ignatius</hi> with his Companions to
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:174734:27"/>his Father; God the Father, when he had graciouſly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaued them to his prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, turning to the Saint, with a cherefull browe, wouchſafed to vtter theſe comfortable words: <hi>Ego vobis Romae propitius ero:</hi> And this was the cheife cauſe, that, after the Confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of te Society, <hi>S. Igna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius</hi> impoſed vpon it the ſoueraigne name of <hi>Ieſus.</hi> Beſides, the writers of his life affirme, that he had of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten viſions of the Diuine perſons, ſometymes all to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geather, at other tymes only ſome one of the alone, and of the diuine Eſſence it
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:174734:27"/>ſelfe; and theſe things eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially at the ſacrifice of the Maſſe, and at ſuch tyme, as being buſy with compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the Conſtitutions of the Society, he implored the light and approbation of the diuine Wiſdome. This appeareth euidently, by a large volume of his viſions, which, for piety and memory ſake, himſelfe tooke the paynes to reduce to a methode: which vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions in him were ſo admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, and ſo penetrating the profoundeſt myſteries of the diuine Eſſence, that the moſt learned and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Doctours of myſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:174734:28"/>and ſchole-Diuinity of our age, doubt not to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe in their printed books that if that opinion be true, which, with <hi>Saint Thomas</hi> and other Fathers of the Church, many men fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, that <hi>Moyſes</hi> and S. <hi>Paul</hi> the Apoſtle, euen in this life, though for a ſhort ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me, beheld perfectly, and not in a figure, (as the Saints in the next life do) the diuine Eſſence, and as other moderne writers be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leiue of S. <hi>Auſien,</hi> S. <hi>Bennet,</hi> and <hi>S Giles,</hi> Companion to <hi>S. F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ancis;</hi> the like perfect viſion of God, euen in this life, may probably be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leiued
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:174734:28"/>to haue been ſeene by S. <hi>Ignatius,</hi> who hath left behind him, of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, with his owne hand writing, that at ſuch tyme as he wrote the Rules of the Society, he often be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held the diuine <hi>Eſſence,</hi> and <hi>Be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> And, before he had ſtudied, being yet vtterly vnlearned, he was in ſo ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable a manner, inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, by intellectuall vi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>s, in matters of the Vnity of the Eſſence, and Trinity of the Perſons, that in that Nonage of his conuerſion, he was able to compoſe a Booke of the B. Trinity.</p>
               <p>That famous viſion of
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:174734:29"/>the holy Ghoſt is not to be omitted, who appeared to <hi>S. Ignatius</hi> whilſt he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed the Conſtitutions of the Society, ſometymes in that admirable faſhion of fiery flames, as heretofore to the Apoſtles, ſometymes in other ſhapes. Beſides all which, it was a thing vſual to this glorious Saint, to be comforted with frequent viſions of Saints &amp; Angels.</p>
               <p>At ſuch tyme as he mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred the Spirituall exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe, in <hi>Mont Caſsino,</hi> to one <hi>Peter Ortizius</hi> an Agent of the Emperours, praiyng earneſtly for the health of <hi>B. Hoſius</hi> his Companion
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:174734:29"/>(whom he knew to ly grieuouſly ſick) he ſuddai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nely ſaw (a thing reported to haue hapned to <hi>S. Bennet,</hi> in the ſame place, at the ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me of the deceaſe of <hi>German</hi> the Biſhop) the ſoule of his Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>panion, ſhining wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous bright, carried vp by Angels, &amp; enter into Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen.</p>
               <p>And not long after, going one day to the Altar; in the very <hi>Introite</hi> of his Maſſe, imploring the aide of all the Saints a glorious Squa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dron of Saints appeared before him, amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt whom he perfectly ſaw <hi>B. Hoſius,</hi> in a moſt glorious manner.
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:174734:30"/>With which two viſions he was ſo ouerioyed, that for many dayes after, he could not containe himſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fe from weeping.</p>
               <p>When Father <hi>Iohn Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>durius,</hi> one of the firſt Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, lay in daunger of his life, with a violent ſicknes, S. <hi>Ignatius</hi> intending to offer vp the holy Sacrifice of the Maſſe for him, at S. <hi>Peters in Mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>te Aure<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>;</hi> in his iourney thither, being almoſt halfe way ouer the bridge <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iculus</hi> common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly knowen now by the name of <hi>Po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>e Six<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi>) he caſt vp and fixed his eyes vpon the heauens, and behold
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:174734:30"/>the ſoule of <hi>F. Iohn Codu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius</hi> gloriouſly carried vp amongſt the Quires of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels; &amp; turning afterwards to <hi>F Baptiſta Viola</hi> his Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panion: <hi>let vs,</hi> quot he, <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne home, for our Codurius is deceaſed.</hi> At an other tyme, whilſt he was writing the Rules of the Society, he behold the Saints, in their glory, in ſo Maieſticall a faſhion, as he confeſſed, was not to be expreſſed. And whilſt he was buſy with the ſame Rules, he often heard, not with the eares of his vndeſtanding only, but with the eares
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:174734:31"/>of his body, moſt harmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious muſicke from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, with which he was enflamed with diuine loue, and melted into teares.</p>
               <p>The yeare after his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſion, being preſent at Maſſe, in the Dominicans Church; at the eleuation of the ſacred Hoſt, he perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſaw, that vnder that figu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, true God and man was really contained.</p>
               <p>At ſuch tyme as hee com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed the Conſtitutions of his Society, hauing one day conſecrated the holy Hoſt, and offered to Almighty God the Rules of his Socie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; God the Father appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:174734:31"/>moſt graciouſly vnto him, inſinuating by ſome myſticall ſignification, that it would be a thing plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to his diuine Maieſty, that the Mother of God ſhould offer vp her prayers vnto him, for him: Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon the B. Virgin ſuddai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nely appeared, recommen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding <hi>S. Ignatius</hi> to the eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall Father, and demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrating that her owne fleſh was there preſent in the Euchariſt, in the fleſh of her ſonne.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:174734:32"/>
               <head>The Books vvhich <hi>S, Ignatius</hi> compoſed, by diuine inspiration.</head>
               <head type="sub">CHAPTER V.</head>
               <p>IT ſeemeth not imperti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent to make mention, in this place, of certaine books of S. <hi>Ignatius,</hi> writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, out of doubt, by diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne inſpiration, as things depending and belonging to the Spirit of prophecy. For though al the writings and Epiſtles of S. <hi>Ignatius,</hi> carry with them a more then ordinary reliſh of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine wiſdome, yet ſome of them in particular, haue a
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:174734:32"/>more perfect taſt of it.</p>
               <p>The firſt booke he wrot, in the firſt yeare of his Conuerſion, whilſt yet he was ignorant of his Gram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer-rules, was that of the B. Trinity, conſiſting wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neare of eight hundred lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues. In which, after that glorious viſion, mentioned in the former Chapter, he expreſſeth this great miſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, (how ſoeuer in a home<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſtile) with ſuch admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble variety of ſimilies and exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ples, that all men, with whom afterwards he diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſed of that ſubiect, ſtood in admiration, and aſtoniſhement of it.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="52" facs="tcp:174734:33"/>About the ſame tyme, in like manner, whilſt he was yet vnlearned, by the reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations of Almighty God, and inſtructions of the B. Virgin, he wrot an other booke of Spirituall Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſes: in which, beſides other excellent admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, he preſcribeth, with admirable dexterity and methode, diuers manners of prayer and contempla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, fit for reformation of manners, and progreſſe in vertue; he giueth Rules for the Examination of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience; and rooting out of vice: for diſtinguiſhing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt great and leſſe offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces:
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:174734:33"/>for reſtraining the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridled paſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of the mi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d; for diſcerning the motions of the good, from them of the bad Spirit: for the good choiſe of a ſtate of life, and directing that choiſe by the rule of Gods will: for the expulſion of ſcruples: and in concluſion, giueth nota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble precepts for the diſcer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of Spirits. This was that booke which gained thoſe firſt Fathers of the Society, and amongſt them <hi>S. Francis Xauerius;</hi> which hath ſtored many Monaſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryes with famous men; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed many Religious perſons wauering in their
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:174734:34"/>good purpoſes; reclaimed many diſſolute people to a reformed diſcipline; and in fine, brought infinite multitudes of ſecular and Eccleſiſticall perſons, through the Chriſtian world, to a reformation of their lewd liues, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uancement of their good; amongſt whom, to omit many of leſſe remarke, one of the cheife is, that great light of the Church, and patterne of Paſtours, S. <hi>Charles Borom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>us,</hi> Cardinall and Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Millay,</hi> who drew thoſe firſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginnings of his vertuous life, from theſe Excerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:174734:34"/>of S. <hi>Ignatius,</hi> which all his life tyme after, he ſo reuerenced and eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, that at firſt once a yeare, afterwards, till his dying day, twice euery yeare, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e was wont to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke vſe of them; ſo to ſtir himſelfe vp to vertue, and a holy gouernment of his Church; and with them laſtly he prepared himſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fe for his laſt agony and death. No marueile them, if euen in the life tyme of S. <hi>Ignatius,</hi> theſe Exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes were wonderfully ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted by all ſuch, as had the charge of reuiewing them, &amp; confirmed by the
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:174734:35"/>Bull of <hi>Paulus tertius</hi> ſupre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me Paſtour of the Church, without altering a tittle of them; and, recommended by him for a worke full of piety and Religion, and moſt profitable and vſefull for the ſpirituall good of ſoules; &amp; by the Auditours of the holy Rote, and Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinalls of the holy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es, acknowledged for things not proceeding from the art, or inuention of any man, but from ſome ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naturall light infuſed from Heauen.</p>
               <p>The third Booke S. <hi>Igna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius</hi> publiſhed, which whilſt he wrote, he was ſo admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:174734:35"/>enlightned, and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured with ſuch glorious celeſtiall apparitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, as hath been ſaid, was that of his Conſtitutions of the Socie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Ieſus, diuided into ten parts; a worke much larger then any of the reſt: which euen in the iudgement of ſome Heretiks, into whoſe hands it often falleth, ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting a ſide the doctrine of Faith, and Eccleſiaſticall ceremonies contained in it, is eſteemed a rate <hi>Peece,</hi> and a thing ſurpaſſing human wiſdome, being a liuely patterne of a perfect and well gouerned Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, And of many holy
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:174734:36"/>and learned men, it is held a peece of work, deſeruing high eſteeme, for the depth of diuine wiſdome contayned in it, and for the excellent doctrine, full of Chriſtian and Religious perfections; and therfore, with good cauſe, appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued by many Popes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>The guifts of a gloriſied Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy miraculouſly beſtovved vppon <hi>S. Ignatius,</hi> in his life tyme.</head>
               <head type="sub">CHAP. 6.</head>
               <p>AMongſt the infallible ſignes of the true
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:174734:36"/>Church of Chriſt, ſome graue Ecleſiaſticall wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, learnedly and piouſly recken t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e endowments of glorified bodyes, in a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion befitting the ſtate of this life, miraculouſly beſtowed vpon ſome children of the Church, famous for their holy liues: amongſt whom they name <hi>B S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>gnatius.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is euident, by the te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonyes of many graue witneſſes, that his body, in this life, was endowed with the guiſt of <hi>Clarity:</hi> for his head and face was of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten ſeene shining in a glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ner: ſo he was ſene
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:174734:37"/>by one <hi>Iſabel Roſella,</hi> at <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celona,</hi> whilſt he was hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring a Sermon in the Church, amongſt the vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar ſort of people: ſo one Iohn Paſchall ſaw him: &amp; ſo he was beheld by them of the hoſpitall whilſt he liued amongſt them. And at <hi>Rome.</hi> by <hi>Alexander Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tronius,</hi> by Father <hi>Oliuier Manare,</hi> and Father <hi>Levvis Gonzaluo;</hi> who, whenſoeuer he came to <hi>Saint Ignatius,</hi> praying in his chamber (which he had often occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to do) he euer beheld him ſhining with moſt glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious beames. And <hi>S. Philip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus Nerius,</hi> a man of won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:174734:37"/>holy life, and a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliar acquaintance of S. <hi>Ignatius,</hi> was a cuſtomed to ſay, that S. <hi>Ignatius</hi> was a man of that Sanctity, that the interiour beauty of his ſoule ſhewed it ſelfe exte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riourly in him; from whoſe eyes and countenance he profeſſeth often to haue ſeene glorious beames, and rayes of brightnes to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed.</p>
               <p>Concerning the guift of <hi>Impaſsibility,</hi> his ſeauen dayes faſts, without taking any ſuſtinance, accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied, either with a violent extaſie (a thing which much impaireth the forces of the
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:174734:38"/>body) or with a cruelle whipping of his body thri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce a day, and many howers ſpent vpon his knees in prayer, without any wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rines, or tiring of his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, do euidently shew it.</p>
               <p>The guift of <hi>Subtility</hi> was miraculouſly graun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to him, when in his life tyme, at the ſelfe ſame mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment or inſtant of tyme, he was perfectly ſeene in bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, at <hi>Rome</hi> and at <hi>Coller,</hi> two places aboue nine hundred miles diſtant from each other, as ſhalbe rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the ſix tee<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>th chapter.</p>
               <p>And that he was often in his prayers lifted from the
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:174734:38"/>ground, was an euident ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gne in him of the guift of <hi>Agility.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>Of the wrtues, and ſupernatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall guifts of <hi>S. Ignatius,</hi> in generall.</head>
               <head type="sub">CHAP. 7.</head>
               <p>BEfore our abridge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the vertues of S. <hi>Ignatius</hi> in particular, ſome what is to be ſaid of his ſupernaturall guifts in generall, by which it will appeare, that he was rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, by the hand of God, to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> rate and eminent degree of Sanctity ſo to
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:174734:39"/>proue a fitter inſtrument to communicate ſo great be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits to the vniuerſall Church of Chriſt. And, as to the comfort and profit of the Church, the diuine prouidence hath moued other great Saints, for ſome particular good end, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare ingenuouſly, though with ſubmiſſion, to their deareſt friends, their moſt concealed and moſt nota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſupernaturall endow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, as we read in their liues; ſo the ſame prouiden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce hath wrought out of the ſecrets of <hi>S. Ignatius,</hi> and procured from his owne vnqueſtionable, and won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:174734:39"/>circumſpect rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, many arguments and tokens of the great fauours of God. He was earneſtly wont to labour, dayly to make ſome new ſtep in the way of vertue, with this only ayme, that he might euer preſent his diuine Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſty with ſome encreaſe of glory. To which purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe, following the Counſell of S. <hi>Iohn Chriſoſtome</hi> and S. <hi>Iohn Climacus,</hi> like a proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Banker, he compared the day preſent with the day paſt, and the profit of one day with that of the other. And, howbeit it is a rare thing for men of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:174734:40"/>life, not to looſe of their firſt ſeruour; and more admirable, by reſpires, if not vvithout in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termiſſion to aduaunce in the vvay of vertue, and moſt of all to be admired, continually and vvithout pauſes o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>terims to profit: yet S. <hi>Ignatius</hi> did not only not make a dayly increaſe in vertue, but comparing the profit of the day preſent vvith that of the day paſt, found and confeſſed that he dayly aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, &amp; vvas more and more en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flamed vvith deſire of Gods ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice: ſo far-forth, that in his old age, he vvas vvont to terme the ſtate he found himſelfe in, at <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> [in vvhich place he had the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſo many glorious fauours, as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> been ſaid before] his firſt Rudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, &amp; as it vvere, his rough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſting, vvhich Almighty God
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:174734:40"/>dayly poliſhed &amp; perfected in him. So that in <hi>S. Ignatius,</hi> that vnqueſtionable doctrine of <hi>S. Thomas</hi> hath place, vvho affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth 2.2 q. 161. art. 3. <hi>That they vvho principate of the guifts of God, knovv they are endovved vvith them; according to that of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 2 <hi>That vve may knovv that of God they are beſtovved vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs.</hi> In vvhich reſpect S. <hi>Vertha,</hi> in the te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>th Chapter of her life, vvith good cauſe termeth it an adulterate humility, vvhich doth not acknovvledge the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uours of God. And this doth e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly ſhevv the excellency of <hi>S. Ignatius</hi> his vertues, that he found the mercy and fauours of Almighty God tovvards him to be ſuch, that by hovv much the more he ſeemed to vvan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, and deſire amendment, by ſo much more liberall Almighty God vvas vvith him, and caſt
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:174734:41"/>vpon him more bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tifully the treaſures of his ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. Wherfore he profeſſed ingenuouſly, that he could not perſwade himſelf, that ſuch a conionction of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treames was to be found in any man, as in himſelfe; to be ſo vngratefull to his di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine Maieſty, and dayly to receaue ſo many, and ſo notable fauours at his hands. To which may be added that which <hi>Andreas Fruſius</hi> (an intimate friend of <hi>S. Ignatius,</hi> and one who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, for his admirable wiſdome and innocency of life, S. <hi>Ignatius</hi> himſelfe and others of his acquaintance, were
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:174734:41"/>wont to compare and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemble to ſome Angell) was accuſtomed to ſay, that in S. <hi>Ignatius,</hi> ſuperna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall grace appeared to be in-bred, and connaturall to him: with ſuch conſtancy and facility, at all tymes &amp; places, he held a ſtraight hand ouer his proceedings. And other iudicious men, with whom he dayly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſed, taking a long and curious account of all his actions, euen to the leaſt geſture or motion of his body, being taken them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues with admiration of his Sanctity, affirmed, that all the perfections contay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:174734:42"/>either in his booke of the Conſtitutions of the Society, or in that golden treatiſe of <hi>Thomas de Kempis</hi> of the imitation of Chriſt, or in his booke of Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall Exerciſes, were per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly, and to life expreſſed in himſelfe: Whence Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Levvis Gon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>alez,</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſour to the King of <hi>Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tugall,</hi> a graue and diſcreet man, was wont to ſay, that to conuerſe with <hi>Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natius,</hi> was nothing els but to ſee the booke of <hi>Thomas de Kempis</hi> (by others thought to be the booke of Gerſon) liuely and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly acted in him.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="71" facs="tcp:174734:42"/>
                  <hi>S. Ignatius</hi> relating vpon occaſion to <hi>F. Iohn Polanco</hi> (a man of great wiſdome, one whoſe helpe he made vſe of for the diſpatch of letters) ſome paſſages con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning himſelfe, for the better inſtruction of the other; and being demaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded of Father <hi>Polanco,</hi> in a kind of freedome, whet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>her he ranne not a hazard of vaine glory, in the rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſuch paſſages, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning himſelfe? the B. Father made anſwere, that he ſtood in feare of no vice leſſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of vaine glory ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding beſides theſes words you may reſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t <hi>Father
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:174734:43"/>Polanco,</hi> that amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand of Gods fauours be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed vpon me, many ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes I reueale not any, and that merely for the incapa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city of them who ſhould heare me. And yet it is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine that S. <hi>Ignatius,</hi> had the Company and acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance of men of rare parts, endowed with great <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>it, iudgement, experience, learning, and Sanctity, and men of deepe inſight and knowledge, as well of the theoricke, as Practicke of matters of Spirit; who if they were not capable of vnderſtanding the graces of God, infuſed in Saint
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:174734:43"/>
                  <hi>Ignatius,</hi> queſtionleſſe they were of a pitch higher then ordinary, far ſurpaſſing the ordinary courſe of other Saints. Which is an admirable token of rare Sanctity.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>S. Ignatius</hi> had euer a great opinion of the holines of the Church, and of the Saints which floriſhed eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry age of the Church: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeuing they were adorned with many more admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ornaments of diuine grace, then is left written of them in their liues, &amp; Eccleſiaſticall hiſtoryes: in which reſpect he held them in great veneration,
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:174734:44"/>taking a ſpeciall care that their honour ſhould be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uanced, and ſpred by them of his Society, with all poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible diligence, againſt all endeauours of any here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tickes to the contrary: of which his opinion of their admirable Sanctity, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſing vpon occaſion with a freind of his he af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed; that, for his parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular, he would not chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge the ſupernaturall gui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s which he himſelf, without any deſert of his, had ai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready, or was in hope to diriue from that diuine fountaine, with any one of the Saints, whoſe liues
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:174734:44"/>were then extant, if they were not endowed with greater graces and guifts, then any he had read, or were written of them.</p>
               <p>Moreouer, the B F. affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of himſelfe, that he ſhould not be able to liue, if his breſt did nouriſh any human affection, or any thing which did not who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reliſh of heauen. In his actions he was not guided by blind affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, by which for the moſt part, men are led to their deſtruction, but by the ſquare and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of reaſon; often rep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ting, that by reaſon men are diſtinguiſhed
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:174734:45"/>from beaſts. He had a ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall care that his actions ſhould be intended purely for Gods ſake, not for feare of chaſtiſement, or hope, of reward: not contented that each action ſhould on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be directed to the glory of God, but labouring, with an act of reflexion of his ſoule, that they might redound to Gods greateſt honour and glory. Whence it came to paſſe, that all his Epiſtles and Sermons, and each leafe of his booke of Conſtitutions, are full of thoſe words: <hi>Ad maiorem Dei gloriam. Ad maius Dei &amp; Creatoris noſtri obſequium,</hi>
                  <pb n="77" facs="tcp:174734:45"/>the like: his hand and mouth vttering, what his hart was ſurcharged with: which ſincerity of inte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tion he began to apply to his actions, from the firſt day of his Conuerſion, obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing it religiouſly till his dying day. No marueile then if Pope <hi>Iulius tertius,</hi> in his Bull publiſhed the 19. of Auguſt 1550. not to affirme, euen in the life ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me of the Saint: <hi>that there vvas nothing to be found in the exe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plar life of ugnatius, which ſauoured not vvholy of piety &amp; Religion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But that is more remar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kable, which, as well the
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:174734:46"/>Auditours of the holy Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te, as the Cardinalls of the holy Rites teſtify in their relations giuen to his Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lines, of S. <hi>Ignatius,</hi> in theſe words: <hi>He vvas ſo i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſtamed vvith the loue of God, that from morning to night, he nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſought, thought, spake nor deſired any thing, but to pleaſe God, and obey <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>as com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunds: &amp; therfore he commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted himſelfe vvholy to him, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolued abſolutely to fellovv him, though the loſſe of Heauen and earth had gon vpon it: he dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted all his thoughts, vvords and deeds to God, as his aym<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>; and imended them only for
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:174734:46"/>him and his honour.</hi> Thus they Which rare and extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary commendations of all S. <hi>Ignatius</hi> his inward and out ward actions, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding from theſe Iudges Apoſtolicall, and the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſtionable aſſertions of ſo many ſworne witneſſes, how rare and eminent a degree of excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cy in ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue is ſheweth in S. <hi>Ignatius</hi> and vnpartiall man will ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily determine. Moreouer, the Deuills incredible ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred and indignation of the Saint, which he failed not often to expreſſe in his life tyme, is no ſlight te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:174734:47"/>vertue. Whence it came to paſſe, that he often appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in horrid and gaſtly ſhapes, endeauoring to fright and diſtract him in his prayers, and was often, with a little ſticke, chaſed away by him, in contempt. At <hi>Rome</hi> the Deuill attem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pted to haue ſtrangled him in the night tyme, ſtopping his wind-pipe with ſuch force, that the Saint for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing his woice to inuoke aloud the holy name of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, became hoarſe, and remayned ſo, many dayes after. At other tymes, in like manner, as heretofore S. <hi>Antony,</hi> and S. <hi>Catharine S,
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:174734:47"/>of Siena,</hi> he was alſo ill in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treated, and ſoarely, be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by the Deuill. And, as well during his life tyme, as ſince his deceaſe, the Deuill hath often co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſed, in the bodyes of poſſeſſed perſons, that he had no greater enemy then S <hi>Igna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius.</hi> All which excellencies of vertues, &amp; guifts of this Saint, &amp; ſome remarkable paſſages in particular, which ſhalbe breifly tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, were co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>firmed by the Oathes of ſix hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dred thre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcore and fifeene witneſſes, in the proceſſe of his Cano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nization, iudicially exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <pb n="82" facs="tcp:174734:48"/>
               <head>The rare Chaſtity of <hi>S. Igna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius</hi> &amp; purity of Conſcience.</head>
               <head type="sub">CHAP. 8.</head>
               <p>A <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ighty God, to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe the Humility and Penance of <hi>Ignatius,</hi> permitted him, whilſt he was a Souldier, to ſall into ſo me wanton and laſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uious loues; but after that mortall wound receaued in the aſſault of <hi>Pamplena,</hi> being by the reading of good books, conuerted to the Warre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>are of Chriſt, he neuer offended mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly his diuine Maieſty; but
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:174734:48"/>the very firſt moneth after his conuertion, and reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery of health, he made an irreuocable vowe of perpetuall Chaſtity: which Sacrifice and Obla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his deuout mind. Almighty God was plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to allow of, and accept in ſo good part; that from that tyme to his dying day, howbeit he was other wiſe of a complexion fiery and hot, and by nature and cuſtome enclined to fall into thoſe laſciuious<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, to which the often errours of his youth paſt had invred him, yet he was vtterly freed from all ſuch
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:174734:49"/>ſenſualityes. Which, how rare excellent a guift it is of Almighty God, in ſuch a man eſpecially as S. <hi>Ignatius</hi> profeſſed himſelfe, before his conuerſion, thoſe vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent tentations may wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, which many innoce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t and holy men haue ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, in matters of the fleſh, ordinarily wont to be reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted, by caſting themſelues into ſnow, nettles, thornes, and the like auſterityes.</p>
               <p>But how he farther ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celled in purity of mind, appeareth by this. He kept a perpetuall watch againſt all allureme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of the world and the idle and vnneceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:174734:49"/>wandring of his mind, preſeruing his ſoule, with as great care from vice, as curious me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, in dirty wayes, are carefull to preſerue their moſt ſumptuous and rich apparell. And how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit he euer kept a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund of himſelfe, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to S. <hi>Bernards</hi> Counſell, gaue himſelfe not to buſineſſes, but lent himſelfe to them; yet he howerly made an exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of his conſcience. He carried a ſeuere hand ouer his ſenſes; he dayly confeſſed all his omiſſions; he held euer in remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance the fauours of God,
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:174734:50"/>taking a ſtrict account of his thoughts, words, and deeds. But this ſufficed not him, whoſe ayme lay ſo high; he inuented an other manner of Examen, which he called <hi>Particular Examen;</hi> and this he made vſe of, not only for obtay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning victory of his leſſer vices, but for the vtter ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion, and ſupplantation of them, and for his aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cement and increaſe in ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue: concerning which he hath preſcribed certayne Rules to his Society, in his booke of Spiritual Exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes. He curiouſly obſerued all things, which he knew
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:174734:50"/>any wayes tended to the maintayning or increaſing of the grace of Chriſt. If he chanced to heare any thing, which might iuſtly moue a man to paſſion or choller, he preſently recol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected and betooke himſelf to God, caſting ſeriouſly with himſelfe what anſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>were to make. Here-hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce it hapned, that neuer any impertinacy outranne his reaſon, nor he neuer loſt the peace of his mind. Which courſe he obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, not in affayres of this nature only, but in all his other diſcourſes he like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe had a care to ſpeake
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:174734:51"/>nothing vnaduiſedly, but with premeditation; ſo that he vttered no word, not well digeſted. And it is certayne, that more then thirty yeares before he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſed, he neuer miſcalled any man by the names of <hi>foole</hi> or <hi>ſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> or gaue any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther reproachfull language to any. When he had iuſt occaſion to reprehend any man, he did it without bitternes, or any pi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>quant word. And euen in his moſt ſeuere reprehenſions, he forebore to giue any man the epithite of diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient, proud, ſottish, or lazy; reprehending men
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:174734:51"/>for their faults, by opening and vnfoulding the nature of them to them. He neuer vſed any words of exagge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration. He neuer detracted from any mans fame, nor lent any eare to any detra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. Which how rare a thing it is, in this world, S. <hi>Thomas</hi> teacheth 2.2. q. 73. art. 2. ad 2. <hi>That there are fevv, or no men at all, vvho out of leuity, at ſome tyme or other, vtter not ſome thing, in vvhich an other mans good name, hovv lightly ſoeuer dothnot ſuffer, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe at it is ſaid</hi> Iacob 3. <hi>If any man offend not in vvord, he is a perfect man.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He neuer diſcourſed of
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:174734:52"/>other mens imperfections, how publicke ſoeuer they were, or obuious to all men; nor permitted other men to ſpeake of them, in his preſence. And if an other man by chance had co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted a fault, he either mitigated and excuſed the fact, or if that could not well be, at leaſt he excuſed the intention of the party. Touching the tranſgreſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of them of his houſehould, his ſilence was admirable; neuer diſcloſing any mans offence, but for his amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; and then alſo with ſuch modeſty &amp; ſweetnes, and with ſuch a regard of
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:174734:52"/>the delinque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts good name, that, if the diſcouery of the fault to one man, were ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient to redreſſe it, he ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer opened it to a ſecond perſon; diſcouering only the truth of it, without any vehemency or heate of words. He went once to Confeſſion only for this ſinne, that he had made knowne the fault of a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine perſon to three of his Fathers, whereas two of them could ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly haue applied a remedy: And yet the delinquent was ſuch an one, that notwithſtanding the diſcouery of this fault of his, his reputation could
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:174734:53"/>not ſuffer, by that third parties knowledge. He ſpake ſo of all men, that each man might beleiue he ftood in his good opinion, and might ſeeme to claime a particular intereſt in his ſoue. He was of behauiour ſo compleate and well faſhioned, that he neuer diſcompoſed either his hands or eyes; preſeruing a <hi>decorum</hi> in his geſture, his gate, his feeding, &amp; ſitting. No maruaile therfore if the perfection and c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cumſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of S. <hi>Ionati<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s</hi> euen in his leaſt actions, were ſuch, and ſo inſeperably conioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with an internal purity
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:174734:53"/>that be tooke all men with admiration that conuerſed with him; in ſomuch, that by how much the oftner and more familiarly men treated with him, by ſo much the more they ſtood affected to him, howbeit, ordinarily that ſaying of S. <hi>Cyrill</hi> be found true: <hi>That he, vvho is euer preſent, looſeth the respects due from them that Keepe him Company.</hi> And that of Tacitus: <hi>That things farth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt off are moſt held in eſteeme.</hi> Certaine it is, that the B. Fathers Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſour, <hi>F. Iames Eguia</hi> (of whom <hi>S. Ignatius</hi> himſelf is reported to haue ſaid, that he was equally
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:174734:54"/>to be reuerenced with the greateſt Saints in heauen) did not only acknowledge S. <hi>Ignatius</hi> to be greater then a Saint, but could not be reſtrayned, notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding any pe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nances inflicted vpon him by the Saint, from extolling, &amp; ſpeaking infinitely in his prayſe: Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getting wonder in all men, with the intimatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of what he would publiſh, if it were his fortune to ſuruiue S. <hi>Ignatius,</hi> but one hower.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <pb n="95" facs="tcp:174734:54"/>
               <head>The guift of Prayer, in <hi>S. Igna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius</hi> moſt excellent.</head>
               <head type="sub">CHAP. IX.</head>
               <p>AFter <hi>S. Ignatius</hi> was co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerted to a better life, he preſently betooke him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to the refuge of Praier, the better to appeaſe the wrath of Almighty God, &amp; implore his diuine grace. He dayly beſtowed ſeauen howers, vpon his knees, in Prayer: beſides that, he had a ſpeciall care euer to be preſent at the Sacrifice of Maſſe, Euenſong, &amp; Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline. And bei<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g afterwards
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:174734:55"/>preferred to the dignity of Preiſt-hood, and Gouerne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Society; euer after he had offered the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice of the Maſſe, he ſpent two howers in Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templation; to omit his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration to Maſſe, and that morning Prayer, which all they of the Society, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their Rules, are o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliged to make, when they awake out of their ſleep.</p>
               <p>He ſeaſoned all his actio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s with the ſalt of Medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, according to the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept of <hi>S. Baſill.</hi> When and as often as he pleaſed, he conioyned himſelf with eaſe, by contemplation to
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:174734:55"/>God, not only by caſting his eyes vpon the heauens and ſtarrs, with which he was moſt taken, but euen ſo, that with the behoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of any herbs or flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, or any thing of leſſe reckning, he was ſuddain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly tranſported with the ſweet conceit of the loue of God. In the reciting of his <hi>Office,</hi> he was often ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſed with ſuch aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of conſolation, and flouds of teares; that he was forced, almoſt at euery word, to make a pauſe, and interrupt his prayers, ſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding great part of the day in repeating the Pſalmes;
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:174734:56"/>So that through the abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of teares, his eyes oft ſuffered much, not without great daunger of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten tymes of falling blind, and his body, by meanes of his often Exraſies was infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitely trauelled. For which cauſe, his Companions ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayned licence of his Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, that it might be lawful for him to omit his <hi>Office,</hi> in lieu of which, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, he would dayly performe a certaine taske of <hi>Beades,</hi> ſo ſoone as he awaked out of his ſleep. And becauſe in performing his other deuotions, and particularly in the Sacrifice
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:174734:56"/>of the Maſſe, he likewiſe ranne the ſame hazard of being blind, through the importunity of his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panions, and Counſell of Phiſicians he reſolued to ſeek, at the handes of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God, that he might haue power, now &amp; then to moderate his teares; which alſo he obtayned. And from that tyme for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, he had ſo abſolute a maiſtry and commaund of his teares, that he could in a manner reſtraine, &amp; let looſe the raynes of them at his pleaſure; in ſo ſetled &amp; quiet a manner, that the drines of his teares was not
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:174734:57"/>impeachment to the fruit of his deuotion, nor the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint of them was no hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drance to the abundance of his diuine viſitations. And whenſoeuer at Maſſe he burſt not out thrice at leaſt into teares, he eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med himſelf dry and inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uout. He prayed with ſuch feruour, that through the intention of his mind, he many tymes contracted ſome diſeaſe. And once he brought himſelf in daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of death, by ſaying two Maſſes without intermiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion vpon Chriſtmas day: in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>much, that except he were ſtrong and perfectly
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:174734:57"/>in health, he could not well offer the Sacrifice of the Maſſe: and it was obſerued by them with whom he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uerſed, that euen at ſuch tymes as he was beſt in health, he often fell into ſome infirmity after Maſſe. And many times he became ſo faint at the Altar, that of neceſſity he was carried from the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to his chamber, by the help of other men, not being able to ſtand vpon his leggs, for thoſe diuine viſitations. In his daily Maſſe (which alwaies, the night before, he put in readines in the Miſſal, rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding it ouer with atte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tion)
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:174734:58"/>he conceaued ſo much <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oy, that his body being ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged with the greatnes of diuine comfort, he could not freely take his breath, nor pronounce or vtter any word, till that abundance and plenty of diuine ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes did ceaſe. And ſomety<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes it fell out, that betwixt the prayers and the Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, his feruour was ſuch, that his whole body was enflamed; his face waxed purple red, and all the vei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of his body beate, with the palpable beating and palpitation of his hart; and oftentymes alſo the very haire of his head ſtood an
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:174734:58"/>end. Neither was this ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hement intention of his mind, in the Sacrifice of the Maſſe only, but euen in the leaſt things which had any reference to God. In his <hi>Graces</hi> before meate and after, and in fine in all other things, he did ſo with-drawe his mind, and recollect himſelf, that he ſeemed to behould God preſent; not in Spirit only, but with his corporal eyes: his affection interiourly being ſo enkindled, that his face grew red with it, and (which his Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>panions haue often ſtood amazed at) ſeemed wholy to be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flamed.
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:174734:59"/>No noiſe whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, if it hapned not by his owne fault, was able to diſtract S. <hi>Ignatius</hi> whilſt he prayed. In matters belon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging to Almighty God, he carried himſelf (as the wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of myſticall Diuinity terme it) rather <hi>paſsiuely</hi> then <hi>actiuely</hi> which by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is eſteemed the ſupreme &amp; moſt perfect degree of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templation. Oftentymes in his prayers he was abſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted from his ſenſes; and once in particular, the very firſt yeare after his conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, he remained ſo in a perpetuall extaſie, like a dead man, for the ſpace of
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:174734:59"/>eight daies, without taking any ſuſtinance. In which meane ſpace, certaine pious people iudging him to be dead, had cauſed him to be buried, but that fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling his body, and cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly obſeruing al things, they diſcouered by ſome little motion of his hart, that life lay hidden in him.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <pb n="106" facs="tcp:174734:60"/>
               <head>S. Ignatius <hi>his more then or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary auſterity in the morti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication of his body.</hi>
               </head>
               <head type="sub">CHAP. X.</head>
               <p>THe B. Father, knowing wel that the entra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the ſeruice of Almighty God, required ſome puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment or chaſtiſement of the body, as the firſt Rudime<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of a ſpirituall life, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prentiſhip of Chriſt, began by all poſſible means, as far forth as it was lawfull for him for his health, to pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh his body. Not that he found it, any wayes, rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lious
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:174734:60"/>to his Spirit (for fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the firſt beginnings of his better life, he was by the ſpecial fauour of Almighty God; freed from all ſenſua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, as hath been ſaid be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore) but that by the ſharp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of pennance, he might waſh away the corruption of his life paſt, and make the fauour of heauen more propitious to him. He fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted all the weeke, (exce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pting Sundayes) with wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and dry bread giuen him in almes. He lodged amongſt the refuſe of Beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, vpon the grownd, or bare boords, without any couerture. Of his meate
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:174734:61"/>and ſleep he was moſt ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring. He puniſhed his body with a ſharpe haire-cloth, beſides a chaine or Iron girdle. He went at the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, bare-footed and bare-headed, vſing after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, when he began to apply himſelfe to ſtudyes, the ſoules of ſhooes boared through. He trauelled in the dead of winter, naked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly clad, notwithſtanding the thick falling of the ſnow, or the freezing vp of all places, with the ſharpnes of the froſts. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides which, he continual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly whipped his body thrice a day, with cruel Iron
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:174734:61"/>whipps; conſtantly auoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding all thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gs which might giue his afflicted body any eaſe or contentment. So farforth, that though he were a man of a comely aſpect, and admirable fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, yet the forces of his body being by little and little decayed, all that ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier-like vigour, &amp; beauty of youth was vtterly faded in him. And in his old age, broken now with the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity of pennance, ſtudies, labours, and other conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall troubles, though his yeares required a compe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent diet, he was yet ſo temperate in his meate and
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:174734:62"/>drinke, that they of his houſhould ſtood amazed at it, &amp; that he ſeemed vtterly to haue loſt his taſt in all things; ſauing when now and then he fed vpon cheſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuts, which in <hi>Italy</hi> and <hi>Spaine</hi> is the food of poore people. His diet out of faſting dayes, was Lambe, or ſome other fleſh of no greater value; Veale, Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kins or any ſuch things as are accounted daynetyes, he would neuer taſt, not though he had inuited ſtraungers to eate with him. He neuer tooke guſt in the taſt of any meate, how hungry ſoeuer he
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:174734:62"/>He neuer found fault with any diſh of meate, howſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, through the igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance or careleſnes of ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants, it were ill dreſſed or ſeaſoned; nor though he were ſerued with ill and ſower wine. And in fine, he himſelfe would haue nothing peculiar to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe: he impoſed once a pennance vpon one who ſerued him at table, for bringing one bunch of gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes more to him then to the reſt. Which circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances no vnpartiall man will eſteeme triuiall, if he conſider either the yeares of the man to which much
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:174734:63"/>is to be graunted; or the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmities of health, which in <hi>S. Ignatius,</hi> were fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent, and the almoſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall indiſpoſition and weaknes of his ſtomacke; or laſtly, the authority he had amongſt them he go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerned, and liberty, as it were, to liue as he liſted. He allotted himſelfe but four howers ſleepe, or the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reabouts. He euer lodged in a little, homely, low, &amp; darke chamber, 29. pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes long, 14. broad, and 10. high.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <pb n="113" facs="tcp:174734:63"/>
               <head>The lone of his neighbour admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable in <hi>S. Ignatius.</hi>
               </head>
               <head type="sub">CHAP. XI.</head>
               <p>SAint <hi>Ignatius,</hi> had no ſooner plunged out of the filth of ſinne, but im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediatly he employed all his endeauours to draw his neighbours out of the ſame mire: and ſpent his whole life-tyme after in thoſe en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deauours, to the good of infinite multitudes of ſou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les, and the notable benefit and profit of the Church. To which only end he ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied himſelfe to his ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyes,
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:174734:64"/>for the ſpare of twelue yeares togeather, beginning them after he was 30. yeares of age; all which tyme he liued vpon almes, with great labour and paynes. At ſuch tyme as he went to the Gram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer-ſchole at <hi>Bercelona,</hi> he laboured by all meanes poſſible, to reduce a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne Monaſtery of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious women, who led at that tyme a diſſolute and debauched life, to their an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient and wonted ſtate of holy life; and actually effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, that many of them did pennance and amended their liues. Which when
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:174734:64"/>ſome prophane Louers of theirs perceaued, &amp; found the way to their deſired beſtialityes more and more dayly blocked, they fel fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly at vnawarres, vpon <hi>Ignatius,</hi> beating him with cudgells, in ſo inhuman a manner, that he was for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, for ſome dayes after, to keepe his bed. But he had ſcarce recouered ſtrength; when nothing at all diſmaid with this ill vſage, he returned chere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully to the ſame charita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble office. And being war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by his frends, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired for Gods ſake, not to bring himſelf againe with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:174734:65"/>the compaſſe of the like danger: <hi>What can there be,</hi> quoth he, <hi>more vvelcome to me, then to giue my life for Christ my Lord, and my neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour?</hi> At <hi>Paris,</hi> hauing of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten laboured, in vaine to reclaime a freind of his, from the familiarity of a certaine diſhoneſt woman, &amp; knowing well the ſtreet, through which he was to paſſe, for the accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of this his wicked de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire; howbeit in a wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful cold ſeaſon of the yeare, he caſt himſelf naked, neck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deepe, into a water neare vnto the place, and when he perceaued his freind co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:174734:65"/>neare: <hi>Wheth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r, vvhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> ſaid he, <hi>miſerable wretch doſt thou haſten, doſt thou not perceaue the ſvvord of diuine Iuſtice bent againſt thee? go on, go on, and ſatisfy thy deteſtable luſt, I vvill here punish my ſelf ſo long for thy ſake, till vvith my ſufferance, I haue diuerted the vengea<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of heauen fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thee.</hi> With which ſtrange ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctacle the party was ſo ſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, and ſo taken with ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miration of that great cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of <hi>S. Ignatius,</hi> that he euer after refrained that dangerous familiarity. He faſted three dayes from all meate or drink, beſtowing his prayers and teares to
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:174734:66"/>this only end, that he might reclaime an other perſon from his wicked purpoſes, who fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a vertuous courſe he had begun, was in the way of falling to his firſt lewd life: and in fine he obtained that that incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant perſon co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtantly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeuered in his good courſe begun. During that tyme he applied himſelf to his ſtudies, he dayly gaue him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf ſome tyme to employ for his neighbours good. He euer drew as many as was poſſible for him, by pious exerciſes and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes, to a vertuous and pious life. He was a cheife
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:174734:66"/>actour in the inſtitution of the B. Sacrament, in his owne Country: and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured that at noone a bell ſhould daily ring, to pray for ſuch as were in mortall ſinne, and for the ſoules in purgatory. He was the cauſe that the vſe of dicing was left off, and that the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues and manners of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular, and clergy people were reformed. He was wont to ſay, that he would be moſt ready to walke bare-foot, loaden with hornes about the ſtreets, ſo it might proue for the good of ſoules, &amp; that he would refuſe no habit, how ridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:174734:67"/>or contemptable ſoeuer ir were, ſo it might redound to the good of others: and he made his word good, whenſoeuer any occaſion preſented it ſelf to him. For this cauſe, with infinite labour and toile, and danger of his life, he made a iourney to <hi>Hieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem,</hi> there to conuert the Infidels, &amp; aſſiſt the Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full: which to performe, hauing afterwards drawne to himſelfe nine eminent perſons for his aſſociats, he made a vowe: and in caſe he would not be permitted <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> all this vowe, he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> his and his Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:174734:67"/>endeauours: to the <hi>Popes Holines,</hi> for the good of ſoules. For the ſame pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe with infinite difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and ſtrong oppoſition of the Deuill, he inſtituted the <hi>Society</hi> of <hi>IESVS,</hi> the ayme of which he would haue to be this, that all they of that Society ſhould labour, not only the ſafety and good of their owne ſoules, but ſeriouſly indea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour the perfection of their neighbours: and he decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red their vocation to be this, to trauell into diuers places, and liue in any part of the world, where the ſeruice of God, and ſafety
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:174734:68"/>of ſoules might beſt be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected. And that they might the better ſerue and aſſiſt others, he would haue the exteriour comport<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of them of the Socie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, not conformable to an Heremticall manner of li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, but faſhioned to the life of Chriſt, and of his Apoſtles: that is, in feeding and cladding themſelues, common with that of the moſt regular Clergy of the Country. By which Socie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty what effects he hath wrought in the Church, and what he doth to this day, worke by the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of it (who ſix yeares
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:174734:68"/>ſince were numbred to be 13112. diſtributed into 33. ſeuerall Prouinces, and 516 Colledges) all vpright and vnpartiall men knowe: and the enemyes of the holy Church, and they in parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular of the Society, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe. He was not aſhamed, when by that meanes he might withdraw any man from his wicked life, to reueale to him, with an vp right intention, ſome ſinnes of his owne, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted whilſt yet he liued in the world: By which courſe he aſſiſted many men, almoſt fallen deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate. And from the ſame de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:174734:69"/>of his neighbours good, proceeded admirable mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numents of piety inſtituted by him. For to omit the many Scholes of the Socie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, for the bringing vp of youth, ouer the whole world, out of all which, in this later age multitudes of famous men haue, and do daily ſpring, endowed with ſingular parts of vertue and learning, and other rare ornaments of grace and nature. He was the cauſe that in Rome, the Miſtris and ſoueraigne Citty of the world, the German Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg was erected, for the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>tirpation of hereſy in
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:174734:69"/>Germany: He was likewiſe the author of the houſe of Orphanes, for children of both ſexes, who had loſt their Parents: Of the houſe of yong Chriſtians, for the bringing vp of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wes, and others newly conuerted to the faith: Of the Monaſtery of women, whoſe mariages are doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full or litigious, where it is lawfull for them to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayne, till ſuch tyme, as all controuerſyes being cleared, thy returne into grace and fauour of their huſbands. For the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of which Monaſtery, be himſelfe, howbeit his
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:174734:70"/>owne wants preſſed him much, hauing gathered a ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me of too. Crownes out of the profit of certaine ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes which had been ſould, digged out of the place where the Church belon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging to his Colledge ſtood, was the firſt that contribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. He in like manner, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted an other Monaſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, commonly called now <hi>Sancta Catharina de Funarus,</hi> in which place certaine yong maydens, who for want of maintena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce liue in daunger of a diſhoneſt life, are brought vp at great charges, either to be mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried, when they come to
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:174734:70"/>yeares, or els to betake themſelues to ſome reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious courſe. Of which kind, to this day, ſome hudreds of ſuch yong Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins liue in the ſame place. He had alſo an intention to effect that, which before, in his owne Country, he had brought to paſſe, that all vlcerous poore people, miſerably begging by the high waies; being gathered into one place, ſhould be maintained by a common purſe. He co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny prayers to be offered to Almighty God, through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Society, for a certai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne perſon, whom threſcore
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:174734:71"/>yeares before had not been at Confeſſion, by which he reduced the party to a better life. In concluſion, he continually lay in wayt, and caſt with himſelfe, how he might drawe diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute people from their ſinnes, to an amendment, willingly vndergoing any troubles, daungers, or inco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ueniences whatſoeuer without repining, for the gaining of ſoules. He brought to paſſe, in like manner, that the law of <hi>Innocentius tertius</hi> of not vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaking the cure of ſicke perſons, from the firſt viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, till ſuch time
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:174734:71"/>as they had duely confeſſed their ſinnes, a cuſtome, by conniuency almoſt quite aboliſhed, was now many yeares after put in force againe. And laſtly, a thing moſt of all beneficiall for the good of ſoules, the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten frequenting of holy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, lectures, Maſſes, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion &amp; Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munion, being long before, through the negligence of Eccleſiaſtical Prelats, out of vſe, <hi>S Igna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius</hi> reduced it to a cuſtome againe; in <hi>Rome</hi> firſt, and afterwards in many other places of the world, as an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient hiſtoriographers teſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tify, and the Auditours of
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:174734:72"/>the holy Rote, firſt, and afterwards the Cardinalls of the holy Rites haue con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed, out of the teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyes of many ſworne wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, liuing in <hi>S. Ignatius</hi> his tyme. Whom, in their Relations to his Holines for his Canonization, they haue in plaine termes ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged truly to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue the title of <hi>Apostle of the Indians and Barbarians, &amp; of other Nations</hi> (which by means of his miſſions, haue come to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſe Chriſt) for the conuerſion of the many barbarous nations, by his Companions. By the ſame reaſon that <hi>S. Gregory the
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:174734:72"/>Great is ſtiled, by venerable Bede, the Apoſtle of England,</hi> for ſending thithers <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sten</hi> and other Monks, to preach the Ghoſpell.</p>
               <p>But the charity of <hi>S Igna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius</hi> was not ſatisfied with the ſpirituall good of his neighbour only, for it extended it ſelfe, in a plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull manner, to their tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall commodities alſo. Immediatly after he had left the ſeruice of the world, and recouered his health, he gaue continuall atte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dance to poore ſick per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, ſeruing the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpital, with great humility,
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:174734:73"/>and Charity: curing their hurts; and ſucking many tymes their ſoares. And though he himſelfe, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing forſaken for Chriſts cauſe, all he had in this world, liued vpon the Charity of other pious people, yet he dayly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded Almes, not only for himſelfe, but for other poore alſo: which when he had, he was moſt libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall in the diſtribution of it, reſeruing to himſelfe the hardeſt &amp; ſtaleſt cruſts of bread, and beſtowing the neweſt, vpon the poore of Chriſt, not without the ſhedding of many teares
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:174734:73"/>for ioy, in expreſſion of the loue of his neighbour, for the loue of God. He was the cauſe that in his owne Country, they of the Sodality of the B. Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, demaunded Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes euery Sunday, for the vnknowne poore, or ſuch as were aſhamed to aske Almes themſelues; cauſing it to be diſtributed faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully amongſt them. He perſwaded his owne Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, euery Sunday in like manner, to beſtow twelue loaues of bread, in honour of the 12. Apoſtles. In viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and conforting ſuch as were any way afflicted,
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:174734:74"/>whether they were priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners or free men, his cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity was admirable: and that he euer obſerued, euen then when he execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted that toilſome function of Generall of the-Society. But in his feruent loue of his enemyes, his charity was more eminent then in any thing whatſoeuer. He neuer repaied any man ill turnes, for ill: he did not only proportion equally his good turnes for bad, but went beyond ill offices done him, in his propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of good. Being diuers tymes, prouoked by di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers, and iuſtly moued
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:174734:74"/>to indignation, he neuer not withſtanding made the leaſt ſhew of paſſion, or tooke any reuenge of any man when he might, how greiueouſly ſoeuer he were prouoked to it. Which might be ſhewed by many notable examples, but that the promiſed breuity of his treatiſe wil not beare it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <head>The loue of God in <hi>S. Ignatius</hi> moſt perfect.</head>
               <head type="sub">CHAP. XII.</head>
               <p>SAint <hi>Ignatius,</hi> himſelfe, by his punctuall obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation of the commaund<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:174734:75"/>of God, and his ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifold charityes towards his neighbour, hath giuen abundant teſtimony of his high eſteeme, &amp; true loue of Almighty God: But yet there are other infallible arguments of it, ſollidly, not Rhetorician like, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed by the Auditours of the holy Rote, and Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinalls of the holy Rites, in their relations for his Canonization, and confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by their iudiciall ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, after curious inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry made, and the examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of many ſworne wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes: <hi>It appeareth</hi> (ſay thoſe Comiſſaries and, Iudges
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:174734:75"/>Apoſtolicall) <hi>how ſincerely he loued God, out of the care and diligence he euer vſed, to do good to his neighbour, for Gods cauſe in all things, spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall and temporall, and out of the especiall regard he had to keepe his hart vndefiled. For, he did not only preſerue his af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection from all ſuch things as are oppoſite to the loue of God, but abſolutely renounced the loue of all creatures, which were nor God; vtterly conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting his affection into the loue of God, and labouring to apply his deſires to him. This loue towards God</hi> (ſay the ſame Iudges and Commiſſaries Apoſtolicall) <hi>he preſerued ſo
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:174734:76"/>without mixture in his brest, that he had viterly bannished all loue of himſelfe: for he ſaid ſometymes of himſelfe, that he would rather be contented if it were in his choiſe, to liue in doubt of his ſaluation, and in the meane tyme ſerue God, then dye at that instant with aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of ſaluation: and that if it should pleaſe God to confine him to hell, he beleeued that the hearing of Gods name blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med would be more hard and painefull to him, then the ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of the torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of hell it ſelf. In concluſion, he was ſo infla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med with the loue of God, that from morning to night he nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſought, thought, spake, nor
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:174734:76"/>deſired any thing, but to pleaſe God and obey his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunds: and therfore he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted himſelf wholy to him, reſolued abſolutely to follow him, though the loſſe of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen and earth had go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> vpon it: he directed all his thoughts, words and deedes to God, as his ayme, intended them only for him, and his honour: euer carrying thoſe words in his mouth, as his deuiſe, AD MAIOREM DEI GLO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RIAM. Hence proceed that ſpirituall ioy with which this ſeruant of God was euer reple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nished, that cherefulnes of coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance he euer enioyed, and that interiour peace of mind.</hi>
                  <pb n="130" facs="tcp:174734:77"/>Thus they. Beſides, theſe are notable argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of his admirable loue of God; that howſoeuer he were ſurcharged with care, or tired out with buſineſſes, with the only calling to mind, or imbracing as it were of Almighty God, he found himſelfe refreſhed, to his infinite content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. He was ſo inflamed with the deſire of behoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding Chriſt our Sauiour, as he is, that for that only, he ſeriouſly begged from day to day, to be freed from the bonds of his fleſh (if Almighty God, for the good of ſoules, did not longer exact his endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uours.)
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:174734:77"/>In ſo much that, if at any tyme, he chanced to fall into agreat ſicknes, in hope of deceaſing, he was preſently abſtracted from his ſenſes, not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the infinite impai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of his health. For which cauſe his Phiſicians enioyned him ſeriouſly to with-draw his mind at ſuch tymes, from the thought of heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly things. In the midſt of his moſt ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious and important affai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, he was ſo zealous of withdrawing diſhoneſt women from their lewd liues; that if any ſuch, at any tyme chanced to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:174734:78"/>&amp; deſired to retire her ſelfe into ſome Monaſtery, he himſelfe being now a graue old man, and execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the Office of Generall of the Society, would not ſtick, for Gods honour, to conduct, and as it were, to vſher her on. And being warned by ſome freinds of his, that it was but labour loſt, vpon ſuch kind of people, who within ſhort tyme after would returne to their vomit: <hi>I</hi> (quoth he) <hi>should eſteeme it a plentifull reward for all my labours and paynes taken in this life, if I could be a meanes to hinder any one of them, but from one nights
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:174734:78"/>tranſgreſsing and offending of God.</hi> Calling often tymes vpon God, he cryed out, in a kind of tendernes of hart. <hi>VVhat I deſire but thee, o Lord, that I deſire but ther, or what is there els that I can deſire?</hi> As often as caſting his eyes vpon the heauens, he beheld the ſtarrs, which he was often and long ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtomed to do, all earthly things appeared contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptible in his eye, and he himſelfe was taken with a vehement deſire of heauen. In his prayers to the B. Trinity, which were fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent and long, he concea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued admirable diuine con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolations.
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:174734:79"/>Though in <hi>Spaine</hi> it be generally eſteemed a foule taint in bloud, and a blemiſh to any family, to haue had anceſters deſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded from a Iewiſh race: yet <hi>S. Ignatius,</hi> howbeit his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily were neuer touched with that infamy, was ouer-heard, by many men, to ſay to <hi>F. Ribadeneira,</hi> that he ſhould haue eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med it a ſingular fauour of Almighty God to haue deſcended from a Iewiſh race; that by that meanes at leaſt, he might in ſome ſort, though farre off haue been allied according to fleſh, to Chriſt our Lord,
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:174734:79"/>and his B. Mother. Which words he vttered with ſuch a ſenſe of piety, out of his feruent loue of piety; out of his feruent loue of Chriſt, that he could not forbeare weeping.</p>
               <p>At <hi>Rome</hi> when he inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted children, and other ignorant Auditors, in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Chriſtian doctrine, he was euer wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>clud his exhortations in ſuch ſort: <hi>Loue God with all your harts, with all your ſoules with al your powe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s.</hi> Which words he vttered with ſuch fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour, that he ſeemed to ſend forth flames, and ſet on fire the harts of his hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers.
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:174734:80"/>The B. Father in his latter tyme, was much cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in his health, and trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled with an almoſt conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall weakenes and yrke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomneſſe of his ſtomacke, for which, he found no better nor more ready re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> medy, then the ſimple and plaine Church ſong, dayly vſed in Churches; <hi>ſo that not only his hart, but his body reioyced in the liuing God, and was ſtrengthned, and recouered with the prayſes of its beſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued.</hi> Wherfore if he had been led by his owne pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate affection, he would haue inſtituted in the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety, the keeping of the
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:174734:80"/>
                  <hi>Quier.</hi> as in other <hi>Orders</hi> it is kept yet becauſe he ſaw that, they of the Society, might propagate no leſſe the glory of God by other meanes, then by the <hi>Quier,</hi> and perfect themſelues and others, in the ſeruice of God, he iudged it moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedient that the Society ſhould forbeare the <hi>Quier;</hi> commending notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the vſe of it (as he did all things els, in other <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders</hi>) as a thing moſt proper to the Inſtitution of them all.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="chapter">
               <pb n="138" facs="tcp:174734:81"/>
               <head>The admirable commaeund in S <hi>Ignatius,</hi> of all his paſsions.</head>
               <head type="sub">CHAPTER XIII.</head>
               <p>SAint <hi>Ignatius,</hi> through the eſpeciall fauour of God, and his owne labour <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd induſtry, had ſo abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely conquered all his paſſions and affections, and ſo ſubdued them to reaſon, that though he could not truly be ſaid to be without them (for that is a thing re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugnant to human nature) yet he appeared to be vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly voyd of paſſion, or any other turbulent motions
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:174734:81"/>of the mind. And therfore, as well the Auditours of the holy Roman Rote, as the Cardinalls of the holy Rites, in their relations to his Holines, for the Cano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nization of <hi>S. Ignatius,</hi> wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes in plaine termes, that <hi>he had an abſolute maiſtry of all his turbulent paſsions and affections.</hi> Which how rare and eminent a thing it is in this mortall life, all men find by experience, and the learned are beſt able to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh, who know what power the inclination to ſinne hath, in our human nature corrupted by Adam. So that although there are
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:174734:82"/>dry affections in men, of hatred, of deſire, of flight, of ioy, of ſorrow, of hope, of deſpaire, of feare, of audacity, of an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger; yet S <hi>Ignatius</hi> had ſo conquered them all, that he made vſe of them, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the rule of rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and ſquare of Gods Lawes, not in any vicious manner, but in the way of neceſſity. Whence it came to paſſe, that though he were naturally of a chol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerike &amp; fiery diſpoſition, yet for the wonderfull mildnes he vſed in all his words and actions, he ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med euen to the Phiſicians themſelues, to be of a cold,
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:174734:82"/>and (as they terme it) of a phlegmatike co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plexion. When at any tyme he was diſcourſing of any ſubiect of merriment, if any of his, in the meane tyme had committed a fault repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſible, at his firſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houlding of the delinquent he altered his countenance, and putting on a ſeuere browe, wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>, in his reprehenſion, and ſuddai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nely again aft<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> the party was departed, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſame inſtant of tyme, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>urned to his former caime and pleaſantnes of diſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ours, with as cherefull and quiet a countenance as if he had
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:174734:83"/>had no cauſe to reproue any man: ſo that he appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red not to haue been mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued at all, but at his plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, to haue taken vpon him, and laid downe againe that ſeuerity requiſite. He alwayes obſerued the ſame method in his buſineſſes, being euer conſtant to himſelfe; and how beit in body he was diuerſly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, and through his frequent infirmityes, more o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> fit for the diſpatch of buſineſſes, his mind notwithſtanding was euer the ſame, ſo that to obtaine or effect any buſines with him, it was not neceſſary
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:174734:83"/>to obſerue tymes or occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions. For, whether you tooke him after Maſſe, or after dinner, as ſoone as he aroſe out of his bed or after his prayers, to him it was the ſame, or whether his buſineſſes went croſſe, or to his mind: in fine, he was neuer altered with any change or alteration of buſineſſes, but was euer himſelf. In all croſſe acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents &amp; viciſſitudes of this life, he was ſo preſent to himſelf, that he neuer ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med in any thing to alter his courſe, or derogate from the dignity of a Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious perſon.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="chapter">
               <pb n="144" facs="tcp:174734:84"/>
               <head>The rare patience and humility of <hi>S. Ignatius.</hi>
               </head>
               <head type="sub">CHAP. XIIII.</head>
               <p>BY how much more re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable the ſuperna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural giſts mencioned were in <hi>S. Ignatius,</hi> by ſo much more glorious was his hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility: which as the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of vertue, from the beginning of his conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion was eminent in him. So that in thoſe firſt yeares, he went barely and naked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly clad, he lodged (how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit in honeſt places) with the ordinary ſort of Beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers;
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:174734:84"/>he curiouſly concea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the nobility of his birth, and thoſe diuine viſions which were ſo fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent with him. He was wont to ſay, that he found matter and example of ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue in all ſuch as he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſed with, and that he was not offended with any man but himſelfe. He deſired that his dead body might be expoſed to the wild beaſts, or birds of the ayre, to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoured, or caſt vpon ſome dung-hill. In matters which were not otherwiſe euident and cleare, he
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:174734:85"/>eaſily ſuffered himſelfe to be led by the opinions of others, and being himſelfe Superiour, accommodated himſelfe to his inferiours. He deſired to become con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptible to all men: and but that he had a regard to the good of his neighbour, (for which it was neceſſary for him to vp-hold him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, and his authority) he would haue walked the ſtreets halfe naked, in a contemptible manner, that ſo he might haue been held and reputed a mad man. He vſed all the power he had, not to be choſen Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall of the Society,
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:174734:85"/>taking that charge vpon him, by the commaund of his Ghoſtly Father, and importunity of his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panions: which he himſelf, ten yeares after, in a Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall congregation of the Society, deſired by all mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes poſſible to haue reſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned: he neuer diſcourſed of his owne affaires, except he were moued to it, by ſome important occaſion (according to the cuſtome of other Saints) for the recouery of the defeaſed minds of others, or for the comforting of deiected perſons, who came to ſeek counſell &amp; remedyes
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:174734:86"/>at his hands, or els for the encouragement or ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of them, by his exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, againſt all croſſe en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counters, and being forced to ſpeake of himſelfe, he did it ſparingly, and that in the tender and growing yeares of the Society, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the example of S. Paul the Apoſtle, who, as S. Gregory ſaith, <hi>concea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led his good deeds, for his owne ſafegard, and published the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parent wenders of God, for the profit of others.</hi> He concea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued ſo humble an opinion of himſelfe, that he valued himſelfe the baſeſt of all mortall men, and thought
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:174734:86"/>he ſtood moſt in need of Gods fauour. Whenſoeuer any diſcourſe hapned of the propagation of the Society, or the fruit it rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped in the Church of God, ouer the Chriſtian world, or of any other ſubiect whatſoeuer which might redound to his praiſe, he ſuddainly recollected him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe; and melting into tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, was ſurpriſed with a modeſt bluſh. He would not permit himſelfe to be praiſed by any man, and hauing vnderſtood that <hi>F. Iames Eguia,</hi> his Ghoſtly Father, aman of wel-neare threſcore and ten yeares of
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:174734:87"/>age, had ſpoken many things in his praiſe, ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſing the ordinary prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of other great Saints, he impoſed vpon him for his pennance, that he ſhould, thrice a day, whipp him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, for three dayes to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geather. But no pennances being afterwards able to reſtraine him from ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king his praiſes, <hi>S. Ignatius</hi> refuſed, at laſt, to vſe him for his Ghoſtly Father, and commaunded him be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, vpon paine of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communication, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion out of the Society, that from thence-forward he ſhould forbeare to
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:174734:87"/>ſpeake any thing in his prayſe. <hi>S. Ignatius,</hi> being newly conuerted, before the performance of his vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yage to <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> was much moleſted with ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations of vaine-glory, againſt which making bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue reſiſtance, and being ſurpriſed with them, in the midſt of a daungerous ſicknes he had contracted, he was more moleſted with the conceit of offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding his diuine Maieſty, then with the vehemency of his deſeaſe growing vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent vpon him; and at laſt through the fauour of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God, he ſo abſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tely
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:174734:88"/>conquered, &amp; vtterly rooted out that vice (and this the very firſt yeare after his conuerſion) that afterwards whenſoeuer the glory of God, or good of ſoules required it, he could as eaſily diſcours of his owne vertues, as of his vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, without any touch, or feeling of vaine glory. Though many men deſired much the true picture of <hi>S Ignatius,</hi> he would neuer ſuffer it to be drawne, or other wayes taken by any. To which purpoſe <hi>Cardinal Pacieco,</hi> comming once to viſit <hi>S Ignatius</hi> lying ſick in bed, intending to ſteale
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:174734:88"/>his picture by a reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious ſtratageme, hauing brought ſecretely, for that end, a Painter in his Company, who through certaine crannies had a full view of the Saint, and ſo might drawe his picture, as he lay. But the Cardinals obſeruancie could not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile againſt the Saints hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility; for his countenance did ſo co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinually alter from one fauour to an other, that the Painter, ſtanding amazed, was forced to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part, without doing any thing. The humility of <hi>S. Ignatius</hi> was the cauſe, that though he acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:174734:89"/>the guifts of God to be admirable in him, and found that he was miracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſly fauoured by him, yet being preferred to the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnity of Preiſthood, he durſt not preſently offer vp his firſt Hoſt to God; but partly with a ſerious atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his mind, partly with an ineſtimable com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of ſpirit, repleniſhed with abundance of new di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine lights, prepared him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf day and night to it, for the ſpace of eighteene mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nethes. But his humility appeared moſt in his ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring all things for Gods cauſe patiently and willin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gly,
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:174734:89"/>with a peaceable and humble mind, iudging him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe worthily to haue de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued all croſſes, and not to haue merited any thing that was good. He be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſought them earneſtly to forbeare, who went about to hinder iniuries and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fronts done him; returning them may thanks, who did him apparent wrongs, doing them all fauours &amp; curteſyes in his power. A certaine heards-mans boy, caſting his eyes in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt vpon the Saint, ash paſſed by him, brake out into a ſcornefull laughter, heaping iniuries vpon him:
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:174734:90"/>at which whilſt he with a cherefull countenance, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained in the place, his Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>panion turning towards him: <hi>Wherfore Father,</hi> quoth he, <hi>make you not haſt from hence to auoid theſe inſolenc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>es of this vngracious boy? To which the Saint replied: Rather<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> quoth he, <hi>why should we depriue the poore boy of this contentment, which, contrary to his expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctation he hath <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hus encoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred.</hi> So that he purpoſely remained in that place offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring himſelfe in a curteous manner, to that impudent fellow to be beheld, &amp; cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly obſerued; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceauing more contentment in this
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:174734:90"/>ſcorne and reproach, then other men in the popular applauſe and acclamations of the vulgar.</p>
               <p>At <hi>Rome,</hi> whilſt he preached openly in the ſtreets, and certaine roguiſh boyes, in contempt, threw apples at his head, he ſtood fixed like a ſtatua, without any ſhew of anger. He was wont to ſay that the vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent perſecutions he endu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, before and after the foundation of the Society, were more deare and wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come to him, then any ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours or commodities this world afforded. Being
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:174734:91"/>demaunded by a freind of his, at ſuch tyme as for a falſe imputation layd to his charge, he was committed to priſon in <hi>Salamanca,</hi> whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that impriſonement, and thoſe chaines did not much afflict him? <hi>And doth,</hi> quoth he, <hi>a priſon appeare to you ſo fearefull? know then that the whole Towne of Sala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manca cannot furnish me with ſo many fetters or shackles, but that I would willingly deſire more, for the loue of Chriſt my Lord.</hi> Neither did he only with humility, patience, and willingnes, embrace all aduerſities, by which his honour, reputation, body,
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:174734:91"/>and affaires might ſuffer, but which is an eminent degree in theſe kind of vertues, he reioyced at any accident which hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned againſt himſelfe, or his good name; as the Auditours of the holy Rote haue noted, and the Cardinalls of the holy Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, in their Relations to his Holines.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="chapter">
               <pb n="160" facs="tcp:174734:92"/>
               <head>The life and reputation of <hi>S. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Ignatius,</hi> miraculouſly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued often tymes, and defended by Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God.</head>
               <head type="sub">CHAP. XV.</head>
               <p>VVHom the diuine Maieſty maketh choiſe of to exploit great actions in his Church, and to raiſe the glory of Chriſt, in ſome eminent degree, them and their reputation he is accuſtomed to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue, and by peculiar fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour and aſſiſtance defend. Of which in the life of S.
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:174734:92"/>
                  <hi>Ignatius,</hi> there are notable and rare examples.</p>
               <p>When S. <hi>Ignatius</hi> lay ſick in his Fathers houſe of his mortall wound, in emmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent danger of death, to the great regret of the whole hous-hould, hauing receaued by the aduice of freinds, the holy Rites of the Church, <hi>S. Peter</hi> the Apoſtle appeared to him, vpon the Eue of his feaſt, reſtoring him miraculouſly to his deſired health. In ſomuch, that immediately he was eaſed of his paines, and began with appetite, to fall to his meate. And it is a token
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:174734:93"/>of a peculiar care Almighty God had of S. <hi>Ignatius</hi> his life, that he committed the cuſtody of him, not to any Augel of an inferiour <hi>Order,</hi> ſuch as are ordinarily ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed for our Guardians, but to an Arch-Angell of a high degree. That he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued him in his ſeauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dayes faſt, without recea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing any ſuſtinance; in his extaſies, and other prayers, without any infirmity, or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mpairing of his ſtrength; with a cruell whipping of his body thrice a day, and the performance of ſeauen howers Prayer vpon his knees.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="161" facs="tcp:174734:93"/>S. <hi>Ignatius</hi> hauing been left by his fellow-trauel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, and arriuing late in the euening at <hi>Venice,</hi> where knowing not the way to the publicke Hoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitall, nor hauing any money to hire himſelfe a guide; being now accuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by long vſe to lodge ill; he found an empty Tradeſ-mans ſtall, in an open publicke gallery, where the night drawing on, he might in ſome ſort reſt his wearied limmes. But whilſt he paſſed thus the night, a neighbouring Senatour, <hi>Marco Antonio Treuiſano:</hi> a man of knowne
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:174734:94"/>integrity, who afterwards came to be <hi>Dogue</hi> of <hi>Venice,</hi> was raiſed vp by a voice from Heauen, rebuking him for ſolacing in a ſoft bed and curious furniture, whilſt in the meane tyme the ſeruant of God being a ſtranger, and deſtitute of all human comfort, lay poorely in an open place not farre from his porch. He therfore being ſtroken with infinite horrour and feare, aroſe ſuddainely, &amp; finding S. <hi>Ignatius,</hi> gaue him noble entertainement. In his ſea-voyage to <hi>Hieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem</hi> he diſcouered that many foule facts were
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:174734:94"/>committed, by ſome of the paſſengers, in the ſhip he paſſed; for which he in reprehending them freely, they conſpired with the marriners, plotting to put aſhoare this troubleſome controller, in ſome deſert Iland, out of their ſight and fellowſhip. Which deſigne of theirs being diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couered by ſome other Spaniſh paſſengers, they acquainted <hi>Ignatius</hi> with it counſelling him with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, to haue a care of himſelfe. But he not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding, when gentle admonitions would not
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:174734:95"/>ſerue, continued to repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend them ſharply for their enormities, relying vpon the prouidence and helpe of Heauen: by the fauour of which it came to paſſe, that they approaching neare the Iland deſtined for their exploit, were violent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly driuen backward with a contrary wind, and whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they would or no, brought <hi>Ignatius</hi> to his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired Hauen.</p>
               <p>Being to returne into Italy, he found by chance three Paſſage-boats bound for that place: two of which being tall, &amp; ſtrongly built ſhips, refuſed to admitt
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:174734:95"/>
                  <hi>Ignatius:</hi> the third, a ſmall and ill compacted veſſell receaued him; and hauing put to ſea togeather with a fauorable wind, the two which refuſed to receaue <hi>S. Ignatius</hi> were ſuddainely caſt away; and the third only, which tranſported him being weake, &amp; much beaten with tempeſt and foule weather, arriued the moneth following, ſafe in <hi>Apulia.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>At <hi>Alcala,</hi> at the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of the Suffragant of that place, one <hi>Iohn Lucena,</hi> made a gathering for the clothing of <hi>S. Ignatius</hi> in his Clergy garments: with
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:174734:96"/>whom comming to a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne perſon of quality, to demaund almes for that purpoſe, the noble man, rurning to. <hi>S. Ignatius: If this fellow,</hi> quoth he, poin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to the Saint, <hi>deſerue not to be burnt,</hi> I <hi>will he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented to be burnt in his place.</hi> And the ſelfe ſame day (a thing worth obſeruing) that noble perſonage was conſumed by fire which by chance had taken hould on part of his houſe.</p>
               <p>At <hi>Paris,</hi> one <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chael</hi> a Spaniard, being incenſed againſt <hi>S. Igna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius,</hi> for hauing drawne <hi>Saint Francis Xauerius,</hi> to
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:174734:96"/>the warrefare of Chriſt, from the midſt of appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent worldly honours at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending him, reſolued to kill him, as the authour of this fact. And hauing violently entred his lod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging, for that purpoſe, and in a rage ruſhed vp ſtaires, with his naked ſword, he was affrighted vpon a ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine, with this voice from Heauen. <hi>Whither goeſt thou miſerable wretch?</hi> and retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned back againe, diſcoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the whole buſines himſelfe, being afterwards conuicted, by the guilt of his owne conſcience.</p>
               <p>Not ſar from <hi>Baſſana</hi> li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:174734:97"/>a certaine Anchorite, a man of a faire reputation of ſanctity, who obſeruing curiouſly <hi>S. Ignatius,</hi> and finding nothing peculiar in his habit, differing from that of the ordinary ſort of Clergy: and perceauing him to be of a pleaſing &amp; familiar behauiour, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any ſhew of an Ereme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall ſpirit: meaſuring his ſanctity by the ſquare of a ſolitary life, concluded there was nothing ſingular in him, or deſeruing parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular note or remarke: and therfore began within him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, to ſlight him, and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue a poore opinion of
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:174734:97"/>his worth. But Almighty God would not long per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit the ſimplicity of the man to be miſled by errour. For being in his prayers, more vehement then or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary, Almighty God was pleaſed to reueale vnto him, that the man of whom he had conceaued ſo ſlight an opinion, was a man full of Apoſtolicall ſpirit, and a veſſell of election for the ſafety of many. From which tyme foreward the Anchorite condemning with ſorrow his owne ras<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hnes, reſolued euer after, to reuerence <hi>S. Ignatius,</hi> &amp; his followers.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="170" facs="tcp:174734:98"/>
                  <hi>F. Iames Fguia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> a man of knowne Sanctity, and Ghoſtly father to <hi>S Ignatius</hi> was wont to ſay, in the life tyme of the Saint, that he liued more by miracle, then by the force of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. And after the death of <hi>S. Ignatius:</hi> the moſt fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous and renowned Phiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians of that tyme, exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the vitall parts of his body being opened, held it for a miracle, that he ſhould liue ſo long, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially vndergoing the charge of Generall of the Society, with ſo continuall and conſtant a pleaſant face and countenance. For his
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:174734:98"/>ſtomacke, through his abſtinence, ſobriety, and continuall drines, appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red ſtrangely contracted. His liuer was ſo hardned and congealed, that it was almoſt become ſtonie. And <hi>Realdo Columbo,</hi> a famous Anatomiſt of that age, wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſeth in his booke of ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temy, that he found three ſtones in his liuer veyne, or as they terme it, in his <hi>Vena Porta.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This extraordinary care God had of the life and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation of S. <hi>Ignatius,</hi> is confirmed by the ſentences of many graue Iudges, of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten giuen in behalfe of the
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:174734:99"/>innocency of <hi>S. Ignatius,</hi> at <hi>Alcala, Salamanca, Venice, Paris &amp; Rome,</hi> howſoeuer his aduerſaries by foule ſlaunders and calumnies, employed all their art to traduce his innocency, and vtterly take a way his fame and good name. But of all others, the clearing of <hi>S. Ignatius</hi> at <hi>Rome,</hi> of that moſt iniurious imputation laid to his charge, by a Monke infected with the hereſyes of Luther, was the moſt famous: For this Mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ke hauing ſpred abroad that <hi>S. Ignatius,</hi> and his fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers, as men guilty of groſſe enormities, had been
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:174734:99"/>conuicted of hereſy and other foule facts in <hi>Spaine</hi> and <hi>France,</hi> and of late alſo at <hi>Venice,</hi> and that hauing eſcaped the ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds of Iuſtice, they were come to <hi>Rome</hi> to debauch &amp; corrupt youth, vnder the colour of pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, with the like foppe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peries, broached by this Monke and his complices, it begat in ſhort tyme, ſo violent a hatred againſt S. <hi>Ignatius</hi> &amp; his Companio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, that many men began to eſteeme them runne-agate wandring Rogues, and to deteſt, and fly their Society and aquaintance. And the bruit had not only filled
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:174734:100"/>the mouthes of the vulgar in <hi>Rome</hi> but it ſpread it ſelf, by meanes of the letters &amp; meſſengers of their aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries, into other Cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tries and adioyning Prouinces, that the IGNATIANS, with their ring leader, were eſteemed branded men, &amp; conuicted of hereſy and other foule crimes. But our Sauiour Ieſus, who had made a promiſe to <hi>S Igna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius,</hi> in his iourney to <hi>Rome,</hi> that he would be ſauorable to him, quickly deliuered him out of theſe calamities. For it came to paſſe miracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſly, that almoſt all they who had been Iudges of S.
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:174734:100"/>
                  <hi>Ignatius</hi> in <hi>Italy, France,</hi> and <hi>Spaine,</hi> arriued at <hi>Rome,</hi> about their ſeuerall occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, at the ſelfe ſame time, when ſentence was to be giuen there againſt S. <hi>Igna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius.</hi> All who being called to Iudgement, diſcouered the fables and impoſters of his aduerſaries, giuing rare teſtimonies of the vertues and piety of S. <hi>Ignatius.</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides which, the letters of the ſeueral Citties of Italy, in which the Fathers had ſometyme reſided, being brought to <hi>Rome</hi> about the ſame tyme, added much to the reputation of their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerts, and the refutation of
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:174734:101"/>the ſlaunders of their falſe accuſers. By which, and by the expreſſe commaund of his Holines, the Gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of the Citty being moued, cleared <hi>S Ignatius,</hi> by his ſentence in ample manner, not only of all fault, but of ſuſpicion of fault. But it hapned far o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe to them that conſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pired againſt him, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit not at the inſtance of <hi>S. Ignatius:</hi> for Michaell, after the diſcouery of the impoſter, was banniſhed: An other of them after Iudgement giuen againſt him, being ſurpriſed with a violent ſicknes, ended
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:174734:101"/>his dayes of it: an other turned hereticke, leauing his picture behind him to be ſentenced to the fire in his place: a fourth was condemned to perpetuall priſon.</p>
               <p>The like fauours of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God to <hi>S. Ignatius</hi> may be farther confirmed by ſome domeſticall exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples. One of his firſt fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers, a man not yet truly marked with a perfect ſtampe of vertue, being tranſported with an affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of a ſolitary life, and comparing the labour of S. <hi>Ignatius</hi> his life, with the reſt and eaſe of the other,
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:174734:102"/>and the dangers of this, with the ſafety of that (as he conceaued it) being thus diſtracted with many doubts, &amp; diſhartned with the greatnes of the Inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Society, reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued to betake himſelfe for counſel to an Anchorite of approued ſanctity. But he had ſearſe put his foot out of the houſe for that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, when a viſion of an armed man was preſented vnto him, threatning him with a naked ſword and menacing aſpect: which notwithſtanding, when ſtill he continued his way to the Anchorite, the ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:174734:102"/>man in a fury oppoſed himſelfe, not ceaſing to purſue him, till he turning with ſpeed, had ſought his refuge in the embraces of <hi>S. Ignatius:</hi> to the admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of all the neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, who ſaw the party affrighted betake himſelfe to his heeles, but could not diſcouer any thing which might occaſion his flight.</p>
               <p>An other of his Fathers conceauing ſome grudge againſt <hi>S. Ignatius</hi> demeaned himſelfe ſtubbernly and contumaciouſly towards him, for whom the B. Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther praying earneſtly in his Maſſe, and ſhedding
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:174734:103"/>many teares, cried out to our Sauiour: <hi>Pardon him, o Lord; forgiue him o Lord.</hi> To which our Sauiour replied: <hi>Let me alone; for</hi> I <hi>will vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take thy quarrell for thee; and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> vergeance of him, if he do no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> repent.</hi> And it came af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards to paſſe, that that Father (caſting his eyes with deuotion vpon ſome reliques in a certaine Church, an armed man ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared, threatning him with a fearefull counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, and whipp in his hand, if he became not obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient to <hi>S. Ignatius.</hi> After the ſight of which though the Father humbled and
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:174734:103"/>ſubmitted himſelfe, yet he was diuerſly afterwards af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted, in confirmation of the truth of that which Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God had reuealed to <hi>S. Ignatius.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="chapter">
               <head>The famous Miracles wrought by S <hi>Ignatius,</hi> in his life tyme.</head>
               <head type="sub">CHAPTER XVI.</head>
               <p>THough: <hi>the triall of ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctity conſiſt not in the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of wonders,</hi> as <hi>S. Gregory</hi> the Pope noteth (whence it came to paſſe, that ſaint Iohn Baptiſt, a man ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowned in the holy writ,
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:174734:104"/>for his ſanctity of life, is not reported in the Gho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell, to haue wrought any miracle, whilſt he liued) yet becauſe the voice of the vulgar ſeemeth to exact miracles, at the hands of Saints, which, howbeit they are not merites, as S. <hi>Bernard</hi> teacheth, yet they are ſignes &amp; tokens of me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rites; the ſanctity of S. <hi>Ignatius</hi> was not voyd of this ornament of Miracles. For in the proceſſes of his Canonization, are mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned more then two hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Miracles wrought by him, all confirmed by the vniforme and graue aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:174734:104"/>of many ſworne wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes.</p>
               <p>Here ſome few only, beſides them often aboue mentioned, which hapned to S. <hi>Ignatius,</hi> in his life<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyme, ſhalbe touched.</p>
               <p>It fell out at <hi>Bercelona,</hi> that two Brothers, about their Patrimony, had long ſued one another. And he, in fine whoſe fortune it was to looſe the ſute, falling, with too vehement appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion, into deſpaire, hung himſelfe, with a hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, vpon a beame in his chamber. The bruite of which came no ſooner to the eares of S. <hi>Ignatius,</hi> but
<pb n="184" facs="tcp:174734:105"/>ſuddainely he betooke himſelfe to the place, and cutting a ſunder the halter, from that vnfortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate rafter, gaue order that the dead body ſhould be laide vpon a bed. Which done; falling a part vpon his knees, he began with many teares, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund the ſafety of that miſerable creature, at the hands of Almighty God. But whilſt <hi>S. Ignatius</hi> (being at that tyme but a ſtudent in the Grammar ſchole) was thus earneſt in his prayers, they who were there preſent, ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in ſuſpence, with their
<pb n="185" facs="tcp:174734:105"/>eyes fixed vpon the bed, (a thing full of miracle:) the dead man returned ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dainly to life, and had the vſe of his voyce ſo long till calling for a Ghoſtly Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, he had confeſſed his ſinnes, and receaued abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution; and then at laſt gaue vp his ghoſt, lately redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med from out the jawes of hell, into the hands of his Creatour.</p>
               <p>He recouered immedia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tely a certaine man called <hi>Baſtida,</hi> who had been many yeares ſick of the falling ſicknes, by caſting vp his eyes and prayers for him to Heauen.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="186" facs="tcp:174734:106"/>He often chaſed the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uil out of poſſeſſed perſons, by the ſigne of the croſſe.</p>
               <p>He reſtored a woman to health, who lay halfe dead of a Conſumption.</p>
               <p>He deliuered one <hi>Simon Rodriguez,</hi> being alſo at deaths dore, from his di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſe, by a pious embrace.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iohn Baptiſta Coce,</hi> who by accident one euening, had ſo burnt his hand, that it became vtterly vnſeruicea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and diſabled for any manuall function, the next day, by his prayers, had his hand healed and reſtored.</p>
               <p>Returning ſick, into his Country, of a quotidian
<pb n="187" facs="tcp:174734:106"/>ague, and preaching often in the open feilds (becauſe the Churches were not ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of the concurſe of people) howbeit his wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenes would not permit him to raiſe his voyce a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loud, yet euery word of his ſermon was perfectly and diſtinctly heatd, and vnderſtood of all men, for the compaſſe of more then three hundred paces.</p>
               <p>Comming once to viſite one <hi>Alexander Petronio,</hi> who lay ſick in a darke &amp; cloſe chamber and bed, in regard the windowes and dores were kept ſhut, to keep out the light, he repleniſhed
<pb n="188" facs="tcp:174734:107"/>the chamber with ſuperna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural ſplendour of his face, and recouered the ſick per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</p>
               <p>He freed one <hi>Eleutherio Pomano,</hi> who had been greiuiouſly moleſted, for the ſpace of more then two yeares, with certaine foule tentations of the Deuill, by his only ſeing, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſing with the party. <hi>Which</hi> (ſaith S. Bernard in the like caſe) <hi>I prefer before the miracle of raiſing a dead body: becauſe there only the exteriour but here the interiour man is reſtored to life.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Colledge of <hi>Loreto</hi> being fearefully haunted
<pb n="189" facs="tcp:174734:107"/>with ſpirits, appearing in ſundry foule ſhapes of men &amp; beaſts, and the ordinary exorciſmes, and other cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies vſuall hauing been applied, and thoſe fearefull apparitions neuertheleſſe not ceaſing: the Rector of the Colledge addreſſed himſelfe, by letters, to <hi>Saint Ignatius,</hi> commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the buſines to his holy ſacrifices &amp; prayers. Who no ſooner receaued newes of it, but he ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely ſreed the houſe, from thoſe haunts of the ill ſpirit, by his prayers and letter, not for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent
<pb n="190" facs="tcp:174734:108"/>only, but for euer af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>S. Ignatius</hi> his linnen, being waſhed with deuotion by a certayne deuout woman, reſtored life and motion to her withered and dead Arme.</p>
               <p>One <hi>Iſaac,</hi> a Iew, refuſing, with a paſſionate obſtinacy to become Chriſtian, and contemning curteſyes and al other courſes taken with him by others, was by S. <hi>Ignatius</hi> ſoone ſatisfed, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peaſed, and perſwaded to be baptiſed, by the only vttering of theſe three words: <hi>Mane nobiſeum Iſaac.</hi> A certaine perſon of note,
<pb n="191" facs="tcp:174734:108"/>being of a more turbulent ſpirit then was fit longer to be endured, and S. <hi>Ignatius</hi> not being able by gentle perſuaſions, to cure his di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſed mind, changing at laſt his ſtile, and beginning to call vpon the Iuſtice of God, and repreſent vnto him the vengeance of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, he did it with ſuch a feeling, and expreſſion of feruour, that the walls and houſe appeared to him to tremble and ſhake with horrour. With the ſight of which the ſtanders by bei<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g ſtroken, immediately fell vpon their knees, implo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the mercy of God, by
<pb n="192" facs="tcp:174734:109"/>their prayers and vowes. And the delinquent pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrating himſelfe at the feet of S. <hi>Ignatius,</hi> and with a voyce of confuſion, beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging pardon for his of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, promiſed from then<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce-foreward an ame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dment of himſelfe.</p>
               <p>Father <hi>Leonard Keſſelius</hi> reſiding at <hi>Collen,</hi> had a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hement deſire to ſee <hi>S. Igna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius,</hi> then at <hi>Rome,</hi> aboue 300. leagues diſtant from thence: And hauing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſought the B. Father by letters, that it might be lawfull for him to trauell a foot to <hi>Rome,</hi> he made an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, that his preſence was
<pb n="193" facs="tcp:174734:109"/>neceſſary at <hi>Collen,</hi> for the good of others; enjoyning him beſides not to ſtir from thence, for that Almighty God peradue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ture, by ſome other courſe, might ſo pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uide that he might ſee him, without the paynes and toyle of ſo tedious a iour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney. The Father therfore being one day at his praiers S. <hi>Ignatius</hi> appeared vnto him, being yet aline and breathing, and diſcourſed long with him, to his infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite contentment.</p>
               <p>The B. Father, lying of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſick, if in the meane time, any difficulty hapned, for the ſolui<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g of which his ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue
<pb n="194" facs="tcp:174734:110"/>and wiſdome was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired, he ſeemed, in a manner, to be perfectly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couered and his mind gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding his body, appeared a ſound man. So that it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came familiar to them of the houſhould, as often as he fell ſick, to deſire that ſome buſines of conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence might happen, for the facilitating of which <hi>S. Ignatius</hi> might riſe, and be quit of his deſeaſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="chapter">
               <pb n="195" facs="tcp:174734:110"/>
               <head>Diuers miracles wrought by <hi>S. Ignatius,</hi> after his deceaſe.</head>
               <head type="sub">CHAP. XVII.</head>
               <p>IN the proceſſes for the Canonization of <hi>S. Igna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius,</hi> commenced by the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of the Ordinaryes firſt, &amp; afterwards by that of the Sea Apoſtolicke, more then two hundred miracles are related, wrought by the merits and interceſſion of <hi>S. Ignatius,</hi> after his deceaſe: Beſides which, there are diuers o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther as authenticall, not yet
<pb n="196" facs="tcp:174734:111"/>publiſhed (becauſe thoſe former for his Canoniza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion were more then ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient) confirmed neuerthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe by the graue teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies of men beyond excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and printed at <hi>Rome</hi> and other parts of <hi>Italy;</hi> in <hi>Spaine</hi> and in <hi>Germany,</hi> and other places, by the appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation of them whom it concerneth to approue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Here only I wil relate ſome few, becauſe my breuity promiſed will not permit many<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </p>
               <p>When the body of S. <hi>Ignatius</hi> lay expoſed vpon the Beere, for the perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of his funerall rites,
<pb n="197" facs="tcp:174734:111"/>one <hi>Bernadina</hi> a Roma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, had a vehement deſire to bring a daughter of hers, who had been lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g troubled with the Emerodes, ſo greiueou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſly that no art of phiſicke could cure her, to kiſſe the hands of his dead body, aſſuring her ſelfe the reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery of her daughter, by that touch: but the daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſported often tymes by the preſſe of people, not being able, for the throng, to approach neare the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, her mother layd hould of a piece of his garment, &amp; had no ſooner applied it to her daughters body, but ſhe was quit of her diſeaſe. Father
<pb n="198" facs="tcp:174734:112"/>daughters body, but ſhe was quit of her diſeaſe.</p>
               <p>Father <hi>Nicolas B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hadilla,</hi> hauing been long ſick of an ague, was recouered by lying in the bed of <hi>S. Igna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>At <hi>Manreſa,</hi> a certaine Lady of quality, feeling no liuing motion of her child in her wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>be, for the ſpace of three howers before ſhe was brought to bed, at laſt was deliuered of a dead child: the vnfortunate ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe of which being much lamented by the ſtanders, by, the rather becauſe the child had not been chriſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned; the midwife, about
<pb n="199" facs="tcp:174734:112"/>halfe an hower after the deliuery of the woman, implored with confidence the help of <hi>S. Ignatius.</hi> And had ſcarſe begun her pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, but the child, before pale and black, returned now to life.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>S. Ignatiu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> being beſought for the life of a little dead infant of an Indian woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s; reſtored the child to life.</p>
               <p>He reſtored many blind men their ſight, deafe men their hearing, lame men their limmes: cured men ſtroken with the palſey; others giuen ouer by the phiſicians, and lying at deaths dore, he reſtored
<pb n="200" facs="tcp:174734:113"/>perfectly to their health. He appeared to many after his deceaſe, either deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring them from greiuious tentations, or freeing them from their diſeaſes, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther dangers, or giuing them good counſell, or fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retelling them things to come, or comforting ſuch as ſerued him with diuine conſolations. And in his iourney to heauen, at the very inſtant of his deceaſe at <hi>Rome</hi> (as afterward appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ared by the computation of howers) he appeared in glory to that noble and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious Lady <hi>Margareta de Lilus,</hi> commending the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety
<pb n="201" facs="tcp:174734:113"/>to her, as to a princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall benefactreſſe of the Colledge of <hi>Bolonia.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Many Deuils haue been caſt out of poſſeſſed per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, and out of houſes which they haunted, by the reliques of the holy Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, or by hanging vp his picture.</p>
               <p>The oile of the lampe, which burneth before his body, hath wrought many ſtrange cures.</p>
               <p>He hath eaſed many wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men who haue called vpon him, in the extreamity of their, child-bearing la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours: and beſtowed chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren vpon barren women.</p>
               <p>At <hi>Carpentras</hi> a certaine
<pb n="202" facs="tcp:174734:114"/>woman being deliuered of a child without motion, &amp; of the complexion of a black-moor; ſo that it was doubtfull what courſe was to be taken, in this prodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious accident, whether the child ought to be chriſtned or no, or whether it were to be deferred till ſome motion were diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered in it. At laſt by the perſuaſion of a certaine Chanon, they implored the aide of <hi>S. Ignatius,</hi> by which the child was ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dainely not recouered only but ſo recouered that his countenance became che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>refull and faire,</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="203" facs="tcp:174734:114"/>He cured diuers of the pleuriſie.</p>
               <p>He protected many men from the fury of their ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myes. Others being fallen head-long from ſome dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous precipice, were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended from all hurt, by inuoking his name.</p>
               <p>At <hi>Ceſenza,</hi> one <hi>Angelo Lopez,</hi> vpon the Eue of S. <hi>Ignatius,</hi> in expreſſion of his affection, had filled his windowes with many pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per-lanterns, adding to each lanterne the picture of the Saint, and, with in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite demonſtrations of gratulation, repeated often theſe words: <hi>Io Loyola, B.
<pb n="204" facs="tcp:174734:115"/>Pater to!</hi> But, in the midſt of this triumph, by chance it came to paſſe, that by the greatnes of the wind, the fire had taken hould of his lanterns; which when it was obſerued by ſome raſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>callity of the vulgar, they began to ſcoffe at this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uotion, vpbraiding the man for his ſuperſtition, and with a bitter alluſion to his <hi>Motto</hi> of triumph, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uert the words of it thus: <hi>At, at, Beatus vritur: at, Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yola crematur!</hi> At which the man growing infinitely out of patience, out of his ſenſe of this irreligion vſed to S. <hi>Ignatius; And I for
<pb n="205" facs="tcp:174734:115"/>my part,</hi> quoth he, <hi>haue ſo high an eſteeme of the ſanct<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>y of the B. Father, that I beleiue him to be able to protect his cin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged picture from the fire</hi> Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was he deceaued in his beleife; for the flame ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing conſumed the paper round about it, forbore to touch the picture, either in demonſtration of the Sanctity of the B. Father, or in obſeruancy of the zeale of him who deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red it.</p>
               <p>At <hi>Braga,</hi> a certaine woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hauing been lately brought a bed, was ſo much weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, for many dayes after, with a continual flux of
<pb n="206" facs="tcp:174734:116"/>bloud, that life could har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dly be kept in her from fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing the courſe of the flux: who drinking of the water into which her child had been dipped, hauing been wrapped im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediatly before in the gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of S. <hi>Ignatius,</hi> her flux ſuddainely ſtopped, and ſhe recouered her ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtomed ſtrength.</p>
               <p>In the Towne of <hi>Gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>arent,</hi> a ceataine woman, hauing already loſt the vſe of her ſight and hearing, and receaued the holy oile and other rites of the Church, lay vtterly out of her ſenſes: and whilſt ſome
<pb n="207" facs="tcp:174734:116"/>about her, out of deuotion, were endeauoring to put her in mind of her laſt words, a certayne woman, who in curteſy ſate by to viſite her, called to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance that a little piece of the guirdle <hi>S. Ignatius</hi> vſed in his life tyme, had lately been ſent to her, by a ſonne of hers of the Society; which ſhe with great con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence, and reuerence towards God, preſently applied to the ſick woman: which done, ſhe began to recouer her ſenſes by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees, to breath, to ſtreatch out her hands, and make ſignes for meate; to the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miration
<pb n="208" facs="tcp:174734:117"/>of the Phiſitians, for the ſuddainneſſe of the cure: all which things were afterwards confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, by the atteſtations of ſworne witneſſes.</p>
               <p>At <hi>Caglari</hi> a certaine el<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Brother ſnatching vp a knife at dinner tyme, hurt his yonger Brother in the eye: and at the ſame tyme, the daughter of a certayne Gentleman, car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing at the table, was ſore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly hurt, in like manner, in one of her eyes. Both which, calling vpon the aide of S. <hi>Ignatius,</hi> were deliuered from daunger, beyond expectation.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="209" facs="tcp:174734:117"/>An other woman had been ſo weakned, for the ſpace of four monethes, with continuall paynes, that ſhe was vtterly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priued of the vſe of her feete: But the feaſt of <hi>S. Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natius</hi> drawing neare, ſhe, deſirous to partake of the common iollity expreſſed that day in our Church, was not fruſtrated of her deſire; for her paine ceaſing and her feete bei<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g reſtored to their wonted ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth, ſhe came thither with ioy to haue a ſhare in the deuotio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
               <p>In the ſame place, vpon the Eue of S. <hi>Ignatius,</hi> the A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lltiery playing round, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> infant who could
<pb n="210" facs="tcp:174734:118"/>not ſpeake, and who had neuer heard the name of S. <hi>Ignatius,</hi> cryed out, to the admiration of all ſtanders by: <hi>To morrow is the day of B. Ignatius.</hi> But they who were preſent, hearing a thing ſo full of wounder, for experiment ſake, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded againe of the child, what was to be done to morrrow; who anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red as before.</p>
               <p>At <hi>Maiorca</hi> dwelt a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, who through the contraction of her ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newes, was become ſo lame, that ſhe could not go without crutches: the whole towne therfore bei<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g,
<pb n="211" facs="tcp:174734:118"/>filled with the noiſes of trumpets, voyces, &amp; other muſicall inſtruments, Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God inſpired her with a deſire of viſiting our Church, Who put her ſelfe in readines to go, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the diſſua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of her ſiſter, who fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red ſhe might miſcarry: by the preſſe of people. She neuertheleſſe gaue no eare to her diſſuaſions, but put her ſelfe vpon the way, and was ſuddainely cured and recouered ſtrength in her feet. And throwing a way her crutches, without any helpe betooke her ſelfe to the Church, where in
<pb n="212" facs="tcp:174734:119"/>thanks-giuing, ſhe cauſed a Maſſe of the B. Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to be ſaid.</p>
               <p>An other woman, who ſome yeares paſt had recea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued her ſight by the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of this B. Father, lying now againe deſperately ſick, and being giuen ouer by foure Phiſicians, not forgetful by whom ſhe had receaued light before, now againe repoſed all her ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes and conſidence in the ſame Phiſician. One night therfore ſhe called out vpon one of the women, who were accuſtomed to watch with her: <hi>Make haſt,</hi> quoth ſhe, <hi>come hither with
<pb n="213" facs="tcp:174734:119"/>ſpeed, and behould this glorious splendour: O if thou hadſt come ſooner thou shouldeſt haue be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held my</hi> S. Ignatius <hi>viſiting me; for I am now recouered, and perfectly well.</hi> And the euent confirmed it to be true. For the Phiſicians themſelues could not deny, but that ſhe was cured by ſome ſecret power.</p>
               <p>At <hi>Monte in Gallicia,</hi> a great fire, raging for many dayes toagether, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuming a certaine wood, gathered ſtill n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>w forces, diſperſing and ſpreading: it ſelfe far and neare, there being no human meanes to ſtop or reſtraine it; To
<pb n="214" facs="tcp:174734:120"/>which the wind ryſing, vpon a ſuddaine, droue the flame towards the Barnes and bordering Towne, ſo that the fire was now ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uanced within three or foure paces of the Corne and houſes: a certaine per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon therefore, taking the picture of <hi>S. Ignatius,</hi> which he had about him, and fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to his prayers, threw it into the midſt of the fla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes, there where the fire raged moſt, and threatned greateſt ruine: and imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatly the fury and rage of it ceaſed, the flames which flew higheſt deſcended and vaniſhed, &amp; the whole
<pb n="215" facs="tcp:174734:120"/>fire returned vpon a ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine from whence it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan. And which is worth admiration, a certaine wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man who had obſerued the throwing in of the picture, leaping into the midſt of the ſmoaking brands, raked away the aſhes with her fingers; and being vnhurt, brought away the picture from the midſt of the burni<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g coales.</p>
               <p>At <hi>Friburg,</hi> a little child of three yeares of age, by chance had broaken his arme; the mother of whom ſearing the diſpleaſure of her huſband, being then abſent, inuoketh the help
<pb n="216" facs="tcp:174734:121"/>of S. <hi>Ignatius:</hi> but she had ſcarſe ended her prayers, when, to her infinite con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment, she found her child before her eyes, whole and without hurt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>S. Ignatius.</hi> being inuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, wrought a preſent cure vpon diuers who had been ſorely wounded: whoſe cure would other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe haue exacted a long tyme.</p>
               <p>Many men, by the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of S. <hi>Ignatius</hi> his pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture, or by the application or touch of his reliques, haue cured the plague, when it raged moſt ſorely, and conſumed multitudes.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="217" facs="tcp:174734:121"/>A certaine Noble man at <hi>Plata</hi> perceauing the skie to be ouercaſt with thick clowds, and fearing a great ſpoile of his Corne; lying yet open in the feild, made a vowe to <hi>S Ignatius;</hi> for the preuenting of the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſt: ſo that when all the adioyning territoryes ſwelled with flouds of raine, not a drop had tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched; or fallen vpon his feilds.</p>
               <p>At <hi>Naples,</hi> one <hi>Vincentio Pagano</hi> hauing prepared certayne artificiall fires for the celebration of the feaſt of <hi>S. Ignatius</hi> had daunge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly through his owne,
<pb n="218" facs="tcp:174734:122"/>folly, ſcorched his hand. Vpon which accident, certayne women of his ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance began to flock about him, applying to his burnt hand a note or ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſcription of <hi>S. Ignatius</hi> his hand-writing; the touch of which preſently eaſed his paine, and the raging of the burnt part, which vſually ceaſeth not till a certayne day, was out of hand appeaſed.</p>
               <p>At <hi>Catanzaro</hi> a certayne pious woman, hauing a ſonne by one <hi>Gaspar Mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcano</hi> her huſband, out of her deuotion to <hi>S. Ignatius,</hi>
                  <pb n="219" facs="tcp:174734:122"/>had a deſire to haue him chriſtned by the name of <hi>Ignatius,</hi> how beit her huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band (in regard the reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ques of <hi>S. Ireneus</hi> were pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued in that Citty) had rather the child ſhould haue been called <hi>Ireneus:</hi> but in concluſion, after much debate about the buſines, they concluded the child ſhould be named <hi>Ignatius Ireneus.</hi> But this contention occaſioned many differences after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards betwixt the man &amp; wife: for the wife, euer after, called her child <hi>Igna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius,</hi> and gaue a ſtrict com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund to them of her houſ
<pb n="220" facs="tcp:174734:123"/>hould to do the like; and <hi>Gaspar,</hi> on the other ſide, commaunded them to call him <hi>Ireneus.</hi> The difference had co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinued thus betwixt them, almoſt the ſpace of three monethes, when ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guing the buſines, one morning, they both grew ſomewhat hot, till the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, at laſt, in ieſt: <hi>VVell,</hi> quoth he, <hi>let the ſtrife be put to the arbitrement of the child himſelfe:</hi> to which the Mother was contented to agree; where vpon the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, in merriment, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded of his child, at that tyme but three mone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thes old, by what name he
<pb n="221" facs="tcp:174734:123"/>would haue himſelf called? when, behould, the child miraculouſly receaued the vſe of his tongue, diſtinctly pronouncing the name of <hi>Ignatius.</hi> Which voyce ſo tooke his Father with ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miration of the miracle, that from thence-foreward he gaue order his child ſhould be called <hi>Ignatius,</hi> dedicating him to the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice of <hi>S. Ignatius.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the Territory of <hi>Peru,</hi> in the <hi>Weſt Indies,</hi> one <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtopher Martinez de Peredes,</hi> for the ſpace of foure yea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res togeather, was forced through the lameneſſe of
<pb n="222" facs="tcp:174734:124"/>his feet, to make vſe of one crutch in the beginning, &amp; afterwards of two: who hearing vpon the feaſt of <hi>S. Ignatius</hi> the triumph of the people: <hi>And shall I,</hi> quoth he, <hi>vpon this day, when all men are in iollity, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine as it were an vnbidden gueſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>? shall</hi> I <hi>alone remaine deſtitute?</hi> Which words he had ſcarſe vttered, when his feete recouered forces, and he found himſelfe ſo ſtrong, that early the next morning, without any other helpe, he betooke himſelfe to the Colledge.</p>
               <p>One <hi>Benedicto Lopez</hi> Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect of the ſiluer mines,
<pb n="223" facs="tcp:174734:124"/>purſuing a certaine Ethio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pian fugitiue, was ſet vpon by fiue others at vnawar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, who ſtabbing and but<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chering him in ſundry pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, dragged him from his horſe, in a moſt barbarous manner. In which his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremityes he implored the aide of <hi>S Ignatius,</hi> who pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently preſented himſelfe to him in theſe exigents, &amp; laving hould of his Cloake, bore of, with both hands, the blowes of his enemyes, ſo that at laſt (his enemyes being depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and the B. Father va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed (he found himſelfe ſafe, and without hurt, ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing
<pb n="224" facs="tcp:174734:125"/>that his hat and other garments were pierced.</p>
               <p>A certaine Lady at <hi>Auig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion,</hi> had a ſonne much af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted with a violent con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall feauer, who beſides the deſeaſe it ſelfe, with the violence of it, had one of his hands diſiointed, and in a deformed manner, turned the wrong ſide out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward; ſo that in the opinion of the Phiſicians, he was in danger of the loſſe of his hand, if not of his life with it. Which la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentable caſe, a certaine Religious woman, allied to the ſick youth, compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſionating,
<pb n="225" facs="tcp:174734:125"/>vowed three Maſſes, and as many waxe candles to <hi>S. Ignatius</hi> for the health of her kinſman. Which done, the youth im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately recouered; and in a more infallible con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation of the miracle, his hand was replaced in the right place.</p>
               <p>At <hi>Bercelona,</hi> one <hi>Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth Rebelles</hi> a Religious woman, being in ſome high place buſy about her worke, vpon a ſuddaine vnfortunately tumbled headlong to the ground, &amp; receaued ſo ſore a blow, that her thigh-bone, which is the ſollideſt bone
<pb n="226" facs="tcp:174734:126"/>of the body, was vtterly broken. The Phiſician &amp; Chirurgian were imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately called, who for more then fourty dayes to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geather, with what dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence was poſſible, applied all the remedyes their arts afforded, how beit to little purpoſe. In concluſion, the ſick woman was brought to thoſe termes, that in all mens iudgements, ſhe was paſt recouery, and as it was conceaued, could not laſt longer then that day. Yet notwithſtanding, as ſoone as a Relique of <hi>S Ignatius</hi> was applied to her hart, ſhe preſently recouered.
<pb n="227" facs="tcp:174734:126"/>One <hi>Hierome Humphrey;</hi> aboy of ten yeares of age: vpon one of his eye-browes, neare the te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ples had recea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued a mortal wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, which occaſioned an inflamma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in his eye, &amp; caſt him into a feauer. For which the Chirurgian had him in cure a moneth, not being able to helpe him; for the wound did not only not heale, but grew ſo deepe and wide, that it receaued a tent of a ſinger long, and voided ſo much filth as amazed the Chirurgian. The Mother of the child made a vow to S. <hi>Ignatius,</hi> commending her child to
<pb n="228" facs="tcp:174734:127"/>him; and behould, when (an other Chirurgian, in the meane tyme hauing been called, for the better conſulting about the cure) the bands of the ſore were vnfoulded, they found the wound perfectly healed, cloſed vp, and ſound.</p>
               <p>One <hi>Ferdinando Pertel</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing fallen into a Tercian ague, which afterwards proued a double Tercian, and at laſt a peſtile<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t feauer, with a kind of rauing and fearefull horrour of his ſenſes, was forſaken by the Phiſicians, and lay in his laſt extremity. Being ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore prepared with all the
<pb n="229" facs="tcp:174734:127"/>Rites of the Church, and inuoking S. <hi>Ignatius;</hi> whoſe picture he held in his had, he began ſuddainly to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couer; and was cured of his diſeaſe.</p>
               <p>One <hi>Anne Barzellona,</hi> a woman of threſcore yea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res of age, hauing for aboue the ſpace of two yeares, been ſo miſerably ſtroken with the palſey, that ſhe was vnfit for any labour, and vnable, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out crutches, to go vp and downe ſtaires, and with her crutches alſo ſeemed rather to creept then go; to which when the applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of no remedyes would
<pb n="230" facs="tcp:174734:128"/>ſerue, and she beſides was taken with an apoplexie in her other ſide, ſo that ſhe became impotent, and was confined to her bed: Finding herſelfe thus void of all human helpe, by the aſſiſtance of her crutches, and one <hi>Margaret</hi> her ſiſter, ſhe betooke herſelfe to a Chappel of <hi>S Ignatius,</hi> two howers trauelling diſtant from her lodging. Where, making a vowe in honour of S. <hi>Ignatius,</hi> immediatly ſhe began to find herſelfe better, and was able to bow her knee, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore was growne ſtiffe: And hauing ended her de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>notions,
<pb n="231" facs="tcp:174734:128"/>aroſe full of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment, and returned a ioyfull woman, nimbly to her lodging.</p>
               <p>A bone and ſuperſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption of S. <hi>Ignatius</hi> being applied to the eyes of a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine Widdow of <hi>Matorca,</hi> called <hi>Iane Clara Noguera,</hi> who was blind, reſtored her her ſight.</p>
               <p>Diuers other Miracles of <hi>S. Ignatius</hi> are related in a late life of his, ſet forth by Father <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ed<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o Ribadeneira</hi> in Spaniſh, printed at <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drid</hi> in the yeare 1601. and tranſlated by others into <hi>Latin, Greeke, Italian,</hi> the <hi>Poland</hi> and other langua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges,
<pb n="232" facs="tcp:174734:129"/>and publiſhed in the cheife Cittyes of <hi>Italy, Spai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, France, Germany</hi> and other places, where ſuch as are curious to peruſe them, may find them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="chapter">
               <head>Of the rare Sanctity of <hi>S. Fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis Xauerius,</hi> aſſociate &amp; ſpirituall child of <hi>S. Igna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius;</hi> redounding to the, glory of <hi>S. Ignatius.</hi>
               </head>
               <head type="sub">CHAP. XVIII.</head>
               <p>SAint <hi>Francis Xauerius</hi> was borne in the Caſtle of <hi>Xauere,</hi> the yeare 1497 of noble Parents, <hi>Iohn Laſſo</hi> Preſident of the kings
<pb n="233" facs="tcp:174734:129"/>Counſell, and <hi>Mary Apzi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leueta,</hi> Lord of the Towne of <hi>Xauere,</hi> and other adia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent Territoryes; by whom he was vertuouſly brought vp and ſent to <hi>Paris:</hi> where whilſt he was enabling his vnderſtanding by his ſtudyes, he was wonne by the pious diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes and ſpirituall exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſes of <hi>S. Ignatius</hi> to the warrefare of Chriſt, and with him eight other aſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciates; men of rare parts of vertue &amp; learning. And in concluſion, after he had ſpent ſome tyme in <hi>Venice, Bolonia</hi> and other Cittyes of <hi>Italy,</hi> as a matchleſſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample
<pb n="234" facs="tcp:174734:130"/>of ſanctity to thoſe places, working rare ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects by his Sermons and other offices of piety, being now preferred to the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnity of Preiſthood, at the inſtance of <hi>Iohn</hi> the third king of <hi>Portugall,</hi> he was commaunded into <hi>India</hi> by <hi>S. Ignatius,</hi> there to conioyne thoſe Eaſterne nations to Chriſt, being honoured for that purpoſe by Pope <hi>Paul</hi> the third, with the dignity and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tority of <hi>Legate Apoſtolicall.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In <hi>India,</hi> by the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of many Churches and Colledges, of the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety, he generally diſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
<pb n="235" facs="tcp:174734:130"/>and ſpred the faith of Chriſt. He gained firſt the kingdome of <hi>Trauancor</hi> to the faith, then the Iland of <hi>Zeilan, Aurea Cherſoneſus,</hi> the region of <hi>Maurica,</hi> and other barbarous Nations: afterwards <hi>Iaponia,</hi> the vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termoſt climate of the Eaſt: where before the name of Chriſt had neuer been heard of, receaued by him the light of the Ghoſpell: a man of an vndainted ſpirit, contemning in his traueils of thoſe vaſt Countryes, the imminent danger of death, the rauing &amp; pyracyes of the Ocean, with the like diſcommo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dityes
<pb n="236" facs="tcp:174734:131"/>of his infinite naui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation. And laſtly, he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended a voyage into that vaſt kingdome of <hi>China,</hi> the more to diſperſe the name and glory of Chriſt. He conuerted and bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed, in the ten yeares ſpace of his reſidence in <hi>India,</hi> many hundred thouſands of people: he aſſiſted many deeply engaged in the filth of ſinne, <hi>Domino cooperante, &amp; ſermonem confirmante, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quentibus ſignis.</hi> For in his life tyme he raiſed more then fourteene dead per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons.</p>
               <p>Vpon the frontiers of <hi>Piſcaria</hi> he raiſed a boy,
<pb n="237" facs="tcp:174734:131"/>who for many howers to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether had layne drowned in a well. In the Towne of <hi>Mutan,</hi> in like manner he raiſed an other boy, who dying of a peſtilent feauer, had remayned dead foure and twenty howers. At <hi>Comire</hi> he raiſed a third body, which had layne buried vnder the earth a whole day togeather. Nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re the Promontory of <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mori,</hi> he raiſed a Girle: not farre from, that place a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine married woman. In the Iland of <hi>Vaccare.</hi> neare <hi>Zeilan,</hi> the ſonne of a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine Infidell. At <hi>Malaca</hi> the daughter of one who
<pb n="238" facs="tcp:174734:132"/>had beene lately conuerted. At <hi>Bembari</hi> a certayne boy: another at <hi>Comori:</hi> At <hi>Puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal</hi> he raiſed a man who had laine dead a whole day. Neare <hi>Manapar</hi> he raiſed one <hi>Antoni Miranda.</hi> At <hi>Malaca,</hi> a certaine mans daughter who had been three dayes buried and ouerwhelmed with earth. He reſtored to life in like manner, the ſonne of one <hi>Mahomet Sarangio,</hi> who had layne three dayes vnder water, to omit others raiſed by him in his life tyme.</p>
               <p>And after his death he reſtored almoſt as many
<pb n="239" facs="tcp:174734:132"/>to life. In the proceſſes for his Canonization, mention is made of aboue fiue and twenty perſons raiſed by him from death to life. He often reſtored blind men to their ſight. Diſpoſſeſſed poſſeſſed perſons: cured many lying deſperate, and giuen ouer by the Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicians, healed lepars, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med tempeſtuous Seas, preſerued ſhips fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wracks reſtored the lame to their limmes, and recouered men ſtroken with the pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſey. He foretold infallibly many things to come, pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netrated mens concealed thoughts, had a certayne
<pb n="240" facs="tcp:174734:133"/>knowledge of ſecrets, and things abſent. He appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in diuers places farre diſtant, at one and the ſelfe ſame tyme. He ſpake ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall languages, which he had neuer learned, as rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily, congruouſly, and eloquently as if he had been borne and bred amongſt thoſe Nations. And it fell out oftentymes, that at ſuch tymes as he preached to multitudes of people, men of ſeuerall Nations, at the ſame tyme, heard him vtter their owne language. And with one and the ſelfe ſame anſwer, he often ſatisfied the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunds
<pb n="241" facs="tcp:174734:133"/>of ſeuerall Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dells. He was ſo rauished and tranſported with the deſire and loue of God, that he was often miracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſly raiſed from the ground, with a countenan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce inflamed, eyes ſpark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling and fixed vpon the heauens, and being ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged with celeſtiall ioy, was forced to exclaime: <hi>Sat eſt, Domine, ſat eſt.</hi> By the ſigne of the croſſe he tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned ſaltwater into freſh, in ſeuerall veſſells at Sea. Hauing dipped a braſen Crucifix, which he wore about his neck into the Sea, to appeaſe a tempeſt,
<pb n="242" facs="tcp:174734:134"/>and by accident loſt it; walking the next day, vpon the ſhoare, he eſpied a ſea crab miraculouſly brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging him his crucifix in his clawes, which hauing de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered it, ſuddainely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned back into the Sea, from whence it came.</p>
               <p>He ended his dayes in the Iſle of <hi>Sancion,</hi> neare <hi>China,</hi> vpon the ſecond day of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cember, in the yeare 1552. famous for many miracles, and all ornaments of San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctity. His body was found entire long after his death, how beit in was neither bowelled nor baulmed, but buried in quick lime:
<pb n="243" facs="tcp:174734:134"/>and it appeared, many mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nothes after his deceaſe, liuely, full of iuyce and freſh colour, ſoft and tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctable, ſending forth an admirable ſweet ſauour, and many tymes bleeding. For whith he was honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and reputed a <hi>Saint</hi> im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediatly after his death, not only amongſt Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, but euen among the Infidells; the rather for the many miracles dayly wrought by him. It appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth by the proceſſes for his Canonization that many dead bodyes were raiſed by him, after his death: that many lamps
<pb n="244" facs="tcp:174734:135"/>burned before his body, with water only put into them, as clearely as if they had been filled with oyle, which being often-tymes extinguiſhed, tooke fire againe of themſelues, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out human helpe: that diuers were cured by him, or by his reliques, or pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture, of leproſy, palſey, blindnes, bloudy-fluxes, cankers, vlcers and other deſperate and incurable diſeaſes.</p>
               <p>This ſo eminent man, deſeruedly ſtiled <hi>the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stle of the Indiaes,</hi> euer had <hi>Saint Ignatius</hi> in ſo great veneration, that as often
<pb n="245" facs="tcp:174734:135"/>as he named him before his familiar acquaintance, he gaue him the Epithet of <hi>Saint</hi> or <hi>Bleſſed;</hi> and when<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer he wrote to him, he did it with reuerence, vpon his knees: and in his Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quary he wore the name of S. <hi>Ignatius,</hi> cut out of a letter of his to him, as the relique, of ſome great <hi>Saint,</hi> whilſt yet he was aliue. He ſuffered himſelfe to be gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded like a child by <hi>S. Igna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius,</hi> depending wholy of him, and euer cheriſhing in his breſt an admirable opinion of his ſanctity, which vpon all occaſions, he deſired to expreſſe.
<pb n="246" facs="tcp:174734:136"/>
                  <hi>VVhich words</hi> (ſaith S. Chriſoſtome, in the like ſubiect, hom. 1. ad popu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum) <hi>do ſufficiently demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate and ſpeake all his vertues. for the iudgments of Saints goe not either by fauour or disfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour, but are to be held vnque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtionable.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="chapter">
               <head>The B. Virgin <hi>S. Tereſia</hi> added much to the glory of <hi>S. Ignatius.</hi>
               </head>
               <head type="sub">CHAP. XIX.</head>
               <p>IF the glory of the Father be the wiſe child, as holy writ expreſſeth: the B. Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin <hi>S. Tereſia:</hi> that glorious
<pb n="247" facs="tcp:174734:136"/>Foundreſſe of the <hi>Diſealced Carmelites,</hi> a woman ſo fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous for her admirable and heroicall vertues; who by thoſe eminent degrees of Contemplation, arriued to ſo faſt a freindſhip with Chriſt, renowned for her writings of myſticall Diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, glorious for her pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience and ſufferance of la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, one ſo higly eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med through the Chriſtian world for her reformation of the <hi>Carmelytes,</hi> an <hi>elect ſpouſe</hi> of Chriſt, who through her vehemency of diuine loue, was often ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſed with extaſies, a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man famous for that fiery
<pb n="248" facs="tcp:174734:137"/>Cherubins dart piercing her breſt, one inflamed with an vnquencheable deſire and thirſt of ſoules, adorned with the flower of pure Virginity, glorious ouer the Chriſtian world for her celeſtiall viſions, her ſpirit of prophecy, her manifold guift of cures, in her life tyme and after: this ſacred Virgin, I ſay, added much to the glory of <hi>S. Ignatius,</hi> as one who ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged herſelfe a child of his <hi>Society;</hi> making vſe of the Fathers of it for her confeſſions, and the whole manage of her ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall affayres, and mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culouſly
<pb n="249" facs="tcp:174734:137"/>came to the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of many things in praiſe of the Society, lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing teſtimonyes of it both by word and writing: and particularly in her <hi>Liſe</hi> written by her ſelfe; by the commaund of a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne great <hi>Diuine</hi> of the Order of S. <hi>Dominick.</hi> Out of which <hi>Life,</hi> tranſlated afterwards into Italian, printed at <hi>Rome</hi> in the yeare 1601. and dedicated to Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe <hi>Clement</hi> the eight, by the Arch-Bishop of <hi>Auig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion.</hi> I will here relate ſome paſſages, tranſlated word by word into Latin.</p>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="250" facs="tcp:174734:138"/>
                  <head>In the <hi>5.</hi> Chapter and <hi>47.</hi> page of the ſaid life, <hi>S. Tereſia</hi> writeth thus.</head>
                  <p>I Remained in this blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes aboue 17. yeares, as I reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber, til a certaine lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Father of the Order or S. <hi>Dominick</hi> opened my eyes in ſome things and they of the <hi>Society of Ieſus,</hi> poſſeſſed me intyrely with ſuch fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res <hi>(to w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>, that certaine ſinnes were not to be eſteemed tr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>fles, which ſome ignorant Ghoſtly Fathers had taught her to be no ſinns)</hi> aggrauating my ill conceaued principles, as I will relate hereafter, &amp;c.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="251" facs="tcp:174734:138"/>
                  <head>In the <hi>23.</hi> Chapter and <hi>236.</hi> page of the ſame life, <hi>S. Tereſia</hi> writeht thus.</head>
                  <p>VVHen the Fathers of the <hi>Society of Ieſus</hi> arriued here, to whom I not knowing any of them, found my ſelfe much addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, only becauſe I had vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood as well of their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſight into matters of Spirit, as of their ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ner of Praier: but I found not worth in my ſelfe to diſcourſe with them, nor ſtrength enough to obey them, &amp;c.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="252" facs="tcp:174734:139"/>
                  <head>And againe in the ſame Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pter page <hi>239.</hi> the ſpeaketh thus.</head>
                  <p>IT was for my greater good that I came to know and deale with men ſo holy as they of the <hi>Society of Ieſus. It is here by the way to be noted, that one Antony Kerbeke an Auguſtin Friar, in his Latin verſion of the life of</hi> S. Tereſia (<hi>published at Me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, the yeare</hi> 1603. <hi>and printed by Iohn Albin</hi>) <hi>hath omitted this; &amp; almoſt all things els written by</hi> S. Tereſia <hi>in praiſe of the Society. But what his drift was in it, it is hard to iudge.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="253" facs="tcp:174734:139"/>
                  <head>And in the <hi>244.</hi> page.</head>
                  <p>I Was afflicted, ſuſpecting my owne miſery, that they of the houſhould ſhould ſee me deale with perſons of ſuch Sanctity as <hi>they of the Society,</hi> &amp; I ſeemed to haue the greater obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion not to become ſo mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable, and to depriue my ſelf of my idle recreations.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>And againe page <hi>246.</hi> in the end of the Chapter, <hi>S. Tereſia</hi> writeth.</head>
                  <p>BLeſſed be God who gaue me grace (howſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer
<pb n="254" facs="tcp:174734:140"/>vnperfectly) to obey my ghoſtly Fathers, who for the moſt part, were thoſe bleſſed men of the <hi>Society of Ieſus,</hi> and my ſoule after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards began to perceaue a manifeſt amendment, as now I will relate.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>In the <hi>24.</hi> Chapter and <hi>249.</hi> page, she writeth thus of the Society.</head>
                  <p>I Dwelt not farre from them, reioyſing much that I could haue often communication with them for my only knowing of the holines of their conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation, was the cauſe of
<pb n="255" facs="tcp:174734:140"/>that great proficience, I diſcouered in my ſoule.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>In the <hi>33.</hi> Chapter and <hi>364.</hi> page, writing of a certaine iourney she made, with licence of her Prouinciall:</head>
                  <p>I Was much comformed when I vnderſtood, that in that place there was a Houſe of the <hi>Society of Ieſus.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>In the <hi>38.</hi> Chapter and <hi>421.</hi> page she writheth thus of the Society:</head>
                  <p>(<hi>SAint</hi> Tereſia <hi>here in her originall manuſcript, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſeth the name of the</hi> Socie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     <pb n="256" facs="tcp:174734:141"/>
                     <hi>and reported the ſame, by word of mouth: witneſſe</hi> Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bera <hi>in his life of</hi> S. Tereſia <hi>printed at</hi> Rome, <hi>in the</hi> 4. <hi>Booke,</hi> 5. <hi>Chapter, and</hi> 207 <hi>page, which life the Reuerend Father, Friar John a</hi> Ieſu Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria, <hi>diſcalced Carmelite, in his abridgement of</hi> S. Tereſia's <hi>life, printed at</hi> Rome <hi>in the yeare</hi> 1609. <hi>and dedicated to Pope</hi> Paul <hi>the firſt, ſtileth a hiſtory moſt worthy to be cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dited, in his</hi> 1. <hi>Book,</hi> 1. <hi>Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pter and</hi> 4. <hi>page</hi>) <hi>thus, ſay</hi> S. Tereſia <hi>writeth of the Socie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty:</hi> I ſaw admirable things of ſome Religious perſons of a certayne Order, and of the whole Order in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall;
<pb n="257" facs="tcp:174734:141"/>I oftentymes ſaw them in Heauen with white banners in their hands, and at other tymes I had the like viſions full of admiration. In which reſpect I hould the ſaid Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der in great veneration, as one who haue long con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſed with them, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue their liues to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formable to that which Almighty God hath reuea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to me, of them. <hi>The ſame is to be read in the life of</hi> S. Tereſia. <hi>pag.</hi> 303. <hi>pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blished in Latin by Martin Martinez, and printed at Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len, by, Iohn Kinckius, in the yeare</hi> 1620.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="258" facs="tcp:174734:142"/>
                  <head>And in the ſame Chapter, in the page <hi>430.</hi> of her life, <hi>S. Tereſia</hi> writeth thus:</head>
                  <p>FInding my ſelfe thus much afflicted in ſoule and body, in a certaine Church of the <hi>Society of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus,</hi> where I was hearing the Maſſe which one of the Fathers ſaid for a Brother of the Society lately decea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, I ſaw him enter into Heauen with great glory, and by a particular fauour, accompany the Maieſty of our Lord.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="259" facs="tcp:174734:142"/>
                  <head>In the <hi>39.</hi> Chapter, and <hi>447</hi> page, towards the end.</head>
                  <p>BEing, <hi>ſaith she,</hi> in a Church of a certaine Colledge of the <hi>Society,</hi> whilſt the Brothers of that Colledge were recea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing the B. Sacrament, I ſaw a precious garment (or as the Italian tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſtileth it <hi>Pallio</hi>) hang ouer their heads: and this I ſaw twice; but when other people communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, I ſaw no ſuch thing.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="260" facs="tcp:174734:143"/>
                  <head>In the. <hi>40.</hi> Chapter, and <hi>455.</hi> page of her life, she spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth thus of the ſaid <hi>Society</hi> of <hi>Ieſus,</hi> witneſſe <hi>Ribera</hi> in her life writen by him, in his <hi>4.</hi> Booke, and <hi>5.</hi> Chapiter.</head>
                  <p>BEing vpon a tyme, at my prayers, with great recollection, peace and quietnes, I ſeemed to my ſelfe to be placed neare God, and inuironed with Angels, where I beſought his diuine Maieſty for the good of the Church. And it was reuealed to me what profit ſhould accrew to the Church, by a certayne
<pb n="261" facs="tcp:174734:143"/>Religious Order in the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter dayes, together with the fortitude with which that Order ſhould vphold the Church. <hi>And</hi> Ribera, <hi>in the place aboue mentioned, expreſſeth theſe words ſpoken then by Chriſt, to</hi> S. Tereſia, <hi>to haue been vnderſtood of the</hi> Society of Ieſus, <hi>as</hi> Martin Martinez <hi>tranſlateth them pag</hi> 307. Oh, if thou didſt know what ſupplies thoſe men shall bring to the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caying Church, in after ages! &amp;c. Which viſion ſhe ſaith ſhe often had. And howbeit in that life of S. <hi>Tereſia</hi> which goeth about in print, the name of the
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:174734:144"/>
                     <hi>Society</hi> is not particularly expreſſed, yet in the ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall life, and in all writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten copies I haue ſeen of it, the name of the <hi>Society</hi> is particularly vſed. And theſe words of our Sauiour ſhe repeateth againe in the 40. Chapter, howſoeuer not expreſſing the name of the <hi>Society</hi> which as I ſaid, is apparent, and receaued from the mouth of <hi>S. The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſia</hi> her ſelfe. So <hi>Martinez.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The ſaid <hi>S. Tereſia</hi> hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring one day the Maſſe of <hi>F. Balthazar Aluarez</hi> of the <hi>Society</hi> of <hi>Ieſus</hi> her Ghoſtly Father, ſaw him crowned with a Crowne of won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:174734:144"/>brightnes, all the tyme his Maſſe endured, as <hi>Lewis de la Puente</hi> recoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth in the life of <hi>F. Alua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rez. c.</hi> 6. § 1. <hi>pag.</hi> 69.</p>
                  <p>It was reuealed to <hi>S. Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſia</hi> that the ſaid <hi>F. Alua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rez</hi> her Ghoſtly Father ſhould be ſaued, and our Sauiour ſhewed her an eminent place in Heauen which he was to enioy, adding, that he was at that preſent arriued to ſo high a degree of perfection in this world, as was not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded by any man then aliue; that according to that degree his ſeate in Heauen was prepared,
<pb n="264" facs="tcp:174734:145"/>&amp; that he was gon beyond the perfection of all crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures then vpon the earth, and yet then the Church of God was well ſtored with men of rare Sanctity, as well in the <hi>Society</hi> as out of it. This reuelation S. <hi>Tereſia</hi> diſcouered to <hi>F. Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tazar</hi> himſelfe, and other Fathers of the <hi>Society;</hi> and to ſome of her owne Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſtery, &amp; other Religious perſons who reported it as a truth infallible. She noted it alſo in her ſecret Notes which fell afterwards into the hands of <hi>Diego Iepeſio</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Tarazona</hi> who ſet forth her life in Spaniſh, in
<pb n="265" facs="tcp:174734:145"/>the yeare 1606. and dedica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted it to Pope <hi>Paul</hi> the fifth, amongſt which Notes, he finding this reuelation, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted it to others as <hi>Lewis de la Puente</hi> writeth in the life of <hi>F. Aluarez</hi> §. 2. <hi>pag.</hi> 124. <hi>and</hi> 126.</p>
                  <p>The ſaid S. <hi>Tereſia,</hi> being demaunded by one of her Nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ns, whether ſhe thought it would any way auaile her to be directed by <hi>F. Aluarez,</hi> replied that it were a great mercy of Almighty God to her, <hi>for,</hi> quoth ſhe, <hi>he is one to whom my ſoule oweth more then to all others in this world, and who hath more aſsiſted <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>d directed me in the way of
<pb n="266" facs="tcp:174734:146"/>perfection.</hi> So writeth <hi>Lewis de la Puente,</hi> in the life of <hi>F. Aluarez</hi> cap. 11. in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of the page 117.</p>
                  <p>The ſame S. <hi>Tereſia</hi> appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring many yeares after her death to a certaine ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of God of approued vertue &amp; credit, and one particularly deuoted to herſelfe, and comforting her in her affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions; amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt other things vttered theſe words: <hi>And I my ſelfe,</hi> quoth ſhe, <hi>am a child of the Society, and had one of that Order for my Ghoſtly Father, whom now I ſee and honour in Heauen.</hi> Which she vnderſtood of <hi>F. Aluarez.</hi> for though she
<pb n="267" facs="tcp:174734:146"/>had other Ghoſtly Fathers alſo of the Society, yet he remained longeſt ſo, and with great induſtry aſſiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted her to put in execution thoſe her aſpiring thoughts and of whom she boaſted that he had been her Ghoſtly Father and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, Se <hi>Lewis de la Puente</hi> in the life of <hi>F. Aluarez cap.</hi> 58. §. 1. <hi>page</hi> 607.</p>
                  <p>The ſame S. <hi>Tereſia</hi> knew by reuelation of the death of fourty Fathers and Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of the Society, mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyred by the heretikes in their iourney to <hi>Braſill,</hi> and as ſoone as they were put to death reuealed it to <hi>F.
<pb n="268" facs="tcp:174734:147"/>Aluarez</hi> her Ghoſtly Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that ſhe had ſeene the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with crownes of Martyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome in Heauen. As <hi>Diego Iepeſio</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Tarazona,</hi> writeth in the life of <hi>S. The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſia lib.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 7. <hi>pag.</hi> 152.</p>
                  <p>The ſame S. <hi>Thereſia</hi> ſaw the ſoule of F. <hi>Gutierez</hi> of the Society of <hi>Ieſus,</hi> who died in <hi>France</hi> for the faith, by the miſeryes ſuſtained in priſon, carried in triumph into Heauen, with a Laurell of Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrdome, as is to be read in the life of F. <hi>Suarez</hi> printed at <hi>Lions</hi> 1620. in the begining of his firſt Tome <hi>de Gra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>a.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="269" facs="tcp:174734:147"/>But they of the Society who haue either been Ghoſtly Fathers of S. <hi>Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſia,</hi> or els at her intreaty, haue had the examination of her ſpirit or reuelations, and haue approued them, are theſe following as they are mencioned by the wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters or tranſlatours of S. <hi>Tereſia's</hi> life: <hi>B. Francis Bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gia, F. Antony Araoz. F. Giles Gonzalez. F. Balthazar Aluarez, F Martin Gutiers. F. Salagar; F. Ripalda, F. Paul Hernandez, F. Rodorignez Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uarez, F. Santander. F. Francis Ribera,</hi> F. <hi>Henriquez F. Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholmew Perez</hi> &amp; others ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gularly expert in matters
<pb n="270" facs="tcp:174734:148"/>of ſpirit, whoſe names the Reader may find in the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridgment of the life of <hi>B. Mother Tereſia</hi> ſet forth at <hi>Rome</hi> by the <hi>Rd. Father, Friar Iohn</hi> diſcalced Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>melite, in his 1. booke, 1. chapter, and 8. page: and 1. booke 10. chapter and 51. page, and 4. booke, 4. and 5. chapters 227. &amp; 231 pag. And in <hi>Ribera.</hi> 4. booke, 7. Chapter and 316. page of his Roman edition in Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian. And in the 8. page of the Italian abridgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed at <hi>Rome</hi> this preſent yeare. And in the preface of <hi>Coſmo Gacci,</hi> annexed to the Italian life of <hi>S. Tertſia.</hi>
                     <pb n="271" facs="tcp:174734:148"/>And in the Epiſtle dedica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory of the ſaid life printed in Latin at Collen, by <hi>Iohn Kinckius.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And that <hi>S. Tereſia</hi> drew thoſe firſt beginnings of her more tender and entire freindſhip with Almighty God, from the aduiſe and cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſel of a Ghoſtly Father of hers of the Society, the R. Father <hi>Iohn a Ieſus Maria,</hi> diſcalced Carmelite wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſeth in his abridgement of her life, lib. 1. c. 10. pag. 51. in theſe words: <hi>About that time,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>her Gh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſtly Father deceaſed at Ab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>a, a thing which much afflicted her, becauſe she co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceaued she should
<pb n="272" facs="tcp:174734:149"/>hardly find another to ſucceed him ſo anſwerable to her deſire. Yet she choſe another of the ſame Society, who diſcouering that out of a noblenes of diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition in her, she would not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer herſelfe to be behind hand with any perſon, who bore her any affection in the way of freind-ship, (in ſuch things no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertheleſſe as leſned not her af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection to heauenly ſubiects) counſelled her vtterly to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trench and renounce all ſuch freindships: a thing which ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared ſome what rigorous in her eye, when she reflected vpon the ingratitude if it. But the Father vrged that she would haue recours to prayer, enioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<pb n="273" facs="tcp:174734:149"/>her for ſome dayes, the hymne of the holy Ghoſt, for ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayning light in that particular which she ſeriouſly vndertocks, and praying ſome what long, for that intention, vpon a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne day, she was ſurpriſed with a ſuddaine extaſie, which till that tyme was a thing vnvſuall with her, and being welneare depriued of her ſenſes she heard theſe words within the center of her ſoule:</hi> It is my will that now thou hould freindſhip with An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, not with men. <hi>VVhich words added ſo ſtrong a reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution to her breſt, that in a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment she ouercame herſelfe in that, which for many yeares to
<pb n="274" facs="tcp:174734:150"/>geather by great induſtry, and much importunity, she could not conquer in herſelfe. From this tyme forward our merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full God began to speake to her, and often conuerſe with her.</hi> Thus he.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="chapter">
               <head>Of the glory deriued, to <hi>S. Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natius,</hi> from S. <hi>Philip Nerius.</hi>
               </head>
               <head type="sub">CHAPTER XX.</head>
               <p>BEfore we treat of the meanes by which <hi>S. Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lip Nerius</hi> increaſed the glory of <hi>S. Ignatius,</hi> we will breifely touch, who, and how eminent a man this <hi>S.
<pb n="275" facs="tcp:174734:150"/>Philip</hi> was. He was therfore the Founder of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation of the Oratory, which as it hath begotten many famous me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſo amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt others it produced that renowned writer of Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticall Annales, <hi>Caeſar Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronius,</hi> and <hi>Thomas Bazius</hi> author of the two Tomes of the maker of the Church: whoſe ſpirituall Maſter and Father <hi>B. S. Philp</hi> was, amongſt all other Chriſtian vertues, in which he was eminent, he euer preſerued his vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginity vntouched; beſides which, he had a miraculous guift beſtowed vpon him
<pb n="276" facs="tcp:174734:151"/>of diſcerning in chaſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, the perfume of cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtity, and in others, the ranknes and ſtench of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſtity. He was famous for the guift, of Prophecy, he arriued to the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of many things con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cealed farre from him, and ſuch as were the moſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timate ſecrets of mens harts; he foretould things to come, he was vſually comforted with the appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritions of Chriſt, and of his Angells and Saints: He appeared to many in his life tyme, releeuing them in their afflictions: he cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red ſick perſons without
<pb n="277" facs="tcp:174734:151"/>number, and recouered men gaſping at deaths dore: he reſtored one dead man to life, in his life ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me, another after his owne deceaſe, to omit many other glorious miracles wrought by him; he was ſeene raiſed from the ground, in the tyme of his Maſſes, and other deuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions: he reclaimed many men from their ſinefull to a vertuous and religious life; he was euer held in great veneration of all men. In concluſion, he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded his dayes at <hi>Rome,</hi> full of merites, the 26. day of May, the yeare of our Lord
<pb n="278" facs="tcp:174734:152"/>1595. in the 80. yeare of his age.</p>
               <p>This eminent man was a familiar acquaintance of <hi>S. Ignatius,</hi> at whoſe hands he ſought long before his inſtitution of the Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation of the Oratory, to haue beene admitted into the Society, as his familiar freinds the two Cardinalls <hi>Cuſane</hi> and <hi>Bellarmine</hi> (to whom he himſelfe had of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten tould it) bore witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe of him after his deceaſe: but he receaued a deniall from <hi>S. Ignatius,</hi> as a man deſigned, by the prouiden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce of God, for ſome other Inſtitution, beneficiall to
<pb n="279" facs="tcp:174734:152"/>the Church: howbeit he was euer a tender louer of the <hi>Society,</hi> as wel in the life tyme of <hi>S. Ignatius</hi> as after, of whom (as <hi>Gallonin,</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt other ſworne wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, teſtifieth in the 15. page of his life, publiſhed at <hi>Rome</hi> in Latin) <hi>S. Philip</hi> was wont to ſay, that <hi>S. Ignatius</hi> was a man of that ſanctity, that the interiour beauty of his ſoule ſhewed it ſelfe in him exteriourly, profeſſing to haue often ſeene rayes of brightnes to proceed from his eyes and countenancd: which thing as well the Auditours of the holy Rote, as Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalls
<pb n="280" facs="tcp:174734:153"/>of the holy Rites, vnderſtood to be an euide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t token of his ſanctity. No merueile then if <hi>S. Philip,</hi> being an eyewitnes of the ſanctity of S <hi>Ignatius,</hi> was wont to haue recourſe to him for counſell in his doubts, and was comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with the only ſight of him, when he was afflicted in mind; and that after the death of <hi>S. Ignatius,</hi> he euer cheriſhed that freindſhip begun with the Society. Beſides, when he changed his place of habitation, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                  <hi>S. Hierom.</hi> to a place neare the Church of <hi>S. Maria in Valicella</hi> for many yeares af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,
<pb n="281" facs="tcp:174734:153"/>as long as he continued Gernerall of the Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation of the Oratory; he vſed for his Ghoſtly Father <hi>F. Iohn Baptiſta Peruſco</hi> of the Society of <hi>Ieſus,</hi> a man of holy life, and well verſed in affaires of ſpirit. And af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards, hauing reſigned his Office of Generall to <hi>Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar Baronius,</hi> one of the ſame Congregation, and begun to vſe him for his Ghoſtly Father, which was two yeares before his death, bei<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g then worne out with yeares, &amp; vnable to betake himſelfe to <hi>F. Peruſco,</hi> dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling farre from him; he was often accuſtomed notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding,
<pb n="282" facs="tcp:174734:154"/>at certaine tymes of the yeare, to addreſſe himſelfe to him, and by a Generall Confeſſion, to giue him an account of his conſcience.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="chapter">
               <head>Of the gl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ry, accrewing to S. <hi>Ignatius</hi> by <hi>S. Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les Borromeus.</hi>
               </head>
               <head type="sub">CHAP. XXI.</head>
               <p>THat matchleſſe exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of Sanctity <hi>S. Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les Borromeus</hi> Cardinal, and Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Milan,</hi> was not the leaſt cauſe of <hi>S. Igna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius</hi> his glory, of whom he euer bore a pious memory after his deceaſe, &amp; by the
<pb n="283" facs="tcp:174734:154"/>vſe of his booke of <hi>Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall Exerciſes,</hi> arriued to that emine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t degree of ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctity notorious to the whole world, and as much as he could conueniently, perpetually made vſe of his Society, as appeareth by many conuin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, out of the memora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble things done by <hi>S. Charles</hi> publiſhed by certaine do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſticall Prelats of his, <hi>Iohn Peter Guiſſano, Grattarolio</hi> and others.</p>
               <p>In the yeare. 1562. <hi>S. Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les,</hi> being to receyue holy Orders, and deſiring wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily to prepare himſelf to offer vp his firſt Sacrifice
<pb n="284" facs="tcp:174734:155"/>of the Maſſe to Almighty God, he made choiſe for that purpoſe of the houſe of the profeſſed Fathers of the Society at <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> where he prepared himſelfe with the <hi>Spirituall Exerciſe</hi> of S. <hi>Ignatius,</hi> Founder of the ſaid Society. So writeth <hi>M. Aurelio Graitarolio</hi> in his I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talian Booke of the ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of the veneration of S. <hi>Charles,</hi> and in an Oration made vpon his anniuerſary day before an other <hi>Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall Borromeus,</hi> &amp; the Clergy and people of Millan, the yeare 1601.</p>
               <p>The ſame S. <hi>Charles,</hi> when he had with great
<pb n="285" facs="tcp:174734:155"/>pompe &amp; ceremony, cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brated his firſt Maſſe in pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blike, to ſatisfy the deuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the people, that he might more freely comply with his owne priuate de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uotion, he would celebrate his ſecond Maſſe, the next day in the houſe of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed Fathers of the Socie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and that in a priuate Chappell S. <hi>Ignatius</hi> was wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to vſe, where he wat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched that whole night. Se <hi>Sachinus,</hi> in his hiſtory of the Society. part. 2. lib. 7. n. 11.</p>
               <p>In the yeare 1562. In the firſt beginning of his Prieſt hood, he began alſo with
<pb n="286" facs="tcp:174734:156"/>more then ordinary auſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, and frequent prayers, to dedicate himſelfe to the exerciſes of vertue. In which that he might walke the more ſecure from dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, he entertained for guide of his Spirituall life, <hi>F. Iohn Baptiſta Ribera</hi> a Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh Father of the Society; a man of long experience, great vertue and learning, who hauing prepared the B. Cardinall by the <hi>Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall Exerciſes</hi> of S. <hi>Ignatius,</hi> directed him in the way of ſolid &amp; true vertues, trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning him in the more per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect exerciſes of them. For which purpoſe he daily
<pb n="287" facs="tcp:174734:156"/>went himſelfe to the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinall, who lodged in the <hi>Pallace,</hi> neare his vncle Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe <hi>Pius quartus,</hi> &amp; diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed long with him. Which the enemy of man-kind perceauing, and fore-ſeing the great good like to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue of this Spirituall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſe of S. <hi>Charles,</hi> ſtirred vp the principall kindred of the Cardinall againſt the Father, whom they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaued to be the cauſe of this cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge of life in S. <hi>Charles</hi> whoſe auerſion from a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular courſe they infinitely deplored: &amp; therfore they began, by all opprobrious courſes, iniuriouſly to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ride
<pb n="288" facs="tcp:174734:157"/>&amp; reuile the Father ſo to deterre him from his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſation with S. <hi>Charles,</hi> which when the Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall diſcouered, he gaue order that euer after, the Father ſhould be brought in to him, by ſome ſecret way. So writeth <hi>Iohn Peter Guiſſano,</hi> in his Italian life of S. <hi>Charles,</hi> printed at <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nice,</hi> the yeare 1615. lib. 1. c. 5. pag. 14. col. 2.</p>
               <p>In the yeare 1563. S. <hi>Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les,</hi> now created Arch-Bis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hop of <hi>Millan,</hi> knowing the corrupt manners of the Clergy &amp; laity there, where aſwell the ſecular as regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Clergy led liues more
<pb n="289" facs="tcp:174734:157"/>ſcandalous then lay-men, infamous for their publike carnalities, putting on the ſword in ſteed of the hood rude and indecent in the Church, and ignorant of things requiſite; in ſomuch that they who had the charge of ſoules, knew not the forme of abſolutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, nor vnderſtood not reſerued caſes, or cenſures, they themſelues neuer frequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the Sacrament of Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, who becauſe the charge of other mens Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſions was committed to them, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceaued that them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues were no wayes obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to it, and committed many things ful of ſca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dale:
<pb n="290" facs="tcp:174734:158"/>and that the lay men, on the other ſide, through their many vices, the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentable contempt of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments, and Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call ceremonyes, and the groſſe ignorance euen of our Lords Prayer it ſelf, were in pittifull eſtate, deſiring to rectify theſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uious courſes of his owne comming to them, ſent be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him out of the Court of <hi>Rome,</hi> one <hi>F. Benedicto Pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mio</hi> of the Society of <hi>Ieſus,</hi> an eloquent and zealous preacher, with ſome other his Companions of the ſame Society, to diſpoſe the people, as his fore-run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners,
<pb n="291" facs="tcp:174734:158"/>by preaching &amp; Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſions, to forſake their lewd liues, and entertaine a new diſcipline and refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation deſigned, and infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitely deſired by him. For which purpoſe he obtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned two <hi>Breues</hi> of <hi>Pius IV.</hi> his vncle, one to the Duke of <hi>Seſſa,</hi> then Gouernour of the ſtate of <hi>Millan,</hi> and an other to the Magiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes of the Citty, by which his <hi>Holines</hi> commended to them the prouiding of a houſe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modious for theſe Fathers to exerciſe their functions. Wher-vpon the Church of S. <hi>Vitus in Perta Ticin,</hi> was giuen to them, &amp;
<pb n="292" facs="tcp:174734:159"/>a houſe commodious pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed for them. So writeth <hi>Guiſſano,</hi> in the place aboue mencioned l. 2. c. 9. p. 22. col 2. and l 2. c. 1.</p>
               <p>In the yeare 1565. In the firſt Prouinciall Counſell he called at <hi>Millan</hi> for the reformation of the Clergy and people of that Citty, he cauſed <hi>M Benedicto Butinie,</hi> to make an Italian Sermon of the meanes and neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity of the reformation of the Church, in the preſence of 4. Cardinalls &amp; eleauen Biſhops. So writeth <hi>Guiſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no,</hi> l. 1. c. 11. p. 26. col. 2.</p>
               <p>In the yeare 1566. He cauſed the Fathers of the
<pb n="293" facs="tcp:174734:159"/>Society of Ieſus to take the firſt charge of his Seminary inſtituted for the reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Clergy which Fathers he euer vſed in all the miniſteryes of his Church. Se <hi>Guiſſano,</hi> l. 2. c. 5. p. 46. col. 1.</p>
               <p>In the yeare 1566. S. <hi>Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les</hi> perceauing his harueſt great, and his labouring men but few, out of a vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment deſire he had to find many good ones, he trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with <hi>F. Palmeo,</hi> Prouin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall of the Society of <hi>Ieſus,</hi> about the foundation of a Colledge at <hi>Millan,</hi> and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayned of the Generall of the Society a competent
<pb n="294" facs="tcp:174734:160"/>number of able men, of wounderfull exe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plar liues, &amp; infinitely zealous of the glory of God, and good of ſoules, to whom he gaue the pariſh Church of S. <hi>Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delis,</hi> with the adioyning houſes, tranſlating the <hi>Cure</hi> of that Church to another. And of theſe Fathers he af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards made vſe for the training of his new Semi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary, and for the aſſiſtance of ſoules, and diuers other vſes. For (they are the words of <hi>Guiſſano</hi>) in their ſermons they were feruent and mouing, diligent and laborious in Confeſſions, and all Eccleſiaſticall fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions,
<pb n="295" facs="tcp:174734:160"/>as men full of cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity and diuine ſpirit, being adorned beſides with rare parts of wiſdome and lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, So <hi>Guiſſano</hi> l. 2. c. 7. p. 52. col. 1. &amp; 2.</p>
               <p>In the yeare 1569. S. <hi>Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les</hi> yearely made the <hi>Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual exerciſes</hi> once, by which he euer encreaſed in fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour of ſpirit, &amp; perfected himſelfe in vertue. After<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards he made thoſe <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerciſes</hi> twice euery yeare, which cuſtome he obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued till his dying day, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwading many others, and principaly his owne Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers, to the vſe of thoſe <hi>Exerciſes:</hi> and he ordayned that the Clergy of his Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minary
<pb n="296" facs="tcp:174734:161"/>minary ſhould make vſe of them, at their firſt entra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, &amp; at their receaui<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g of holy <hi>Orders;</hi> For which purpoſe he built a houſe, with in the <hi>Canons</hi> quarter, calling it by the Greck name <hi>Aſcete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rium,</hi> or place of Excerciſe. Se <hi>Guiſſano,</hi> l. 2. c. 16 p. 78. col. 2. And l. 7. cap. 11. p. 317. col. 1. and l. 8. c. 5. &amp; 23. And <hi>Greatorolia</hi> in the place aboue. mencioned. n. 1.</p>
               <p>The B. Cardinall percea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing the Church of S. <hi>Fide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis,</hi> which he had giuen to the Fathers of the Society, not to be capable of the concourſe of people, which
<pb n="297" facs="tcp:174734:161"/>for deuotion ſake, reſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to it, gaue order that the deſigne of a new Church ſhould be made, by a famous Architect, &amp; laid the firſt ſtone himſelfe, much furthering the fabri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cke of it, by his liberality. Se <hi>Guiſſano</hi> l. 2. c. 19. p. 9. col. 2. In the yeare 1572. At <hi>Millan</hi> he founded the Colledge of the Society, commonly called <hi>Brerano,</hi> in which, beſides the Latin ſchooles, he ordained ſchooles of Philoſophy &amp; Diuinity, which ſchooles he would haue them of his Clergy frequent.</p>
               <p>Moreouer, by permiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion
<pb n="298" facs="tcp:174734:162"/>of his <hi>Holines,</hi> he reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gned the Abbey of <hi>Arona</hi> to the Society, &amp; founded in that place, a <hi>Nouitiate</hi> of that <hi>Order.</hi> So <hi>Guiſſano</hi> l. 3. c. 1. p. 23. and 124.</p>
               <p>Hauing inſtituted a Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge for the vertuous bree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of yong Gentlemen, in Chriſtian ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ners, neere the Colledge of the Socie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, he committed the firſt Gouernment of it, to the Fathers of the ſame Society So <hi>Guiſſano</hi> l. 3. c. 4. p. 132. c. 1.</p>
               <p>In the yeare 1575. Being called to <hi>Rome,</hi> for the yeare of <hi>Iubily,</hi> he prepared himſelfe to gaine the ſaid
<pb n="299" facs="tcp:174734:162"/>
                  <hi>Iubily,</hi> by the <hi>Spirituall Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſes</hi> of the Society. So <hi>Grattarolio</hi> in the place abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue mentioned n. 1. And <hi>Guiſſano</hi> l. 3. c. 6. p. 139. col. 2.</p>
               <p>In the yeare 1576. Hauing obtained, of Pope <hi>Gregory</hi> the 13. a <hi>Iubily</hi> for the Citty of <hi>Millan,</hi> he employed <hi>F. Francis <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eruſco</hi> of the Socie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of <hi>Ieſus</hi> to compile a trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe of the manner of gai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning a <hi>Iubily,</hi> So <hi>Guiſſano</hi> l, 3. cap. 8. p. 146. c. 1.</p>
               <p>In the yeare 1576. he tranſlated the bodyes of S. <hi>Fidelis</hi> and <hi>S. Carpopho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> Martyrs, from the Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey of <hi>Arona,</hi> to the Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the Society, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding
<pb n="300" facs="tcp:174734:163"/>the ſtrong oppoſition of the inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants. Se <hi>G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iſſano,</hi> l. 3. cap. 8. p. 147. 148.</p>
               <p>In the yeare 1578. Being to take a iourney into <hi>Sauoy</hi> to viſite the ſacred <hi>Sindon</hi> of Chriſt our Sauiour, he tooke to accompany him in his iourncy, <hi>F. Francis Adorno,</hi> of the Society of <hi>Ieſus,</hi> and <hi>F. Iames Crucio,</hi> with intention to make vſe of him for his directour in the <hi>Spirituall Exerciſes.</hi> which he intended to make in that iourney. Se <hi>Guiſſano</hi> l. 5. c. 5. p. 216. c. 1.</p>
               <p>And in this iourney, he cauſed <hi>F. Adorno,</hi> ouer
<pb n="301" facs="tcp:174734:163"/>night, to propoſe points of meditation to all his follo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wers. Se <hi>Guiſſano</hi> in the ſame place c. 2.</p>
               <p>Being to make an other pilgrimage to <hi>Monte Varal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo,</hi> a place adorned with the myſteryes of the paſſion of our Sauiour, he would haue the ſame <hi>F. Ad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> along with him, to be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected by him in the ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall mannage of his life. Se <hi>Guiſſano</hi> l. 5. cap. 6. p. 222. c. 2.</p>
               <p>In which pilgrimage, whilſt he viſited thoſe Chappels honoured with the memory of the paſſion of our Sauiour, meditating
<pb n="302" facs="tcp:174734:164"/>of the myſteryes of the paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, he tooke his points of Meditation from <hi>F. Ader<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no.</hi> So <hi>Guiſſano</hi> in the place aboue me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cioned p. 223 c. 1.</p>
               <p>Hauing founded a Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of <hi>Suitzers,</hi> he ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned that the ſchollers of it ſhould frequent the ſchoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les of the Society. So <hi>Guiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſano</hi> l. 5 c. 12. p. 238. col. 1.</p>
               <p>In the yeare 1580. At <hi>Flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence,</hi> many men deſiring to receaue the B. Sacrament, at his ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds, he made choice for that ſolemnity, of the Colledge of the Society. So <hi>Guiſſano</hi> l. 6. 3. p. 247. col 1.</p>
               <p>At <hi>Venier,</hi> being requeſted to miniſter the Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion
<pb n="303" facs="tcp:174734:164"/>in generall, for the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction of the deuotion of the people, who infini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tely deſired it, he made choiſe for that purpoſe, of the Colledge of the Socie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, where alſo at the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of the Popes Nun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cio, and the Patriarch of that Citty, he preached. So <hi>Guiſſano,</hi> in the place aboue mentioned.</p>
               <p>Two Colledges of the Society were founded in <hi>Switzerland</hi> by the meane<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of the B. Cardinall, one at <hi>Lu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>erna,</hi> the other at <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burg.</hi> Se <hi>Guiſſano</hi> l. 6. c. 8. p. 265. col. 2.</p>
               <p>In the yeare 1583. Being
<pb n="304" facs="tcp:174734:165"/>made <hi>Viſitour Apoſtolicall</hi> of the valleyes of the <hi>Griſons</hi> infected with hereſy, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt other aſſiſtants of ſo good a worke, famous for their liues &amp; learning, he made choiſe of F. <hi>Achil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les Giliardo</hi> of the Society of Ieſus to accompany him in this iourney, dayly em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploying him in the expli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of Chriſtian beliefe. Se <hi>Guiſſano</hi> l. 7. c. 4. p. 300. col. 2. And being to place ſome good men in lieu of other ſcandalous Prieſts, in thoſe valleyes, for the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall profit of the inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants, he left behind him the <hi>Oblates</hi> of S. Ambroſe,
<pb n="305" facs="tcp:174734:165"/>an <hi>Order</hi> inſtituted by him ſelfe, and highly eſteemed by him, and ſome of the Society of Ieſus. Se <hi>Guiſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no,</hi> p. 302. col. 1.</p>
               <p>He cauſed a <hi>Catechiſme</hi> to be made by the ſaid F. <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiles Galiardo</hi> for the help and inſtruction of them of that Country, printed in the yeare following. Se <hi>Guiſſano</hi> l. 7. c. 5. pag. 305. col. 1.</p>
               <p>In the yeare 1584. Being ſollicited by certaine of the <hi>Griſons,</hi> to ſend thither ſome pious Preiſts, to aſſiſt them in matters of faith, &amp; good life, amongſt three, he made choiſe of, F. <hi>Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis
<pb n="306" facs="tcp:174734:166"/>Adorno</hi> was one, who, with the reſt, wrought much good amongſt them. So <hi>Guiſſano</hi> l. 7. cap 6 p. 307. c 2.</p>
               <p>The laſt month before his death, being to make, as his cuſtome was the <hi>ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall Exerciſes,</hi> he cauſed F. <hi>Franc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s Adorno</hi> to come to him, being directed, and obeying him, as a man of holy life, and long expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience in affayres of ſpirit, and direction of ſoules, whoſe helpe he ordinarly vſed in the like caſes. Se <hi>Guiſſano</hi> l. 7. c 11. p. 317 c. 1.</p>
               <p>In this holy recollection, in which before his death;
<pb n="307" facs="tcp:174734:166"/>he made the <hi>spirituall Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe,</hi> vnder the conduct of F. <hi>Adorno,</hi> he himſelfe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore day, brought a candle to the ſaid Father, that he afterwards might raiſe the reſt of his family, who by his order alſo made the ſayd Exerciſes, in the ſame place. And <hi>S. Charles</hi> bore ſo much reuerence to F. <hi>Adorno,</hi> that he came with great ſilence into his cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, leaſt otherwiſe he might wake him, and paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing by him bowed with reuerence to him, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding that often tymes he perceaued him to be a ſleepe. <hi>So Guiſſano</hi> lib. 7. col. 2.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="308" facs="tcp:174734:167"/>Paſſing by <hi>Arona,</hi> in his returne to <hi>Millan,</hi> and being inuited to ſee hunting by one Count <hi>Renato</hi> a kinſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of his, who had pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared to ſhew him ſport, he refuſed it, and tooke vp his lodging with the Fathers of the Society (ſee <hi>Guiſſano</hi> l. 7. c. 11. p. 321 c. 1) And in that Church celebrated his laſt Maſſe. Se <hi>Guiſſano,</hi> in the ſame place.</p>
               <p>In the laſt howers of his life, he tooke counſell of F. <hi>Adorno,</hi> in all things, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pending wholy of his obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, as his ſpirituall Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and Confeſſour, who aſſiſted him at his death,
<pb n="309" facs="tcp:174734:167"/>with a crucifix in his hand, putting him in mind of heauenly things. Se <hi>Guiſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no</hi> l. 7. c. 12. p. 322. c. 1. And 323. c. 2. And c. 14. p. 329. c. 1. And l. 8. c. 3. p. 359. col. 1.</p>
               <p>When F. <hi>Adorno</hi> of the Society of <hi>Ieſus,</hi> who aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted <hi>S. Charles</hi> at his death, in the quality of his Ghoſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Father, was returned to his Colledge, after the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſe of the ſaint, the ſame night <hi>S. Charles</hi> appeared to him, clad in his Biſhops ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bes, &amp; with a countenance and face pleaſant, and ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning with glory, ſpake to him thus: <hi>Our Lord ſendeth
<pb n="310" facs="tcp:174734:168"/>death, and our Lord reſtored life. I am well, and you shall ſoone follow me.</hi> And it came to paſſe accordingly, that within few moneths after F. <hi>Adorno</hi> deceaſed at <hi>Genua</hi> with an opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſanctity. So <hi>Guiſſano</hi> l. 9. cap. 14. p. 329 col. 1.</p>
               <p>And it is a great argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the extraordinary opinion <hi>S. Charles</hi> had of the inſtitution and gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nement of the Society of <hi>Ieſus,</hi> that as a familiar freind of the Society, and one who reuerenced that <hi>Order,</hi> he would haue his owne houſhould, as neare as was poſſible, ordered ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording
<pb n="311" facs="tcp:174734:168"/>to the Rules and Inſtitutions of the Society, giuing the names and epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thetes vſuall in the Society to diuers Officers of his owne houſhould, of which thing ſee <hi>Guiſſano</hi> in his ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond booke, third, fourth and fifth Chapter, and elſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="chapter">
               <head>Certaine Spirituall admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of S. <hi>Ignatius.</hi>
               </head>
               <head type="sub">CHAP. XXII.</head>
               <p>IT would exact a great volume to include all theſe ſpiritual admonitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, with which, as with ſo many pretious ſtones, the
<pb n="312" facs="tcp:174734:169"/>Bookes and ſundry Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles of <hi>S. Ignatius</hi> are ador<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. Some few of them therfore ſhall here be men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned and theſe in his owne words, that (omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting many others for bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uity ſake) theſe may cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpond to thoſe things which haue already been breifely related of his vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues and Miracles.</p>
               <p n="1">1. For as much as man is created to this end, that he may praiſe and reuerence his God, and by ſeruing of him, arriue at laſt to ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, &amp; that all other crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, vpon the face of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>arth are created for mans
<pb n="213" facs="tcp:174734:169"/>vſe, as meanes to aſſiſt him in the purſuit of this ayme of his creatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, it followeth that they are ſo farre forth to be made vſe of, or for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borne, as they further or hinder the proſecution of this end In which reſpect, we ought to carry our ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues with indifferency to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards all things created (as they are permitted and not prohibited to the freedome of our will) ſo that (as much as lyeth in vs) we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire not health rather then ſicknes, or prefer not riches before pouerty, honours before contempt, long life before ſhort: for it ſtandeth
<pb n="214" facs="tcp:174734:170"/>with reaſon, that in all things, we deſire and make choiſe of ſuch as lead vs to the end for which we were created.</p>
               <p n="2">2 Euery good Chriſtian ought to be readier to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpret in a good ſence any doubt full or obſcure pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of an other mans then to condemne it: and if he find the words not to be excuſed, let him examine the inte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tion of the ſpeaker, which if he find alſo to be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, led him reprehend him with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eekeneſſe: and if that ſuffice not, let him then lay hould of all other oportunityes, by which he
<pb n="215" facs="tcp:174734:170"/>may rectify his vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, and ſecure him from errour.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The firſt ſtep neceſſary to ſaluation is, that I abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely ſubmit my ſelfe to the obſeruance of Gods lawes, and that I willingly tranſgreſſe not againſt any diuine or human precept, which obligeth vnder paine of <hi>mortall</hi> ſinne, not though the gouernement of the whole world were propoſed to me for it, or the vttermoſt extremity of my life went vpon it.</p>
               <p>The ſecond ſtep is yet of greater perfection: that with a conſtant mind, I be
<pb n="216" facs="tcp:174734:171"/>equally inclined, where the honour of God, or oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of my good is equall, to riches, pouerty, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, contempt, ſhortnes or length of life. And that for no hope of human feli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city whatſoeuer or daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of my owne life, I euer be induced to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſent to the leaſt ſinne, though <hi>Veniall.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The third ſtep is of moſt abſolute and profund hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility: that hauing arriued to the other two degrees of perfection though the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of God were equall, without any aduantage, yet in more perfect imitation of Chriſt, that I rather chooſe
<pb n="217" facs="tcp:174734:171"/>with him, who was poore, contemned and ſcoffed at, to be poore, contemptible and eſteemed a foole, then to enioy wealth, honours and the reputation of wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</p>
               <p n="4">4. For the good choiſe of any thing, it is our duty to conſider, with a pure and ſincere intention, wherfore we were created, to wit, for Gods honour and our owne ſaluation. Which being ſo, ſuch things are only to be made choiſe of as leade vs to that end, for as much as the meanes euer ought to be ſubordinate to the end, not the end to the
<pb n="318" facs="tcp:174734:172"/>meanes. By which it appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth that they are in an er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, who reſolue princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally to marry, or ſeeke af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſome Eccleſiaſticall of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice or benefice, and then to ſerue God, prepoſterouſly confounding the end with the meanes, &amp; not tending directly towards God, but labouring indirectly to wine him to their peruerſe intentions. A quite contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry courſe is to be taken, by propoſing firſt to our ſelues the honour of God, as our ayme, and then making choice of marriage or Preiſthood, and all other thinges, as they are ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned,
<pb n="319" facs="tcp:174734:172"/>or tend to that end. Wherfore nothing ſhould moue vs to the vſe or for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearance of any meane, till firſt we haue had a particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar regard, as well of the honour of God, as of our owne ſaluation.</p>
               <p n="5">5. For the good choiſe of a ſtate of life, or of any other courſe (whether it be matter of deliberation of beſtowing money vpon my kindred, or others, to whom I haue any tyes of freindſhip, or any other thing, which by circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances may proue good or bed, it infinitely importeth me to conſider, if a man
<pb n="320" facs="tcp:174734:173"/>whom I had neuer ſeene, &amp; a mere ſtranger to me, yet one to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I wiſh all kind of perfection, ſhould oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curre, with the like doubts concerning choiſe or ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, what I would coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell him to do, and what choiſe to make, for the greater glory of God, and perfection of his ſoule. Which when I haue conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, let me reſolue to do my ſelf what I would coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell an other.</p>
               <p>I muſt likewiſe caſt with my ſelfe, what courſe I would rather wiſh I had ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, in the preſent action or deliberation, if I were
<pb n="321" facs="tcp:174734:173"/>now at the point of death; &amp; accordingly now I ought to reſolue vpon the ſame.</p>
               <p>Moreouer I muſt conſider what courſe, in this particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar I ſhould deſire to haue taken, when I ſhall ſtand at the tribunall of God to be iudged. Which, when I haue conſidered, let me re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolue now vpon the ſame, that I may then be more ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Nothing ought to be concluded or reſolued in tyme of tentation or deſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, touching our ſtate of life, or good purpoſes; but muſt be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtant to that which we formerly deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined
<pb n="322" facs="tcp:174734:174"/>in tyme of diuine conſolation. For as a ſoule when ſhe e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>oyeth diuine conſolation, is not guided by her owne inſtinct, but by that of the good ſpirit, ſo in tyme of deſolation ſhe is ruled by the ill ſpirit, by whoſe inſtigation, nothing is right done.</p>
               <p n="7">7. A man enioying the conſolation of God, ought to conſider how he will af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards carry himſelfe when he ſhall chance to fall againe into deſolation, and then in tyme put on a reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution &amp; ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth to breake the force of it when it ſhall come.</p>
               <p n="8">
                  <pb n="323" facs="tcp:174734:174"/>8. Euen as a woman ray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling or conteſting with a man, if ſhe perceaue him make reſiſtance with a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute &amp; conſtant browe, relenteth and quitteth him, but if ſhe diſcouer him to be timerous or deſirous to auoid her, ſetteth vpon him a freſh, with extreame inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency; ſo the Deuill is wont to looſe hart and faile in his reſolution, when he findeth a ſpirituall Champion, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely and with a feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe and vndaunted ſpirit, withſtand his tentations. But if he diſcouer feare in the firſt brunt or encou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ter, or argue want of courage, no ſauage beaſt, vpon the
<pb n="324" facs="tcp:174734:175"/>face of the earth, is more barbarous or vntamed.</p>
               <p n="9">9. Our enemy imitateth the example of ſome volup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous louer, who intending to debauch a yong Maide or Wife, deſireth to haue his words and counſells concealed, fearing, or di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruſting nothing more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that the Maiden ſhould diſcouer his deſigne to her Father, or the Wife to her Huſband, becauſe then he knoweth his labours and endeauours are in vayne. In the ſame ſort the Deuill ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly endeauoreth that the ſoule which he inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth to circumuent or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trap, keepe his falſe ſugge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions
<pb n="325" facs="tcp:174734:175"/>vnder the ſeale of ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crecy: and taketh it for a foule affront to haue his deſignes reuealed, either to a Ghoſtly Father, or any ſpirituall man, for then he is aſſured to faile in his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation, and receaue an vtter ouerthrow.</p>
               <p n="10">10. He is wont, in like manner, to imitate a Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral of an Army, who inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to giue on, or aſſault a <hi>Fort</hi> beſieged, maketh firſt his diſcouery of the ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth of the place, falling on there, where he findeth it leaſt fortified. In the ſame ſort the Deuill laying ſiege to our ſoule, ſubtily en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth
<pb n="326" facs="tcp:174734:176"/>with what vertues morrall or Theologicall the ſoule is fortified, or voyde of, and in that place eſpecially placeth the force of his aſſault, hoping there to ouerthrow vs, where he diſcouereth vs leaſt proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and ſlighteſt guarded.</p>
               <p n="11">11. It is a cuſtome of the ill ſpirit to transforme him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf into an Angell of light, and diſcouering the pious intentions of our ſoule, to ſeeme at firſt to approue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, beginning afterwards to intice vs to his peruerſe deſires: for he ſeemeth to cheriſh, and comply with the pious intentions of the
<pb n="327" facs="tcp:174734:176"/>ſoule, but in concluſion, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gageth her by little and little, and entangleth her in his ſnares.</p>
               <p n="12">12. We ought to take a curious account of our thoughts concerning the beginnings, the middle, and the end; which three cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances if they be right, it is an argument that the good Angel inſpireth thoſe thoughts: but if by diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe and due examinatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, we diſcouer &amp; follow any thing, which either in it ſelf is ill, or draweth vs fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> any good, or forceth vs to a leſſe good then the ſoule in her firſt ſearch, was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolued
<pb n="328" facs="tcp:174734:177"/>to haue followed; or tireth, diſturbeth, or affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cteth our ſoule in lieu of the quiet, peace; and tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quillity it enioyed, it is an euident ſigne that the ill ſpirit is author of thoſe thoughts, as an enemy to our good.</p>
               <p n="13">13. <hi>S. Ignatius</hi> was wont to ſay that Innocency and Sanctity of life were rare things in themſelues, and by many degrees to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred before all things whatſoeuer: but except they were ſeaſoned with wiſdome, &amp; a certaine me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod in treating with men, that they were lame &amp; im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect,
<pb n="329" facs="tcp:174734:177"/>and not fit to guide others: &amp; that in matter of gouernme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, great wiſdome conjoined with meane ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctity, was of more force, then eminent ſanctity con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyned with leſſe wiſdome.</p>
               <p n="14">14. He was wont to ſay that the familiarity of all women whatſoeuer ought to be auoided, euen of ſuch women as appeared ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall, but eſpecially of ſuch whoſe yeares and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dition might import greateſt dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> out of which, for the moſt part either ſmoke or flame followeth.</p>
               <p n="15">15. He ſaid it was a thing full of daunger to direct all
<pb n="330" facs="tcp:174734:178"/>men the ſame way in a ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual courſe, or to meaſure other me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by ones ſelf; or to reduce others to the ſame method of liuing and pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, which a man findeth profitable in himſelfe.</p>
               <p n="16">16. He was wont to ſay, that the proficience a man made in the way of vertue, was not to be gathered out of the face or countenance, or out of the eaſines or good natural diſpoſition of a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or out of continual prayers or often recollection, but out of the victory of ones ſelf, &amp; ſuppreſſing of diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinate paſſions rebelling againſt reaſon; &amp; principal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="331" facs="tcp:174734:178"/>out of the peace &amp; equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the mind, immouea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in all ſuddaine &amp; deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate affayres. Inſomuch, that though he himſelfe were eminent in the holy guift of prayer, yet he euer preferred the ſpirit of mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tification as they terme it, before the ſpirit of ſpecula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or prayer. For as in matter of eloquence, in which there is a neceſſity as wel of art as practiſe, me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of vnderſtanding attribute much more to practiſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> precept; ſo in the purſuit of vertues, in which as well ſpeculation as action is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite, much more profit
<pb n="332" facs="tcp:174734:179"/>is made by practiſe &amp; exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by mere ſpeculatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
               <p n="17">17. He ſaid it was infinite beneficial for the fortunate ſucceſſe of buſineſſes, that in the vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding of pious actions, a man ſo much rely vpon the deſired aſſiſtance of God, as if no human help were to be expected; and on the other ſide, ſo farre make vſe of human reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyes, which are lawfull, as if no diuine helpe or aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance were requiſite.</p>
               <p n="18">18. He ſaid the Ghoſtly Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers and Superiours of other men ought to imitate the Angells, who in preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing the ſoules committed
<pb n="333" facs="tcp:174734:179"/>to their charge, omit no ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary diligence, yet what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer happen, looſe no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing notwithſtanding of their peace and happines.</p>
               <p n="19">19. He aduiſed men cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lericke by nature, to haue a ſpeciall care how they treate with collerick per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, in regard that diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions eaſily ariſe. In which reſpect he counſelled ſuch me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> often to premeditate &amp; caſt with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues, how to auoid that inconuenience: which courſe he held ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary not in men of ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty diſpoſitions only, but in all men for the conqueſt of all other vices.</p>
               <p n="20">
                  <pb n="334" facs="tcp:174734:180"/>20. He was wont to ſay, that if a man demaund any thing at thy hands vnbeſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g thy perſon, thou ough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt to moderate thy indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnation, &amp; ſo to carry thy ſelf, that thou both deny what is ſought or demaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded at thy hands, and yet alſo part freinds with him who demaundeth it.</p>
               <p n="21">21. He ſaid it was the Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of a Religious man, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to gaine me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to Chriſt, by diſſwading them from a Courtiers life, then to be a meanes to bring any man to the Court.</p>
               <p n="22">22. The B. Father was wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to ſay, that if Miracles were
<pb n="335" facs="tcp:174734:180"/>to be ſought at the ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds of Almighty God, men ought to demaund more &amp; more conuincing Miracles tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the obſeruance of the <hi>Commaunds</hi> only, then tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the obſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce &amp; fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing of the <hi>Counſells:</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe Chriſt our Sauiour did plainely perſwade vs to follow his <hi>Counſells,</hi> and on the other ſide, demo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtrated the great difficulties, &amp; eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent danger of ſaluation, in the enioyning &amp; poſſeſſing of riches. <hi>Matth.</hi> 19. v. 23.24.</p>
               <p n="23">23. It is a thing infinitely beneficiall to the aduaunce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and proficience of a ſpirituall life, wholy, &amp; not
<pb n="336" facs="tcp:174734:181"/>in part to abhorre al things which the world affecteth and embraceth, &amp; to couet with all our powers, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer Chriſt our Sauiour loued &amp; approued; to wit, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tumelies, falſe witneſſes, the ſufferance of iniuries, to be reputed a foole: but this without any cauſe gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen on our parts.</p>
               <p n="24">24. That we may the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter arriue to this degree of perfection, each man ought to employ his beſt indea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uours, to ſeek in our Lord, the greater abnegation and mortification of himſelf, as much as poſſible in al thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gs.</p>
            </div>
            <closer>Ad maiorem Dei gloriam.</closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:174734:181"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
